<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE archimedes SYSTEM "../dtd/archimedes.dtd">
<archimedes xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">      <info>
        <author>Pseudo Euclid</author>
        <title>de ponderoso et levi</title>
        <date>2002</date>
        <place>MPIWG</place>
       <translator>PMcL</translator>
        <lang>en</lang>
        <cvs_file>eucli_ponde_061_en.xml</cvs_file>
        <cvs_version/>
        <locator>061.xml</locator>
</info>      <text>
<pb xlink:href="061/01/001.jpg"/><front>

<section><p type="head"><s id="id.000001">The book of Euclid on the heavy and the light  and on the comparison of bodies to one another</s></p></section></front><body><chap><p type="main">
<s id="id.000002">1. Bodies are equal in size that fill equal places.</s></p><p>
<s id="id.000003">2. And which fill unequal places are said to be different in size.</s></p><p>
<s id="id.000004">3. And what are said to be great among bodies, are said to be ample among places.</s></p><p>
<s id="id.000005">4. Bodies are equal in force whose motions in equal times are through equal places in the same air or in the same water.</s></p><p>
<s id="id.000006">5. And those that traverse equal places in different times are said to be different in fortitude.</s></p><p>
<s id="id.000007">6. And what is the larger in force is the smaller in time.</s></p><p>
<s id="id.000008">7. Bodies are of the same kind of which in equals the force is equal.</s></p><p>
<s id="id.000009">8. If bodies equal in magnitude are different in force in respect to the same water or air, they are different in kind.</s></p><p>
<s id="id.000010">9. And the more solid [dense] is the stronger.</s></p></chap><chap><p>
<s id="id.000011">1. Of bodies that pass through unequal places in equal times, that which passes through the larger place is of larger force.</s></p><p>
<s id="id.000012">2. If of two bodies of the same kind one is the multiple of the other, then its force will be similarly in respect to the force of the other.</s></p><p>
<s id="id.000013">3. Of bodies of the same kind there is one proportion in size and power.</s></p><p>
<s id="id.000014">4. Bodies of which each is equipollent in kind to one, are of the same kind.</s></p><p>
<s id="id.000015">5. When there is one proportion in the size and force of bodies, they are of the same kind.</s></p></chap></body></text></archimedes>
