<?xml version="1.0"?>
<archimedes xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" >      <info>
	<author>Foscarini, Paolo Antonio</author>
	<title>An Epistle to Fantoni</title>
	<date>1661</date>
	<place>London</place>
	<translator>Salusbury, Thomas</translator>
	<lang>en</lang>
	<cvs_file>fosca_epist_067_en_1661.xml</cvs_file>
	<cvs_version></cvs_version>
	<locator>067.xml</locator>
</info>      <text>          <front> 

<section>	<pb xlink:href="067/01/001.jpg"></pb><p type="head">


<s>AN <lb></lb>EPISTLE <lb></lb>Of the Reverend Father <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>PAOLO ANTONIO FOSCARINI,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>A CARMELITE; <lb></lb>Concerning <lb></lb>The <emph type="italics"></emph>PYTHAGORIAN<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>COPERNICAN<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Opinion <lb></lb>OF <lb></lb>The Mobility of the <emph type="italics"></emph>EARTH,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>AND <lb></lb>Stability of the <emph type="italics"></emph>SVN;<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>AND <lb></lb>Of the New Syſteme or Conſtitution <lb></lb>OF THE <lb></lb>WORLD.</s></p><p type="head">

<s>IN WHICH, <lb></lb>The Authorities of <emph type="italics"></emph>SACRED SCRIPTVRE,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>and <emph type="italics"></emph>ASSERTIONS<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> of <emph type="italics"></emph>DIVINES,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>commonly alledged againſt this Opinion, <lb></lb>are Reconciled.</s></p><p type="head">

<s>WRITTEN <lb></lb>To the moſt Reverend FATHER, <lb></lb>SEBASTIANO FANTONI, <lb></lb>General of the Order of CARMELITES.</s></p><p type="head">

<s><emph type="italics"></emph>Engliſhed from the Original,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>BY <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>THOMAS SALVSBVRIE.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="head">

<s><emph type="italics"></emph>So quis indiget ſapientia, poſtulet <lb></lb>à Deo.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Jacobi 1. verſu. 5.</s></p><p type="head">

<s><emph type="italics"></emph>Optavi, &amp; datus eſt mihi ſenſus.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>Sapientiæ 7. verſu. </s>

<s>7.</s></p><p type="head">

<s><emph type="italics"></emph>LONDON,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>Printed by WILLIAM LEYBOURN, MDCLXI.</s></p><pb xlink:href="067/01/002.jpg"></pb>       </section>  </front>          <body>            <chap>


<pb xlink:href="067/01/003.jpg" pagenum="473"></pb><p type="head">

<s>To the Moſt <lb></lb>Reverend Father <lb></lb>SEBASTIANO FANTONI, <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>General of the Order of<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>CARMELITES.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>In obedience to the command of the No­<lb></lb>ble <emph type="italics"></emph>Signore Vincenzo Carraffa,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> a Neapo­<lb></lb>litan, and Knight of S. <emph type="italics"></emph>John of Jeru­<lb></lb>ſalem,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> (a perſon, to ſpeak the truth, of <lb></lb>ſo great Merit, that in him Nobility of <lb></lb>Birth, Affability of Manners, Univerſal <lb></lb>knowledge of Arts and things, Piety <lb></lb>and Vertue do all contend for prehemi­<lb></lb>nence) I reſolved with my ſelf to un­<lb></lb>dertake the Defence of the Writings of the New, or rather Re­<lb></lb>newed, and from the Duſt of Oblivion (in which it hath long <lb></lb>lain hid) lately Revived Opinion, <emph type="italics"></emph>Of the Mobility of the Earth, <lb></lb>and Stability of the Sun,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> in times paſt found out firſt by <emph type="italics"></emph>Pytha­<lb></lb>goras,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and at laſt reduced into Practice by <emph type="italics"></emph>Copernicus<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; who like­<lb></lb>wiſe hath deduced the Poſition of the Syſteme and Conſtitution <lb></lb>of the World and its parts from that Hypotheſis: on which <lb></lb>Subject I have formerly writ to You, Moſt Reverend Sir: But <lb></lb>in regard I am bound for <emph type="italics"></emph>Rome<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> to preach there by your Com­<lb></lb>mand; and ſince this Speculation may ſeem more proper for a­<lb></lb>nother Treatiſe, to wit, a Volume of <emph type="italics"></emph>Coſmography,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> which I am <lb></lb>in hand with, and which I am daily buſie about, that it may <lb></lb>come forth in company with my <emph type="italics"></emph>Compendium of the Liberal Arts,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>which I have already finiſhed, rather than now to diſcuſs it by it <lb></lb>ſelf, I thought to forbear, imparting what I have done for the <lb></lb>preſent; Yet I was deſirous to give, in the mean time, a brief ac­<lb></lb>count of this my Determination, and to ſhew You, Moſt Reve­<lb></lb>rend Father, (to whom I owe all my indeavours, and my very <lb></lb>ſelf) the Foundations on which this Opinion may be grounded, <lb></lb>leaſt, whilſt otherwiſe it is favoured with much probability, it be <lb></lb>found in reality to be extreamly repugnant (as at firſt ſight it 


<pb xlink:href="067/01/004.jpg" pagenum="474"></pb>ſeems) not onely to Phyſical Reaſons, and Common Principles <lb></lb>received on all hands (which cannot do ſo much harm) but alſo <lb></lb>(which would be of far worſe conſequence) to many Authori­<lb></lb>ties of ſacred Scripture: Upon which account many at their <lb></lb>firſt looking into it, explode it as the moſt fond Paradox and <lb></lb>Monſtrous <emph type="italics"></emph>Capriccio<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> that ever was heard of. </s>

<s>Which thing pro­<lb></lb>ceeds only from an antiquated and long confirmed Cuſtome, <lb></lb>which hath ſo hardened men in, and habituated them to Vul­<lb></lb>gar, Plauſible, and for that cauſe by all men (aſwell learned as <lb></lb>unlearned) Approved Opinions, that they cannot be removed <lb></lb>one ſtep from them: So great is the force of Cuſtome (which <lb></lb>not unfitly is ſtiled a ſecond Nature) prevailing over the whole <lb></lb>World, that touching things men are rather pleaſed with, de­<lb></lb>lighted in, and deſirous of thoſe, which, though evil and obnox­<lb></lb>ious, are by uſe made familiar to them, than ſuch, wherewith, <lb></lb>though better, they are not accuſtomed and acquainted. </s>

<s>So in <lb></lb>like manner, and that chiefly, in <emph type="italics"></emph>Opinions,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> which when once they <lb></lb>are rooted in the Mind, men ſtart at, and reject all others <lb></lb>whatſoever; not only thoſe that are contrary to, but even all <lb></lb>that ever ſo little diſagree with or vary from theirs, as harſh to <lb></lb>the Ear, diſcoloured to the Eye, unpleaſant to the Smell, nauſe­<lb></lb>ous to the Taſt, rough to the Touch. </s>

<s>And no wonder: For <lb></lb>Phyſical Truths are ordinarily judged and conſidered by men, <lb></lb>not according to their Eſſence, but according to the preſcript of <lb></lb>ſome one whoſe deſcription or definition of them gaines him <lb></lb>Authority amongſt the vulgar. </s>

<s>Which authority nevertheleſs <lb></lb>(ſince &#039;tis no more than humane) ought not to be ſo eſteemed, as <lb></lb>that that which doth manifeſtly appear to the contrary, whether <lb></lb>from better Reaſons lately found out, or from Senſe it ſelf, ſhould <lb></lb>for its ſake be contemned and ſlighted; Nor is Poſterity ſo to be <lb></lb>confined, but that it may, and dares, not only proceed farther, <lb></lb>but alſo bring to light better and truer Experiments than thoſe <lb></lb>which have been delivered to us by the Ancients. </s>

<s>For the <emph type="italics"></emph>Ge­<lb></lb>nius&#039;s<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> of the Antients, as in Inventions they did not much ſur­<lb></lb>paſs the Wits of our times; ſo for the perfecting of Inventions <lb></lb>this Age of ours ſeems not only to equal, but far to excell former <lb></lb>Ages; Knowledge, whether in the Liberal or Mechanical Arts, <lb></lb>daily growing to a greater height. </s>

<s>Which Aſſertion might be <lb></lb>eaſily proved, were it not that in ſo clear a caſe, there would be <lb></lb>more danger of obſcuring, than hopes of illuſtrating it with any <lb></lb>farther light.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>But (that I may not wholly be ſilent in this point) have not the <lb></lb>ſeveral Experiments of Moderns, in many things, ſtopped the <lb></lb>mouth of Venerable Antiquity, and proved many of their great­<lb></lb>teſt and weightieſt Opinions, to be vain and falſe? </s>

<s>The Doctrine 


<pb xlink:href="067/01/005.jpg" pagenum="475"></pb>of the <emph type="italics"></emph>Antipodes<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> by many of the Antients of approved Wiſ­<lb></lb>dome and Learning was held a Paradox no leſs abſurd than this <lb></lb>Our Opinion of the <emph type="italics"></emph>Earths Motion<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> may ſeem to be; as likewiſe <lb></lb>that of the <emph type="italics"></emph>Habitableneſſe of the Torrid Zone<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>: Of theſe Opini­<lb></lb>ons, the firſt was accounted unpoſſible by many, but the latter <lb></lb>was abſolutely denyed by the unanimous conſent of all: But <lb></lb>later Authors (to the great felicity and perpetual Glory of <lb></lb>their Age) have, not ſo much by Authority, as by accurate <lb></lb>diligence and indefatigable ſtudy to finde out the truth, pro­<lb></lb>ved them both to be undoubtedly true. </s>

<s>Thus I affirm that <lb></lb>the Antients were deceived, and that in too lightly challenging <lb></lb>Credid and Authority for their Inventions, they diſcovered too <lb></lb>much folly. </s>

<s>Here for brevities ſake I paſs by many Dreams <lb></lb>lately detected, both of <emph type="italics"></emph>Ariſtotle<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and other of the antient Philo­<lb></lb>ſophers; who in all likelihood if they had dived into the Obſer­<lb></lb>vations of Modern Writers, and underſtood their Reaſons, would, <lb></lb>by changing their Judgements, have given them the precedency, <lb></lb>and would have ſubſcribed to their manifeſt Truth. </s>

<s>Hereby we <lb></lb>ſee that we are not to have ſo high a reſpect for the Antiens, that <lb></lb>whatever they aſſert ſhould be taken upon truſt, and that Faith <lb></lb>ſhould be given to their ſayings, as if they were Oracles and <lb></lb>Truths ſent down from Heaven. </s>

<s>But yet (which indeed is <lb></lb>chiefly to be regarded in theſe matters) if any thing be found out <lb></lb>that is repugnant to Divine Authority, or to the Sacred Leaves, <lb></lb>that were dictated by the Holy Ghoſt, and by His Inſpiration <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg874"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>expounded by the Holy Doctors of the Church, in this caſe not <lb></lb>onely Humane Reaſon, but even Senſe it ſelf is to ſubmitt: <lb></lb>which, though by all manner of weighty Conditions and circum­<lb></lb>ſtances it ſhould hold forth any thing contrary to Divine Autho­<lb></lb>rity, (which indeed is ſo plain, that there is no way left to evade <lb></lb>the right un erſtanding of it) yet is it to be rejected; and we <lb></lb>muſt conclude our ſelves deceived by it, and believe that that is <lb></lb>not true which Senſe and Reaſon repreſents unto us: For, however <lb></lb>we judge of things, we have, both in this and all other caſes, a <lb></lb>more certain knowledge, which proceeds from Divine Faith; as <lb></lb>S. <emph type="italics"></emph>Peter<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> hath moſt excellently expreſt it: Who though with his <lb></lb>Senſes he ſaw, and perceived the Glory of our Lord in his <lb></lb>Transfiguration, and heard his words manifeſting his great Pow­<lb></lb>er, yet nevertheleſs all theſe things compared with the Light of <lb></lb>Faith, he adds: ^{*}<emph type="italics"></emph>We have alſo a more ſure word of Prophecy,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> &amp;c. <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg875"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>Wherefore ſince this Opinion of <emph type="italics"></emph>Pythagoras<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>Copernicus<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> hath <lb></lb>entred upon the Stage of the World in ſo ſtrange a Dreſs, and at <lb></lb>the firſt appearance (beſides the reſt) doth ſeem to oppoſe ſun­<lb></lb>dry Authorities of Sacred Scripture, it hath (this being granted) <lb></lb>been juſtly rejected of all men as a meer abſurdity.</s></p>


<pb xlink:href="067/01/006.jpg" pagenum="476"></pb><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg874"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>Faith is more <lb></lb>certain, than ei­<lb></lb>ther Senſe or Rea­<lb></lb>ſon.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg875"></margin.target>* 2 Pet. </s>

<s>1. 19.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>But yet becauſe the common Syſteme of the World deviſed by <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Ptolomy<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> hath hitherto ſatisfied none of the Learned, hereupon a <lb></lb>ſuſpicion is riſen up amongſt all, even <emph type="italics"></emph>Ptolemy&#039;s<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> followers them­<lb></lb>ſelves, that there muſt be ſome other Syſteme, which is more true <lb></lb>than this of <emph type="italics"></emph>Ptolemy<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; For although the <emph type="italics"></emph>Phœnomena<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> of Celeſtial <lb></lb>Bodys may ſeem to be generally reſolved by this Hypotheſis, yet <lb></lb>they are found to be involved with many difficulties, and refer­<lb></lb>red to many devices; as namely of Orbes of ſundry Forms and <lb></lb>Figures, Epicicles, Equations, Differences, Excentricks, andinnu­<lb></lb>merable ſuch like fancies and Chymæra&#039;s which ſavour of the <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Ens Rationis<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> of Logicians, rather than of any <emph type="italics"></emph>Realem Eſſentiam.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>Of which kinde is that of the <emph type="italics"></emph>Rapid Motion,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> than which I finde <lb></lb>not any thing that can be more weakly grounded, and more eaſi­<lb></lb>ly controverted and diſproved: And ſuch is that conceit of the <lb></lb>^{*} Heaven void of Stars, moving the inferior Heavens or Orbes: <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg876"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>All which are introduced upon occaſion of the variety of the <lb></lb>Motions of Celeſtial Bodyes, which ſeemed impoſſible, by any <lb></lb>other way, to be reduced to any certain and determinate Rule. <lb></lb></s>

<s>So that the Aſſertors of that common Opinion, freely confeſs, <lb></lb>that in deſcribing the Worlds Syſteme, they cannot as yet diſco­<lb></lb>ver, or teach the true Hypotheſis thereof: But that their endea­<lb></lb>vours are onely to finde out, amongſt many things, what is moſt <lb></lb>agreeable with truth, and may, upon better and more accomo­<lb></lb>date Reaſons, anſwer the Celeſtial <emph type="italics"></emph>Phœnomena.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg876"></margin.target>* Or <emph type="italics"></emph>Primum<lb></lb>Mobile.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>Since that, the Teleſcope (an Optick Invention) hath been found <lb></lb>out, by help of which, many remarkable things in the Heavens, <lb></lb>moſt worthy to be known, and till then unthought of, were diſ­<lb></lb>covered by manifeſt ſenſation; as for inſtance, That the Moon is <lb></lb>Mountainous; <emph type="italics"></emph>Venus<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>Saturn<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Tricorporeal; and <emph type="italics"></emph>Jupiter<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>Quadricorporeal: Likewiſe that in the <emph type="italics"></emph>Via Lactea,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> in the <emph type="italics"></emph>Ple­<lb></lb>iades,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and in the Stars called <emph type="italics"></emph>Nobuloſœ<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> there are many Stars, and <lb></lb>thoſe of the greateſt Magnitude which are by turns adjacent to <lb></lb>one another; and in the end it hath diſcovered to us, new fixed <lb></lb>Stars, new planets, and new Worlds. </s>

<s>And by this ſame Inſtru­<lb></lb>ment it appears very probable, that <emph type="italics"></emph>Venus<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>Mercury<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> do not <lb></lb>move properly about the Earth, but rather about the Sun; and <lb></lb>that the Moon alone moveth about the Earth. </s>

<s>What therefore <lb></lb>can be inferred from hence, but that the Sun doth ſtand immo­<lb></lb>vable in the Centre, and that the Earth, with the other Celeſtial <lb></lb>Orbes, is circumvolved about it? </s>

<s>Wherefore by this and many <lb></lb>other Reaſons it appears, That the Opinion of <emph type="italics"></emph>Pythagor as<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Copernicus<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> doth not diſagree with Aſtronomical and Coſmogra­<lb></lb>phical Principles; yea, that it carryeth with it a great likelihood <lb></lb>and probability of Truth: Whereas amongſt the ſo many ſeve­<lb></lb>ral Opinions, that deviate from the common Syſteme, and deviſe 


<pb xlink:href="067/01/007.jpg" pagenum="477"></pb>others, ſuch as were thoſe of <emph type="italics"></emph>Plato, Calippus, Eudoxus<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; and ſince <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg877"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>them of <emph type="italics"></emph>Averroe, ^{*} Cardanus, Fracaſtorius,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and others both Anti­<lb></lb>ent and Modern, there is not one found that is more facile, more <lb></lb>regularly ahd determinately, accommodated to the <emph type="italics"></emph>Phœnomena<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>and Motions of the Heavens, without <emph type="italics"></emph>Epicycles, Excentrix, Ho­<lb></lb>mocentricks<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Deferents, and the ſupputation of the Rapid Motion. <lb></lb></s>

<s>And this Hypotheſis hath been aſſerted for true, not onely by <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Pythagoras,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and, after him, by <emph type="italics"></emph>Copernicus,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> but by many famous <lb></lb>men, as namely, <emph type="italics"></emph>Heraclitus,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>Ecphantus, Pythagoreans,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> all the <lb></lb>Diſciples of that Sect, <emph type="italics"></emph>Miceta<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> of <emph type="italics"></emph>Syracuſe, Martianus Capella,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <lb></lb>many more. </s>

<s>Amongſt whom, thoſe (as we have ſaid) that <lb></lb>have attempted the finding out of New Syſtemes (for they refu­<lb></lb>ſed both this of <emph type="italics"></emph>Pythagoras,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and that of <emph type="italics"></emph>Ptolemy)<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> are numberleſs: <lb></lb>who yet notwithſtanding allowed this Opinion of <emph type="italics"></emph>Pythagoras<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> to <lb></lb>carry with it much probability, and indirectly confirmed it; inaſ­<lb></lb>much as that they rejected the common one as imperfect, defe­<lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg878"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>ctive, and attended with many contradictions and difficulties. <lb></lb></s>

<s>Amongſt theſe may be numbered Father ^{*} <emph type="italics"></emph>Clavius,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> a moſt learn­<lb></lb>ed Jeſuite; who, although he refutes the Syſteme of <emph type="italics"></emph>Pythagoras,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>yet acknowledgeth the Levity of the common Syſteme, and he <lb></lb>ingeniouſly confeſſeth, that for the removal of difficulties, in which <lb></lb>the common Syſteme will not ſerve the turn, Aſtronomers are <lb></lb>forced to enquire after another Syſteme, to the diſcovery of <lb></lb>which, he doth very earneſtly exhort them.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg877"></margin.target>* Cardan de re­<lb></lb>rum variet. </s>

<s>Lib. 1. <lb></lb>Cap. 

1.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg878"></margin.target>* P. </s>

<s>Clavins in <lb></lb>ultima ſuor. </s>

<s>Ope­<lb></lb>rum editione.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>Now can there a better or more commodious Hypotheſis <lb></lb>be deviſed, than this of <emph type="italics"></emph>Copernicus,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>? </s>

<s>For <emph type="italics"></emph>t<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>his Cauſe many Mo­<lb></lb>dern Authors are induced to approve of, and follow it: but <lb></lb>with much hæſitancy, and fear, in regard that it ſeemeth in their <lb></lb>Opinion ſo to contradict the Holy Scriptures, as that it cannot <lb></lb>poſſibly be reconciled to them. </s>

<s>Which is the Reaſon that this <lb></lb>Opinion hath been long ſuppreſt, and is now entertained by men <lb></lb>in a modeſt manner, ad as it were with a veiled Face; according <lb></lb>to that advice of the Poet:</s></p><p type="main">

<s><emph type="italics"></emph>Judicium populi nunquam contempſeris unus,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s><emph type="italics"></emph>Ne nullis place as, dum vis contemnere multos.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>Upon conſideration of which, (out of my very great love to­<lb></lb>wards the Sciences, and my ardent defire to ſee the encreaſe and <lb></lb>perfection of them, and the Light of Truth freed from all Er­<lb></lb>rours and Obſcurities) I began to argue with my ſelf touching <lb></lb>this Point after this manner: This Opinion of the <emph type="italics"></emph>Pythagoreans<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>is either true, or falſe; If falſe, it ought not to be mentioned, and <lb></lb>deſerves not to be divulged: If true, it matters not, though it <lb></lb>contradict all, as well Philoſophers as Aſtronomers: And though <lb></lb>for its eſtabliſhment and reducement to uſe a new Philoſophy 


<pb xlink:href="067/01/008.jpg" pagenum="478"></pb>and Aſtronomy, (ſounded upon new Principles and Hypotheſe) <lb></lb>ſhould be conſtituted: For the Authority of Sacred Scripture <lb></lb>will not oppoſe it; neither doth one Truth contradict another. <lb></lb></s>

<s>If therefore the Opinion of <emph type="italics"></emph>Pythagoras<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> be true, without doubt <lb></lb>God hath diſpoſed and dictated the words of of Holy Writ in <lb></lb>ſuch a manner, that they may admit an apt ſenſe and reconcilia­<lb></lb>tion with that Hypotheſis. </s>

<s>Being moved by theſe Reaſons, and <lb></lb>the probability of the ſaid Opinion, I thought good to try whe­<lb></lb>ther Texts of Sacred Scripture might be expounded according to <lb></lb>Theological and Phyſical Principles, and might be reconciled to <lb></lb>it, ſo that (in regard that hitherto it hath been held probable) it <lb></lb>may in after times, coming without ſcruple to be acknowledged <lb></lb>for true, advance it ſelf, and appear in publick with an uncover­<lb></lb>ed Face, without any mans prohibition, and may lawfully and <lb></lb>freely hold a Sacred intelligence with Holy Truth, ſo earneſtly <lb></lb>coveted and commended by good Men. </s>

<s>Which deſigne, having hi­<lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg879"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>therto been undertaken by none that I know, wil, I am perſwaded, <lb></lb>be very acceptable to the Studious of theſe Learnings, eſpecially to <lb></lb>the moſt Learned <emph type="italics"></emph>Galilœo Galilœi,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> chief Mathematician to the <lb></lb>moſt Serene Grand Duke of <emph type="italics"></emph>Tuſcany,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>John Kepler,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> chief <lb></lb>Mathematician to his Sacred and invincible Majeſty, the Empe­<lb></lb>rour, and to all that Illuſtrious, and much to be commended Ac­<lb></lb>cademy of the <emph type="italics"></emph>Lynceans<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; whom, if I miſtake not, are all of this <lb></lb>Opinion. </s>

<s>Although I doubt not but they, and many other <lb></lb>Learned Men might eaſily have found out theſe or the like Re­<lb></lb>conciliations of Scriptural expreſſions; to whom nevertheleſs I <lb></lb>have thought fit (in reſpect of that profeſſion which I have under­<lb></lb>taken, upon the faith of my ſoul, and the propenſity that I have <lb></lb>towards Truth) to offer that of the Poet,</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg879"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>The Author <lb></lb>firſt Theologically <lb></lb>defendeth the <lb></lb>Earths Mobili­<lb></lb>ty, approved by <lb></lb>many of the Mo­<lb></lb>derns.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s><emph type="italics"></emph>Nullius addictus jur are in verba Magiſtri.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>And in teſtimony of my eſteem to them and all the Learned, <lb></lb>to communicate theſe my thoughts; confidently aſſuring my ſelf <lb></lb>that they will accept them, with a Candor equal to that where­<lb></lb>with I have written them.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>Therefore to come to the buſineſs: All Authorities of Di­<lb></lb>vine Writ which ſeem to oppoſe this Opinion, are reducible to <lb></lb>ſix Claſſes: The firſt is of thoſe that affirm the Earth to ſtand <lb></lb>ſtill, and not to move: as <emph type="italics"></emph>Pſal. </s>

<s>92. He framed the round World <lb></lb>ſo ſure, that it cannot be moved<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>: Alſo <emph type="italics"></emph>Pſal. </s>

<s>104. Who laid the <lb></lb>Foundations of the Earth, that it ſhould not be removed for ever<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>: <lb></lb>And <emph type="italics"></emph>Eccleſiaſtes 1. But the Earth abideth for ever<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>: And others <lb></lb>of the like ſenſe.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>The ſecond is of thoſe which atteſt the Sun to move, and 


<pb xlink:href="067/01/009.jpg" pagenum="479"></pb>Revolve about the Earth; as <emph type="italics"></emph>Pſal. </s>

<s>19. (b) In them hath be ſet a <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg880"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>Tabernacle for the Sun, which cometh forth as a Bridegroom out <lb></lb>of his chamber, and rejoyceth as a Gyant to run his Courſe. </s>

<s>It <lb></lb>cometh forth from the uttermoſt part of the Heaven, and runneth <lb></lb>about unto the end of it again; and there is nothing hid from the <lb></lb>heat thereof.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> And <emph type="italics"></emph>Eccleſiaſt. </s>

<s>1. The Sun riſeth, and the Sun go­<lb></lb>eth down, and haſteth to the place where be aroſe: it goeth towards <lb></lb>the South, and turneth about unto the North.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Whereupon the <lb></lb>Suns Retrogradation is mentioned as a Miracle, <emph type="italics"></emph>Iſaiah 38. The <lb></lb>Sun returned ten degrees.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> And <emph type="italics"></emph>Eccleſiaſticus 48. In his time the <lb></lb>Sun went backward, and lengthened the life of the King.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> And <lb></lb>for this reaſon it is related for a Miracle, in the Book of <emph type="italics"></emph>Joſbuah,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>that at the Prayers of that great Captain the Sun ſtood ſtill, its <lb></lb>motion being forbidden it, by him<emph type="italics"></emph>: Joſh.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>10. <emph type="italics"></emph>Sun ſtand thou <lb></lb>ſtill upon Gibeon.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Now if the Sun ſhould ſtand ſtill, and the <lb></lb>Earth move about it, its ſtation at that time was no Miracle; <lb></lb>and if <emph type="italics"></emph>Joſhuah<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> had intended, that the light of the day ſhould <lb></lb>have been prolonged by the Suns ſplendour, he would not have <lb></lb>ſaid, <emph type="italics"></emph>Sun ſtand thou ſtill,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> but rather <emph type="italics"></emph>Earth ſtand thou ſtill.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg880"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(b) Or<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> In Sole <lb></lb>poſuit tabernacu­<lb></lb>lum ſuum, <emph type="italics"></emph>accor­<lb></lb>ding to the Tran­<lb></lb>ſlation our Au­<lb></lb>thor followeth.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>The third Claſſis is of thoſe Authorities which ſay, that Hea­<lb></lb>ven is <emph type="italics"></emph>above,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and the Earth <emph type="italics"></emph>beneath<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; of which ſort is that place <lb></lb>of <emph type="italics"></emph>Joel, chap.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 2. cited by S. <emph type="italics"></emph>Peter,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> in <emph type="italics"></emph>Acts. </s>

<s>2. I will ſhew wonders <lb></lb>in Heaven above, and ſignes in the Earth beneath,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> with others of <lb></lb>the like purport. </s>

<s>Hereupon Chriſt at his Incarnation is ſaid to <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>come down from Heaven<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; and after his Reſurrection to have <emph type="italics"></emph>aſ­<lb></lb>cended up into heaven.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> But if the Earth ſhould move about <lb></lb>the Sun, it would be, as one may ſay, in Heaven, and conſe­<lb></lb>quently would rather be <emph type="italics"></emph>above<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Heaven than <emph type="italics"></emph>beneath<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> it. </s>

<s>And <lb></lb>this is confirmed; For that the Opinion which placeth the Sun in <lb></lb>the Centre, doth likewiſe place <emph type="italics"></emph>Mercury<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> above the Sun, and <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Venus<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> above <emph type="italics"></emph>Mercury<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; and the Earth above <emph type="italics"></emph>Venus,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> together <lb></lb>with the Moon, which revolves about the Earth, and therefore <lb></lb>the Earth, together with the Moon, is placed in the third Heaven. <lb></lb></s>

<s>If therefore in Spherical Bodies, as in the World, <emph type="italics"></emph>beneath<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> ſigni­<lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg881"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>fies no more than to be neer to the centre, and <emph type="italics"></emph>above,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> than to <lb></lb>approach the Circumference, it muſt needs follow, that for ma­<lb></lb>king good of Theological Poſitions concerning the Aſcenſion <lb></lb>and Deſcenſion of Chriſt, the Earth is to be placed in the cen­<lb></lb>tre, and the Sun, with the other Heavens in the Circumference; <lb></lb>and not according to <emph type="italics"></emph>Copernicus,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> whoſe Hypotheſis inverts this <lb></lb>Order: with which one cannot ſee how the true Aſcenſion and <lb></lb>Deſcenſion can be conſiſtent.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg881"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>In Spberieall <lb></lb>Bodies,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Deorſum <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>is the Centre, and<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>Surſum <emph type="italics"></emph>the Cir­<lb></lb>cumference.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>The fourth Claſſis is of thoſe Authorities which make Hell to <lb></lb>be in the Centre of the World, which is the Common Opinion <lb></lb>of Divines, and confirmed by this Reaſon, That ſince Hell (ta­


<pb xlink:href="067/01/010.jpg" pagenum="480"></pb>ken in its ſtrict denomination) ought to be in the loweſt part of <lb></lb>the World, and ſince that in a Sphere there is no part lower <lb></lb>then the Centre, Hell ſhall be, as it were, in the Centre of the <lb></lb>World, which being of a Spherical Figure, it muſt follow, that <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg882"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>Hell is either in the Sun (foraſmuch as it is ſuppoſed by this Hy­<lb></lb>potheſis to be in the Centre of the World) or elſe ſuppoſing <lb></lb>that Hell is in the Centre of the Earth, if the Earth ſhould move <lb></lb>about the Sun, it would neceſſarily enſue, that Hell, together <lb></lb>with the Earth, is in Heaven, and with it revolveth about the third <lb></lb>Heaven; than which nothing more abſurd can be ſaid or imagi­<lb></lb>ned.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg882"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>Hell is in the <lb></lb>centre of the <lb></lb>Earth, not of the <lb></lb>World.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>The fifth Claſſis, is of thoſe Authorities which alwayes op­<lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg883"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>poſe Heaven to the Earth, and ſo again the Earth to Heaven; as <lb></lb>if there were the ſame relation betwixt them, with that of the <lb></lb>Centre to the Circumference, and of the Circumference to the <lb></lb>Centre. </s>

<s>But if the Earth were in Heaven, it ſhould be on one <lb></lb>ſide thereof, and would not ſtand in the Middle, and conſequent­<lb></lb>ly there would be no ſuch relation betwixt them; which never­<lb></lb>theleſs do, not only in Sacred Writ, but even in Common Speech, <lb></lb>ever and every where anſwer to each other with a mutual Oppo­<lb></lb>fition. </s>

<s>Whence that of <emph type="italics"></emph>Geneſ. </s>

<s>1. In the beginning God created <lb></lb>the Heaven and the Earth<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>: and <emph type="italics"></emph>Pſal. </s>

<s>115. The Heaven, even <lb></lb>the Heavens are the Lords; but the Earth hath he given to the <lb></lb>Children of men:<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and our Saviour in that Prayer which he pre­<lb></lb>ſcribeth to us, <emph type="italics"></emph>Matth. </s>

<s>6. Thy will be done in Earth, as it is in <lb></lb>Heaven:<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and S. <emph type="italics"></emph>Paul, 1 Corinth. </s>

<s>15. The firſt man is of the <lb></lb>Earth, earthy; the ſecond man is of Heaven, heavenly:<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Coloſſ. </s>

<s>1. By him were all things created that are in Heaven, and <lb></lb>that are in Earth<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>: and again, <emph type="italics"></emph>Having made peace through the <lb></lb>Blood of his Croſſe for all things, whether they be things in Earth <lb></lb>or things in Heaven:<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>Chap. </s>

<s>3. Set your affections on things <lb></lb>above, not on things on the Earth<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; with innumerable other ſuch <lb></lb>like places. </s>

<s>Since therefore theſe two Bodies are alwayes mu­<lb></lb>tually oppoſed to each other, and Heaven, without all doubt, <lb></lb>referreth to the Circumference, it muſt of neceſſity follow, that <lb></lb>the Earth is to be adjudged the place of the Centre.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg883"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>Heaven and <lb></lb>Earth are always <lb></lb>mutually oppoſed <lb></lb>to each other.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>The ſixth and laſt Claſſis is of thoſe Authorities, which (being <lb></lb>rather of Fathers and Divines, than of the Sacred Scripture) ſay, <lb></lb>That the Sun, after the day of Judgment ſhall ſtand immoveable <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg884"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>in the Eaſt, and the Moon in the Weſt. </s>

<s>Which Station, if the <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Pythagorick<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Opinion hold true, ought rather to be aſcribed to <lb></lb>the Earth, than to the Sun; for if it be true, that the Earth doth <lb></lb>now move about the Sun, it is neceſſary that after the day of <lb></lb>Judgment it ſhould ſtand immoveable. </s>

<s>And truth is, if it muſt <lb></lb>ſubſiſt without motion in one conſtant place, there is no reaſon 


<pb xlink:href="067/01/011.jpg" pagenum="481"></pb>why it ſhould rather ſtand in one ſite of that Place than in ano­<lb></lb>ther, or why it ſhould rather turn one part of it than another to <lb></lb>the Sun, if ſo be that every of its parts without diſtinction, which <lb></lb>is deſtitute of the Suns light, cannot chooſe but be diſmal, and <lb></lb>much worſe affected than that part which is illuminated. </s>

<s>Hence <lb></lb>alſo would ariſe many other abſurdities beſides theſe.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg884"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>After the day <lb></lb>of Judgment the <lb></lb>Earth ſhall ſtand <lb></lb>immoveable.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>Theſe are the Claſſes, &amp;c. </s>

<s>from which great aſſaults are made <lb></lb>againſt the ſtructure of the Pythagorick Syſteme; yet by that <lb></lb>time I ſhall have firſt laid down ſix Maximes or Principles, as <lb></lb>impregnable Bulwarks erected againſt them, it will be eaſie to <lb></lb>batter them, and to defend the Hypotheſis of <emph type="italics"></emph>Pythagoras<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> from <lb></lb>being attaqued by them. </s>

<s>Which before I propound, I do pro­<lb></lb>feſs (with that Humility and Modeſty which becometh a Chri­<lb></lb>ſtian, and a perſon in Religious Orders) that I do with reverence <lb></lb>ſubmit what I am about to ſpeak to the Judgment of Holy <lb></lb>Church. </s>

<s>Nor have I undertaken to write theſe things out of <lb></lb>any inducements of Temerity, or Ambition, but out of Charity <lb></lb>and a Deſire to be auxiliary to my neighbour in his inquiſition <lb></lb>after Truth. </s>

<s>And there is nothing in all this Controverſie <lb></lb>maintained by me (that expect to be better inſtructed by thoſe <lb></lb>who profeſs theſe Studies) which I ſhall not retract, if any per­<lb></lb>ſons ſhall by ſolid Reaſons &amp; reiterated Experiments, prove ſome <lb></lb>other Hypotheſis to be more probable; but yet, until ſuch time as <lb></lb>they ſhall decide the Point, I ſhall labour all I can for its ſupport.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>My firſt and chiefeſt Maxime is this; When any thing is at­<lb></lb>tributed in Holy Writ, to God, or to a Creature, thats not be­<lb></lb>ſeeming to, or incommenſurate with them, it muſt of neceſſity <lb></lb>be received and expounded one, or more of the four following <lb></lb>wayes; Firſt, it may be ſaid to agree with them <emph type="italics"></emph>Metaphorically, <lb></lb>and Proportionally, or by Similitude.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Secondly, <emph type="italics"></emph>According to <lb></lb>our manner of Conſidering, Apprehending, Conceiving, Vnderſtand­<lb></lb>ing, Knowing, &amp;c.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Thirdly, <emph type="italics"></emph>according to the Opinion of the <lb></lb>Vulgar, and the Common way of Speaking:<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> to which Vulgar <lb></lb>Speech the Holy Ghoſt doth very often with much ſtudy acco­<lb></lb>modate it ſelf. </s>

<s>Fourthly, <emph type="italics"></emph>In reſpect of our ſelves, and for that <lb></lb>he makes himſelf like unto us.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Of each of theſe wayes there are <lb></lb>theſe examples: God doth not walk, ſince he is Infinite and Im­<lb></lb>moveable; He hath no Bodily Members, ſince he is a Pure Act; <lb></lb>and conſequently is void of all Paſſion of Minde; and yet in <lb></lb>Sacred Scripture, <emph type="italics"></emph>Gen. </s>

<s>3. verſ.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 8. it is ſaid, <emph type="italics"></emph>He walked in the cool of <lb></lb>the day<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>: and <emph type="italics"></emph>Job 22. verſ.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 14. it is ſaid, <emph type="italics"></emph>He walketh in the ^{*} Cir­<lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg885"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>cuit of Heaven:<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and in many other places coming, departing, <lb></lb>making haſt is aſcribed to God; and likewiſe Bodily parts, as <lb></lb>Eyes, Ears, Lips, Face, Voice, Countenance, Hands, Feet, Bow­<lb></lb>els, Garments, Arms; as alſo many Paſſions, ſuch as Anger, 


<pb xlink:href="067/01/012.jpg" pagenum="482"></pb>Sorrow, Repentance, and the like. </s>

<s>What ſhall we ſay there­<lb></lb>fore? </s>

<s>Without doubt ſuch like Attributes agree with God (to <lb></lb>uſe the Schoolmens words <emph type="italics"></emph>Metaphorically, Proportionally, and by <lb></lb>Similitude<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>: And touching Paſſions, it may be ſaid, that God <lb></lb>condeſcendeth to repreſent himſelf after that manner: as for <lb></lb>inſtance, <emph type="italics"></emph>The Lord is angry<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; i.e. <emph type="italics"></emph>He revealeth himſelf as one that <lb></lb>is angry: He grieved<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; i. </s>

<s>e. <emph type="italics"></emph>He revealeth himſelf, as one that <lb></lb>is ſorrowful: It repented him that he had made man<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; i.e. <emph type="italics"></emph>He ſee­<lb></lb>med as one that repented.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> And indeed all theſe things are <emph type="italics"></emph>Com­<lb></lb>parativè ad nos,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and in reſpect of us. </s>

<s>So God is ſaid to be in <lb></lb>Heaven, to move in time, to ſhew himſelf, to hide himſelf, to <lb></lb>obſerve and mark our ſteps; to ſeek us, to ſtand at the door, <lb></lb>to knock at the door; not that he can be contained in a bodily <lb></lb>place, nor that he is really moved, nor in time; nor that humane <lb></lb>manners or cuſtomes can agree with him, ſave only according to <lb></lb>our manner of Apprehenſion: This Conception of ours orderly <lb></lb>diſtinguiſheth theſe Attributes in him one from another, when, <lb></lb>notwithſtanding, they are one and the ſame with him: This Ap­<lb></lb>prehenſion of ours divideth alſo his actions into ſeveral times, <lb></lb>which, nevertheleſſe, for the moſt part, are produced in one and <lb></lb>the ſame inſtant: And this, to conclude, alwayes apprehendeth <lb></lb>thoſe things with ſome defect, which, notwithſtanding are in <lb></lb>God moſt perfect. </s>

<s>For this reaſon doth the Sacred Scripture <lb></lb>expreſs it ſelf <emph type="italics"></emph>according to the Vulgar Opinion,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> whilſt it aſcribes <lb></lb>to the Earth Ends and Foundations, which yet it hath not; to <lb></lb>the Sea a Depth not to be fathomed; to Death (which is a Pri­<lb></lb>vation, and conſequently a Non entity) it appropriates Actions, <lb></lb>Motion, Paſſions, and other ſuch like Accidents, of all which it is <lb></lb>deprived, as alſo Epithites and Adjuncts, which really cannot <lb></lb>ſuit with it: <emph type="italics"></emph>Is not the bitterneſſe of Death paſt<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>? </s>

<s>1 Sam. </s>

<s>15. 32. <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Let death come upon them,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Pſal 6. <emph type="italics"></emph>He hath prepared the Inſtru­<lb></lb>ments of Death,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Pſal. </s>

<s>7. 14. <emph type="italics"></emph>Thou raiſeſt me from the gates of <lb></lb>Death,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Pſal. </s>

<s>84. <emph type="italics"></emph>In the midſt of the ſhadow of Death,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Pſal. </s>

<s>23. <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Love is ſtrong as Death,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Cant. </s>

<s>8. 9. <emph type="italics"></emph>The Firſt-Born of Death,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Job <lb></lb>18. 13. <emph type="italics"></emph>Deſtruction and Death ſay, &amp;c.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Job 28. 22. And who knows <lb></lb>not that the whole Hiſtory of the rich Glutton doth conſiſt of <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg886"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>the like phraſes of <emph type="italics"></emph>Vulgar Speech<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>? </s>

<s>So <emph type="italics"></emph>Eccleſiaſticus,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Chap. </s>

<s>27. <lb></lb>verſ. </s>

<s>11. <emph type="italics"></emph>The godly man abideth in wiſdome, as the Sun; but a <lb></lb>fool changeth as the Moon<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; and yet the Moon according to the <lb></lb>real truth of the matter no wayes changeth, but abides the ſame <lb></lb>for ever, as <emph type="italics"></emph>Aſtronomers<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> demonſtrate, one half thereof remain­<lb></lb>ing alwayes lucid, and the other alwayes opacous. </s>

<s>Nor at any <lb></lb>time doth this ſtate vary in it, unleſſe <emph type="italics"></emph>in reſpect of us,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>ac­<lb></lb>cording to the opinion of the Vulgar.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Hence it is cleer, that the <lb></lb>holy Scripture ſpeaks according to the common form of ſpeech u­


<pb xlink:href="067/01/013.jpg" pagenum="483"></pb>ſed amongſt the unlearned, and according to the appearance of <lb></lb>things, and not according to their true Exiſtence. </s>

<s>In like man­<lb></lb>ner <emph type="italics"></emph>Geneſ.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 1. in the deſcription of the Creation of all things, <lb></lb>the Light is ſaid to be made firſt of all, and yet it followeth in <lb></lb>the Text, <emph type="italics"></emph>And the Evening and the Morning made the firſt day<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>: <lb></lb>and a little after the ſeveral Acts of the Creation are diſtinguiſhed <lb></lb>and aſſigned to ſeveral days, and concerning each of them it is <lb></lb>ſaid in the Text, <emph type="italics"></emph>And the Evening and the Morning made the <lb></lb>ſecond day<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; and then <emph type="italics"></emph>the third day, the fourth day, &amp;c.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Hence <lb></lb>many doubts ariſe, all which I ſhall propound according to the <lb></lb>common Syſteme, that it may appear even from the <emph type="italics"></emph>H<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>ypotheſis <lb></lb>of that Syſteme, that the ſacred Scripture ſometimes, for the a­<lb></lb>voyding of emergent difficulties, is to be underſtood in a vulgar <lb></lb>ſenſe and meaning, and in reſpect of us, and not according to <lb></lb>the nature of things. </s>

<s>Which diſtinction even <emph type="italics"></emph>Ariſtotle<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> himſelf <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg887"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>ſeemeth to have hinted, when he ſaith, ^{*} <emph type="italics"></emph>Some things are more <lb></lb>intelligible to us; others by nature,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> or <emph type="italics"></emph>ſecundum ſe.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg885"></margin.target>* Circa Cardi­<lb></lb>nes Cœli.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg886"></margin.target>Luke 16.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg887"></margin.target>Alia ſunt notio­<lb></lb>ra nobis, alia, no­<lb></lb>tiora natura, vel <lb></lb>ſecundum ſe, <emph type="italics"></emph>A­<lb></lb>r ſt. </s>

<s>lib. 

1. Phyſ.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>Firſt therefore; If the light were made before heaven, then <lb></lb>it rolled about without heaven to the making of the diſtinction <lb></lb>of Day and Night. </s>

<s>Now this is contrary to the very doctrine <lb></lb>of theſe men, who affirm that no Cœleſtial Body can be moved <lb></lb>unleſſe <emph type="italics"></emph>per accidens,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and by the motion of <emph type="italics"></emph>H<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>eaven, <emph type="italics"></emph>and as a knot <lb></lb>in a board at the motion of the board.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Again, if it be ſaid, that <lb></lb>the Light was created at the ſame time with <emph type="italics"></emph>H<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>eaven, and began <lb></lb>to be moved with <emph type="italics"></emph>H<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>eaven, another doubt ariſeth, that likewiſe <lb></lb>oppoſeth the foreſaid common <emph type="italics"></emph>Hypotheſis:<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> For it being ſaid, <lb></lb>that Day and Night, Morning and Evening were made, that ſame <lb></lb>is either in reſpect of the Univerſe, or onely in reſpect of the <lb></lb>Earth and us. </s>

<s>If ſo be that the Sun turning round (according to <lb></lb>the <emph type="italics"></emph>Hypotheſis<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> of the Common Syſteme) doth not cauſe the <lb></lb>Night and Day, but only to opacous Bodies which are deſtitute <lb></lb>of all other light, but that of the Sun, whilſt in their half part <lb></lb>(which is their <emph type="italics"></emph>Hemiſphœre)<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and no more, (for that the Suns <lb></lb>light paſſeth over but one half of an opacous Body, unleſs a ve­<lb></lb>ry ſmall matter more in thoſe of leſſer bulk) they are illumina­<lb></lb>ted by the Suns aſpect, the other half remaining dark and tene­<lb></lb>broſe, by reaſon of a ſhadow proceeding from its own Body. <lb></lb></s>

<s>Therefore the diſtinction of dayes by the light of heaven, ac­<lb></lb>cording to the deſcription of them in the ſacred Scriptures, muſt <lb></lb>not be underſtood <emph type="italics"></emph>abſolutely,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>ſecundum ſe,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>Nature her <lb></lb>ſelf<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; but in reſpect of the Earth, and of us its inhabitants, and <lb></lb>conſequently <emph type="italics"></emph>ſecundum nos.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> &#039;Tis not therefore new, nor unu­<lb></lb>ſual in ſacred Scripture to ſpeak of things <emph type="italics"></emph>ſecundum nos,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and on­<lb></lb>ly <emph type="italics"></emph>in reſpect of us,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>ſecundum apparentiam<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; but not <emph type="italics"></emph>ſecundum <lb></lb>ſe,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>reinaturam,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> or <emph type="italics"></emph>Abſolutely<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>Simply.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p>


<pb xlink:href="067/01/014.jpg" pagenum="484"></pb><p type="main">

<s>And if any one would underſtand theſe Days of ſacred Scri­<lb></lb>pture, not only <emph type="italics"></emph>ſecundum nos,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> but alſo <emph type="italics"></emph>ſecundum naturam,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> as <lb></lb>circulations of Cœleſtial Light returning to the ſelf ſame point <lb></lb>from whence it did at firſt proceed; ſo as that there needs no <lb></lb>reſpect to be had to Night or to ^{*} Darkneſſe, for which ſole rea­<lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg888"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>ſon we are fain to imbrace the Interpretation of ſacred Scripture <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>ſecundum nos<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; In oppoſition to this we may thus argue: If the <lb></lb>ſacred Scripture be underſtood to ſpeak <emph type="italics"></emph>abſolutely,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> of iterated <lb></lb>and ſucceſſive circulations of light, and not <emph type="italics"></emph>reſpectu noſtri,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> as if <lb></lb>theſe words <emph type="italics"></emph>Evening and Morning<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> had never been inſerted, which <lb></lb>in their natural acceptation denote the Suns habitude to us and to <lb></lb>the Earth: For that the <emph type="italics"></emph>Morning<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> is that time when the Sun be­<lb></lb>gins to wax light, and to riſe above the <emph type="italics"></emph>Horizon<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> in the Eaſt, <lb></lb>and become viſible in our <emph type="italics"></emph>Hemiſphœre,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>Evening<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> is the time <lb></lb>in which the Sun declines in the Weſt, and approacheth with its <lb></lb>light neerer to the other oppoſite <emph type="italics"></emph>Horizon<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>Hemiſphœre,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>which is contiguous to this of ours. </s>

<s>But the word <emph type="italics"></emph>Day<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> is a Co­<lb></lb>relative to the word <emph type="italics"></emph>Night.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> From hence therefore it evidently <lb></lb>appeareth, that theſe three words <emph type="italics"></emph>Evening, Morning,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>Day,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>cannot be underſtood of a Circulation of Light <emph type="italics"></emph>ſecundum ſe,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>and <emph type="italics"></emph>abſolutè,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> but only <emph type="italics"></emph>ſecundum nos,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>reſpectu noſtri<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; and in <lb></lb>that ſenſe indeed the <emph type="italics"></emph>Morning<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>Evening<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> do make the <emph type="italics"></emph>Night<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>and <emph type="italics"></emph>Day,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg888"></margin.target>* Aut ad Umbram</s></p><p type="main">

<s>In like manner, <emph type="italics"></emph>Gen.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 1. 16. it is ſaid, <emph type="italics"></emph>God made two great Lights; <lb></lb>the greater Light to rule the Day, and the leſſer Light to rule the <lb></lb>Night, and the Stars.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Where both in the Propoſition and in the <lb></lb>ſpecification of it, things are ſpoken which are very diſagreeing <lb></lb>with Cœleſtial Bodies. </s>

<s>Therefore thoſe words are in that place <lb></lb>to be interpreted according to the foreſaid Rules; namely, ac­<lb></lb>cording to the third and fourth; ſo that they may be ſaid to be <lb></lb>underſtood <emph type="italics"></emph>according to the ſenſe of the vulgar, and the common <lb></lb>way of ſpeaking,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> which is all one, as if we ſhould ſay, <emph type="italics"></emph>ſecundum <lb></lb>apparentiam,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>ſecundum nos, vel reſpectu noſtri.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> For firſt, it <lb></lb>is ſaid in the Propoſition, <emph type="italics"></emph>And God made two great Lights<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; <lb></lb>meaning by them the Sun and Moon, whereas according to the <lb></lb>truth of the matter theſe are not the Greater Lights; For al­<lb></lb>though the Sun may be reckoned amongſt the Greater, the Moon <lb></lb>may not be ſo, unleſs <emph type="italics"></emph>in reſpect of us.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Becauſe amongſt <lb></lb>thoſe that are abſolutely the Greater, and a little leſſer than the <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg889"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>Sun (nay in a manner equal to it) and far bigger than the Moon, <lb></lb>we may with great reaſon enumerate <emph type="italics"></emph>Saturn,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> or ſome of the <lb></lb>Fixed Stars of the firſt Magnitude, ſuch as <emph type="italics"></emph>Canopus,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> (otherwiſe <lb></lb>called <emph type="italics"></emph>Arcanar)<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> in the end of a River; or the <emph type="italics"></emph>Little Dog<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> in <lb></lb>the mouth of the <emph type="italics"></emph>Great Dog<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; or the Foot of <emph type="italics"></emph>Orion,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> called <emph type="italics"></emph>Ri­<lb></lb>gel<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; or his <emph type="italics"></emph>Right ſhoulder,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> or any other of that Magnitude. 


<pb xlink:href="067/01/015.jpg" pagenum="485"></pb>Therefore the <emph type="italics"></emph>two great Lights<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> are to be underſtood in reſpect of <lb></lb>us, and according to vulgar eſtimation, and not according to the <lb></lb>true and reall exiſtence of ſuch Bodies. </s>

<s>Secondly, in the ſpeci­<lb></lb>fication of the Propoſition it is ſaid, <emph type="italics"></emph>The greater Light to rule the <lb></lb>Day<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; hereby denoting the Sun; in which the verbal ſenſe of <lb></lb>Scripture agreeth with the Truth of the Thing; For that the Sun <lb></lb>is the Greateſt of all Luminaries, and Globes. </s>

<s>But that which <lb></lb>followeth immediately after, <emph type="italics"></emph>And the leſſer Light to rule the <lb></lb>Night,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> meaning the Moon, cannot be taken in the true and real <lb></lb>ſenſe of the words: For the Moon is not the leſſer Light, but <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Mercury<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; which is not only much leſſer than the Moon, but alſo <lb></lb>than any other Star. </s>

<s>And if, again, it be ſaid, That the Holy <lb></lb>Text doth not ſpeak of the Stars, but onely of the Luminaries, <lb></lb>for that preſently after they are mentioned apart, <emph type="italics"></emph>And the Stars<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; <lb></lb>and that what we ſay is true touching the compariſon of the Stars <lb></lb>amongſt themſelves, but not in reſpect of the Luminaries, name­<lb></lb>ly, the Sun and Moon: This reply doth diſcover a man to be <lb></lb>utterly ignorant in theſe Studies, and ſuch who having not the <lb></lb>leaſt ſmattering in them, doth conceive an abſurd and erroneous <lb></lb>Opinion of the Cœleſtial Bodies. </s>

<s>For the Moon and Sun, con­<lb></lb>ſidered in themſelves, and as they appear to us, if they ſhould <lb></lb>be a far greater diſtance from us, than indeed they are, would be <lb></lb>no other, nor would appear to us otherwiſe than Stars, as the <lb></lb>reſt do in the Firmament. </s>

<s>But Great Luminaries they neither <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg890"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>are, nor ſeem to be, ſave only <emph type="italics"></emph>in reſpect of us:<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> And ſo, on <lb></lb>the other ſide, the Stars, as to themſelves, are no other than ſo <lb></lb>many Suns and ſo many Moons; yet are ſo far remote from us, <lb></lb>that by reaſon of their diſtance they appear thus ſmall, and dim <lb></lb>of light, as we behold them. </s>

<s>For the greater and leſſer diſtance <lb></lb>of heavenly Bodies <emph type="italics"></emph>(cæteris paribus)<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> doth augment and diminiſh <lb></lb>their appearance both as to Magnitude and Light. </s>

<s>And there­<lb></lb>fore the words which follow in that place of <emph type="italics"></emph>Geneſis, And the <lb></lb>Stars<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> (as diſtinguiſhing the Stars from the Sun and Moon) are <lb></lb>to be taken in no other acceptation than that which we have ſpo­<lb></lb>ken of, namely, <emph type="italics"></emph>according to the ſenſe of the Vulgar, and the <lb></lb>common manner of ſpeech.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> For indeed, according to the truth <lb></lb>of the matter, all Cœleſtial Bodies, being ſhining Globes, are of <lb></lb>a vaſt bigneſs, to which if we ſhould be ſo neer as we are to the <lb></lb>Moon, they would ſeem to us of as great, yea a greater magni­<lb></lb>tude than the Moon: As likewiſe on the contrary, if we were as <lb></lb>far diſtant from the Sun and Moon, as we are from them, both <lb></lb>Moon and Sun would ſhew but as ſtars to us. </s>

<s>And yet the <lb></lb>ſplendor of the Sun would doubtleſs be greater <emph type="italics"></emph>intenſivè<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> than <lb></lb>that of any other ſtar. </s>

<s>For, although it ſhould be granted that <lb></lb>ſome ſtars (as thoſe of the Fixed that twinkle) do ſhine of them­


<pb xlink:href="067/01/016.jpg" pagenum="486"></pb>ſelves, aud by their own nature, as the Sun, that derives not its <lb></lb>light from others (which yet remains undecided and doubtful) <lb></lb>and borrow not their light from the Sun; Nevertheleſs ſince the <lb></lb>brightneſs of none of the ſtars may be compared with the Suns <lb></lb>ſplendour, which was created by God firſt, and before all other <lb></lb>Luminaries, in the higheſt kind of Light, it would therefore <lb></lb>notwithſtanding follow, that none of thoſe ſtars, although pla­<lb></lb>ced in the ſame proximity to us with the Sun, and therefore ap­<lb></lb>pearing to us of the ſame Magnitude as the Sun, can beſtow up­<lb></lb>on us ſo much Light as we receive from the Sun: As on the <lb></lb>contrary, the Sun, at the ſame remoteneſſe from us as they are, <lb></lb>would indeed, as to its Magnitude, appear to us as one of thoſe <lb></lb>ſtars, but of a ſplendour much more <emph type="italics"></emph>intenſe<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> than that of theirs. <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg891"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>So that, now, the Earth is nothing elſe but another Moon or ſtar, <lb></lb>and ſo would it appear to us, if we ſhould behold it from a con­<lb></lb>venient diſtance <emph type="italics"></emph>on high.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> And in it might be obſerved (in that <lb></lb>variety of Light and Darkneſs which the Sun produceth in it by <lb></lb>making Day and Night) the ſame difference of Aſpects that are <lb></lb>ſeen in the Moon, and ſuch as are obſerved in tricorporate <emph type="italics"></emph>Ve­<lb></lb>nus<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; in like manner alſo &#039;tis very probable that the ſame might <lb></lb>be diſcerned in other Planets, which ſhine by no light of their <lb></lb>own, but by one borrowed from the Sun. </s>

<s>What ever there­<lb></lb>fore may touching theſe matters be delivered in the ſacred Leaves <lb></lb>or the common ſpeech of men, diſſenting from the real truth, it <lb></lb>ought (as we have ſaid before) abſolutely to be received and un­<lb></lb>derſtood <emph type="italics"></emph>ſecundum vulgi ſententiam, &amp; communem loquendi &amp; <lb></lb>concipiendi ſtylum.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg889"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>Which are really <lb></lb>the great Lights <lb></lb>in Heaven.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg890"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>The Sun, Moon, <lb></lb>and Stars are one <lb></lb>&amp; the ſame thing.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg891"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>The Earth is a­<lb></lb>nother Moon or <lb></lb>Star.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>And ſo, to return to our purpoſe, if, all this conſidered, the <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Pythagorian<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> opinion be true, it will be eaſie, according to the <lb></lb>ſame Rule, to reconcile the authority of ſacred Scriptures with <lb></lb>it, however they ſeem to oppoſe it, and in particular thoſe of the <lb></lb>firſt and ſecond Claſſis, <emph type="italics"></emph>ſcilicet<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> by my firſt <emph type="italics"></emph>Maxime:<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> For that in <lb></lb>thoſe places the holy Records ſpeak according to our manner of <lb></lb>underſtanding, and according to that which appeareth in reſpect <lb></lb>of us; <emph type="italics"></emph>For thus it is with thoſe Bodies, in compariſon of us, and<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg892"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>as they are deſcribed by the vulgar and commune way of humane <lb></lb>Diſcourſe; So that the Earth appears as if it were ſtanding ſtill <lb></lb>and immoveable, and the Sun, as if it were circumambient about <lb></lb>her.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> And ſo the Holy Scripture is uſed in the Commune and <lb></lb>Vulgar way of ſpeaking; becauſe in reſpect of our ſight, the <lb></lb>Earth ſeems rather to ſtand fixed in the Centre, and the Sun to <lb></lb>circumvolve about it, than otherwiſe: as it happens to thoſe that <lb></lb>are putting off from the Banks of a River to whom the ſhose <lb></lb>ſeems to move backwards, and go from them: but they do not <lb></lb>perceive (which yet is the truth) that they themſelves go forwards. 


<pb xlink:href="067/01/017.jpg" pagenum="487"></pb>Which fallacy of our ſight is noted, and the Reaſon thereof aſ­<lb></lb>ſigned by the Opticks; upon wich, as being ſtrange to, and be­<lb></lb>ſides my purpoſe, I will not ſtay) and on this account is <emph type="italics"></emph>Æneas<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>brought in by <emph type="italics"></emph>Virgil,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> ſaying;<lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg893"></arrow.to.target></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg892"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>Why the Sunne <lb></lb>ſeemeth to us to <lb></lb>move, &amp; not the <lb></lb>Earth.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg893"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>Æneid.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 3.</s></p><p type="head">

<s><emph type="italics"></emph>Provehimur portu, terræque urbeſque recedunt.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>But it will not be amiſs to conſider why the ſacred Scripture <lb></lb>doth ſo ſtudiouſly comply with the opinions of the Vulgar, and <lb></lb>why it doth not rather accurately inſtruct men in the truth of the <lb></lb>matters, and the ſecrets of Nature. </s>

<s>The Reaſon is, firſt, the be­<lb></lb>nignity of Divine Wiſdome, whereby it ſweetly accomodates it <lb></lb>ſelf to all things, in proportion to their Capacity and Nature. <lb></lb></s>

<s>Whence in Natural Sciences, it uſeth natural and neceſſary cau­<lb></lb>ſes, but in Liberal Arts it worketh liberally, upon Generous <lb></lb>Perſons after a ſublime and lofty manner; upon the Common <lb></lb>People, familiarly and humbly; upon the Skilful, learnedly; <lb></lb>upon the Simple, vulgarly; and ſo on every one, according to <lb></lb>his condition and quality. </s>

<s>Secondly, becauſe it is not its In­<lb></lb>tention to fill our mindes in this life with vain and various curi­<lb></lb>oſities, which might occaſion our doubt and ſuſpenſe. </s>

<s>For the <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg894"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>truth is, <emph type="italics"></emph>(a) He that increaſeth knowledge, increaſeth ſorrow.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>Moreover it did not only permit, but even decree, thatth e <lb></lb>World ſhould be very much buſied in Controverſies and Diſpu­<lb></lb>tations, and that it ſhould be imployed about the uncertainty of <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg895"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>things; according to that ſaying of <emph type="italics"></emph>Eccleſiaſtes<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> <emph type="italics"></emph>(b) He hath <lb></lb>ſet the World in their heart; ſo that no man can find out the work <lb></lb>that God maketh from the beginning unto the end.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> And touching <lb></lb>thoſe doubts, God will not permit that they ſhall be diſcovered <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg896"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>to us before the end of the World: <emph type="italics"></emph>(c) At which time he will <lb></lb>bring to light the hidden things of darkneſſe:<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> But Gods onely <lb></lb>ſcope in the ſacred Scripture is to teach men thoſe things which <lb></lb>conduce to the attainment of Eternal Life; which having ob­<lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg897"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>tained, <emph type="italics"></emph>(d) We ſhall ſee him face to face: (e) and ſhall be<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg898"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>like him, for we ſhall ſee him as he is.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Then ſhall he clearly <emph type="italics"></emph>à <lb></lb>Priori<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> make known unto us all thoſe Curioſities, and Dogmati­<lb></lb>cal Queſtions, which in this life, <emph type="italics"></emph>(f) in which we ſee through a<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg899"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Glaſſe darkly,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> could be known by us but imperfectly and <emph type="italics"></emph>à poſte­<lb></lb>riori,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and that not without much pains and ſtudy. </s>

<s>For this <lb></lb>cauſe the Wiſdome of God, revealed to us in the ſacred Leaves, <lb></lb>is not ſtiled Wiſdome abſolutely, but <emph type="italics"></emph>(g) Saving Wiſdome<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg900"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>Its onely end being to lead us to ſalvation. </s>

<s>And S. <emph type="italics"></emph>Paul<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> preach­<lb></lb>ing to the <emph type="italics"></emph>Corinthians,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> ſaith; <emph type="italics"></emph>(h) I determined to know nothing<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg901"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>among you, ſave Jeſus Chriſt, and him crucified:<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> whereas not­<lb></lb>withſtanding he was thorowly inſtructed, and profoundly learned 


<pb xlink:href="067/01/018.jpg" pagenum="488"></pb>in all humane Sciences; but making no account of theſe things <lb></lb>he profeſſeth that it was his deſire to teach them no more but the <lb></lb>way to Heaven. </s>

<s>Hence is that which God ſpeaketh to us by <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg902"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Iſaiah,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> <emph type="italics"></emph>(i) Ego Dominus Deus, docens te utilia<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> [<emph type="italics"></emph>I am the Lord <lb></lb>thy God which teacheth thee profitable things:<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>] Where the <emph type="italics"></emph>Gloſ­<lb></lb>ſary<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> addeth, <emph type="italics"></emph>non ſubtilia<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> [not ſubtilties.] For God neither taught <lb></lb>us, Whether the <emph type="italics"></emph>Materia Prima<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> of Heaven, and the Elements <lb></lb>be the ſame; nor Whether <emph type="italics"></emph>Cominual<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> be compoſed of Indiviſi­<lb></lb>bles, or whether it be diviſible <emph type="italics"></emph>in infinitum<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; nor, whether the <lb></lb>Elements are formally <emph type="italics"></emph>mixt<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; nor how many the Cœleſtial <lb></lb>Spheres, and their Orbs are; Whether there be Epicycles or <lb></lb>Eccentricks; nor the Vertues of Plants and Stones; nor the Na­<lb></lb>ture of Animals; nor the Motion and Influence of the Planets; <lb></lb>nor the Order of the Univerſe; nor the Wonders of Minerals, <lb></lb>and univerſal Nature: but only [<emph type="italics"></emph>utilia:<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>] things profitable, to <lb></lb>wit, his Holy Law ordained to the end, that we being put into <lb></lb>poſſeſſion of Bleſſedneſs, might at length be made capable of all <lb></lb>perfect knowledge, and the viſion of the whole Order and ad­<lb></lb>mirable Harmony, as alſo the Sympathy and Antipathy of the <lb></lb>Univerſe and its parts, <emph type="italics"></emph>in his Word,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> wherein all thoſe <lb></lb>things ſhall moſt clearly and diſtinctly, then, appear to us, which <lb></lb>mean while, in this life, he hath remitted (as far as its ability <lb></lb>reacheth) to humane ſearch and enquiry: But it was not his <lb></lb>purpoſe to determine any thing, directly or indirectly, touching <lb></lb>the truth of them. </s>

<s>Becauſe as the knowledge thereof would lit­<lb></lb>tle or nothing profit Us, but might in ſome caſes prove prejudi­<lb></lb>cial; ſo the ignorance thereof can doubtleſs be no detriment, <lb></lb>but may in ſome caſes be very beneficial to us. </s>

<s>And therefore <lb></lb>by his moſt admirable Wiſdome it comes to paſs, that though all <lb></lb>things in this World are dubious, uncertain, wavering, and per­<lb></lb>plexed; yet his Holy Faith alone is moſt certain; and although <lb></lb>the opinions about Philoſophical and Doctrinal points be divers, <lb></lb>there is in the Church but one Truth of Faith and Salvation. <lb></lb></s>

<s>Which Faith, as neceſsary to Salvation, is ſo ordered by Divine <lb></lb>Providence, that it might not only be indubitable, but alſo un­<lb></lb>ſhaken, ſure, immutable, and manifeſt to all men: the infallible <lb></lb>Rule of which he hath appointed the Holy Church, that is waſh­<lb></lb>ed with his precious Blood, and governed by his Holy Spirit, to <lb></lb>whom belongs our Sanctification, as being his work. </s>

<s>This there­<lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg903"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>fore is the Reaſon why God would have Speculative Queſtions, <lb></lb>which nothing conduce to our Salvation and Edification, and why <lb></lb>the Holy Ghoſt hath very often condeſcended to Vulgar Opini­<lb></lb>ons and Capacities, and hath diſcovered nothing that is ſingular <lb></lb>or hidden to us, beſides thoſe things that pertain to Salvation. <lb></lb></s>

<s>So that conſequently it is clear by what hath been ſaid, how and 


<pb xlink:href="067/01/019.jpg" pagenum="489"></pb>why nothing of certainty can be evinced from the foreſaid Au­<lb></lb>thorities to the determining of Controverſies of this Nature; as <lb></lb>alſo with what Reaſon from this firſt <emph type="italics"></emph>Axiome<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> the Objections of <lb></lb>the firſt and ſecond Claſſe are eaſily anſwered, as alſo any other <lb></lb>Authority of ſacred Scripture produced againſt the <emph type="italics"></emph>Pythagorian<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>and <emph type="italics"></emph>Copernican<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Syſteme ſo long as by other proofs it is true.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg894"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(a)<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Eccleſ. <emph type="italics"></emph>c. </s>

<s>1. v. <lb></lb></s>

<s>ult.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg895"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(b) Chap. </s>

<s>3. v.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 11.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg896"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(c)<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 1 Cor. <emph type="italics"></emph>c. </s>

<s>4. v.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 5</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg897"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(d)<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 1 Cor. <emph type="italics"></emph>c. </s>

<s>13. v.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>12.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg898"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(e)<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 1 John <emph type="italics"></emph>c. </s>

<s>3. v.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>2.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg899"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(f)<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 1 Cor. <emph type="italics"></emph>c. </s>

<s>13. v.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>12.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg900"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(g)<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Eccleſiaſt. </s>

<s>15. 3</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg901"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(h)<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 1 Cor. <emph type="italics"></emph>c. </s>

<s>2. v.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 2</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg902"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(i)<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Iſa. <emph type="italics"></emph>c. </s>

<s>48. v.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 17.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg903"></margin.target>1 Theſſ. </s>

<s>4.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>And the Authorities of the ſecond Claſſe in particular by <lb></lb>this ſame Maxime, <emph type="italics"></emph>Of the ordinary manner of apprehending <lb></lb>things as they appear to us, and after the common way of ſpeak­<lb></lb>ing,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> may be thus reconciled and expounded; namely, Oftentimes <lb></lb>an Agent is commonly, and not improperly ſaid to move, (though <lb></lb>it have no motion) not becauſe it doth indeed move, but <emph type="italics"></emph>by ex­<lb></lb>trinſick denomination,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> becauſe receiving its influence and action at <lb></lb>the motion of the Subject; the Form and Quality infuſed to <lb></lb>the Subject by the ſaid Agent doth likewiſe move. </s>

<s>As for ex­<lb></lb>ample, a Fire burning in a Chimney is an immoveable Agent, <lb></lb>before which a man oppreſt with cold ſits to warm himſelf who <lb></lb>being warmed on one ſide, turns the other to the Fire, that he <lb></lb>may be warmed on that ſide alſo, and ſo in like manner he holds <lb></lb>every part to the Fire ſucceſſively, till his whole body be warm­<lb></lb>ed. &#039;Tis clear, that although the Fire do not move, yet at the <lb></lb>Motion of the Subject, to wit the Man, who receiveth the heat <lb></lb>and action of the Fire, the Form and Quality of its Heat doth <lb></lb>move <emph type="italics"></emph>ſingulatim, &amp; per partes,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> round about the mans body, and <lb></lb>alwayes ſeeketh out a new place: and ſo, though the Fire do <lb></lb>not move, yet by reaſon of its effect, it is ſaid to go round all <lb></lb>the parts of the Mans body, and to warm it, not indeed by a <lb></lb>true and real motion of the Fire it ſelf, ſince it is ſuppoſed (and <lb></lb>that not untruly) not to move, but by the motion to which the <lb></lb>Body is excited, out of a deſire of receiving the heat of the Fire <lb></lb>in each of its parts. </s>

<s>The ſame may be applied to the Illumina­<lb></lb>tion impreſſed ſucceſſively on the parts of any Globe, which <lb></lb>moves Orbicularly at the aſpect of a ſhining immoveable <lb></lb>Light. </s>

<s>And in the ſame manner may the Sun be ſaid to riſe and <lb></lb>ſet, and to move above the Earth, although in reality he doth <lb></lb>not move, nor ſuffer any mutation; that is to ſay, Inaſmuch as <lb></lb>his Light (which effect is the Form and Quality proceeding from <lb></lb>him, as the Agent, to the Earth as the Subject) doth ſenſibly <lb></lb>glide forwards, by reaſon of the Orbicular motion of the Earth; <lb></lb>and doth alwayes be take it ſelf to ſome new place of her ſurface; <lb></lb>upon which ground he is truly ſaid <emph type="italics"></emph>(ſecundum vnlgarem ſermo­<lb></lb>nem)<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> to move above, and revolve about the Earth: Not that the <lb></lb>Sun doth move, (for by this Opinion we affirm the Earth to <lb></lb>move, that it may receive the Sun one while in one, another <lb></lb>while in another part of it) but that at the motion of the Earth 


<pb xlink:href="067/01/020.jpg" pagenum="490"></pb>her ſelf a contrary way, the Quality diffuſed into her, and im­<lb></lb>preſſed upon her by the Sun, namely the Light of the Day is <lb></lb>moved, which riſeth in one part of her, and ſets in another con­<lb></lb>trary to that, according to the nature and condition of her motion; <lb></lb>And for this reaſon the Sun it ſelf by conſequence is ſaid to riſe <lb></lb>and ſet, (which notwithſtanding <emph type="italics"></emph>ex Hypotheſi<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> ſtands immovea­<lb></lb>ble) and that no otherwiſe then <emph type="italics"></emph>per donominationem extrinſecam,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>as hath been ſaid.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>After this manner the command of <emph type="italics"></emph>Joſhuah, Sun ſtand thou<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg904"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>ſtill,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and the Miracle of the Suns ceſſation of Motion wrought <lb></lb>by him, may be ſo underſtood, as that not the Solar Body pro­<lb></lb>perly, but the Suns ſplendour upon the Earth ſtood ſtill; ſo that <lb></lb>not the Sun it ſelf, (being of it ſelf before that time immovea­<lb></lb>ble) but the Earth that receiveth its ſplendour, ſtayed her Mo­<lb></lb>tion; which, as ſhe inceſſantly purſuing her ordinary Motion to­<lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg905"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>wards the Eaſt, ^{*} called up the Light of the Sun in the Weſt, ſo <lb></lb>ſtanding ſtill, the Suns light impreſt upon it likewiſe ſtood ſtill. <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg906"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>After the ſame manuer pioportionally is that Text of <emph type="italics"></emph>Iſaiah<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> ex­<lb></lb>plained, touching the Suns going ten degrees back ward upon the <lb></lb>Dial of <emph type="italics"></emph>Ahaz.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> So (which may ſerve for another Example) the <lb></lb>Hand being moved about the flame of a burning Candle that <lb></lb>ſtands ſtill, the Light moveth on the Hand, that is to ſay, the <lb></lb>ſaid Hand is illuſtrated now in one part, anon in another, when <lb></lb>as the Candle it ſelf all the while removes not out of its place: <lb></lb>whereupon <emph type="italics"></emph>per denominationem extrinſecam,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> the ſaid Light may <lb></lb>be affirmed to riſe and ſet upon the Hand, namely, by the ſole <lb></lb>motion of the ſaid Hand, the Candle it ſelf never moving all the <lb></lb>while. </s>

<s>And let this ſuffice for the explanation of my firſt Prin­<lb></lb>ciple or <emph type="italics"></emph>Maxime,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> which by reaſon of its difficulty and extraordi­<lb></lb>nary weight required ſome prolixity in the handling of it.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg904"></margin.target>Joſhua <emph type="italics"></emph>c. </s>

<s>10. <lb></lb>ver.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 12.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg905"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>* expected.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg906"></margin.target>Iſa. <emph type="italics"></emph>c. </s>

<s>38. v.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 8.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>My ſecond Maxime is this, Things both Spiritual and Cor­<lb></lb>poreal, Durable and Corruptible, Moveable and Immoveable, <lb></lb>have received from God a perpetual, unchangeable, and inviola­<lb></lb>ble Law, conſtituting the Eſſence and Nature of every one of <lb></lb>them: according to which Law all of them in their own Na­<lb></lb>ture perſiſting in a certain Order and Conſtancy, and obſerving <lb></lb>the ſame perpetual Courſe, may deſervedly be ſtiled moſt Stable <lb></lb>and Determinate. </s>

<s>Thus Fortune (than which there is nothing <lb></lb>in the World more inconſtant or fickle) is ſaid to be conſtant <lb></lb>and unalterable in her continual volubility, viciſſitude, and in­<lb></lb>conſtancy, which was the occaſion of that Verſe,</s></p><p type="head">

<s><emph type="italics"></emph>Et ſemper conſtans in levitate ſua eſt.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>And thus the motion of Heaven (which by the conſtan Law 


<pb xlink:href="067/01/021.jpg" pagenum="491"></pb>of Nature ought to be perpetual) may be ſaid to be immutable <lb></lb>and immoveable, and the Heavens themſelves to be immovea­<lb></lb>bly moved, and Terrene things to be immutably changed, be­<lb></lb>cauſe thoſe never ceaſe moving, nor theſe changing. </s>

<s>By this Prin­<lb></lb>ciple or Maxime all difficulties belonging to the firſt Claſſis are <lb></lb>cleared, by which the Earth is ſaid to be ſtable and immoveable, <lb></lb>that is, by underſtanding this one thing, That the Earth, as to its <lb></lb>own Nature, though it include in it ſelf a local Motion, and that <lb></lb>threefold, according to the opinion of <emph type="italics"></emph>Copernicus (ſcilicet<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Diur­<lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg907"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>nal, with which it revolveth about its own Centre; Annual, <lb></lb>by which it moveth through the twelve Signes of the Zodiack, <lb></lb>and the motion of Inclination, by which its Axis is alwayes op­<lb></lb>poſed to the ſame part of the World) as alſo other Species of <lb></lb>Mutation, ſuch as Generation and Corruption, Accretion and <lb></lb>Diminution, and Alteration of divers kinds; yet in all theſe ſhe <lb></lb>is ſtable &amp; conſtant, never deviating from that Order which God <lb></lb>hath appointed her, but moveth continually, conſtantly and im­<lb></lb>mutably, according to the ſix before named Species of Motion.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg907"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>Several Motions <lb></lb>of the Earth ac­<lb></lb>cording to<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Coper­<lb></lb>nicus.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>My third Maxime ſhall be this; When a thing is moved ac­<lb></lb>cording to ſome part of it, and not according to its whole, it <lb></lb>cannot be ſaid to be <emph type="italics"></emph>ſimply &amp; abſolutely<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> moved, but only <emph type="italics"></emph>per acci­<lb></lb>dens,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> for that ſtability taken ſimply &amp; abſolutly do rather accord <lb></lb>with the ſame. </s>

<s>As for example, if a Barrel or other meaſure of <lb></lb>Water be taken out of the Sea, and transferred to another place, <lb></lb>the Sea may not therefore <emph type="italics"></emph>abſolutely &amp; ſimply<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> be ſaid to be remo­<lb></lb>ved from place to place; but only <emph type="italics"></emph>per accidens,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>ſecundum <lb></lb>quid,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> that is, according to a part of it, but rather (to ſpeak ſim­<lb></lb>ply) we ſhould ſay that the Sea cannot be carried or moved out of <lb></lb>its proper place,, though as to its parts it be moved, and transfer­<lb></lb>red to &amp; again. </s>

<s>This Maxime is manifeſt of it ſelf, and by it may <lb></lb>the Authorities be explained which ſeem to make for the immo­<lb></lb>bility of the Earth in this manner; namely, The Earth <emph type="italics"></emph>per ſe &amp; <lb></lb>abſolutè<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> conſidered as to its <emph type="italics"></emph>Whole,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> is not mutable, ſeeing it is <lb></lb>neither generated nor corrupted neither increaſed nor diminiſhed; <lb></lb>neither is it altered <emph type="italics"></emph>ſecundum totum,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> but only <emph type="italics"></emph>ſecundum partes.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg908"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>Now it plainly appears, that this is the genuine and true Senſe of <lb></lb>what is aſcribed to it out of <emph type="italics"></emph>Eccleſiaſtes, cap. 

1. v. </s>

<s>4. One Generation <lb></lb>paſſeth away, and another Generation cometh, but the Earth abideth <lb></lb>for ever<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>: as if he ſhould ſay; although the Earth, according to its <lb></lb>parts, doth generate and corrupt, and is liable to the viciſſitudes of <lb></lb>Generation and corruption, yet in reference to its Whole it never <lb></lb>generateth nor Corrupteth, but abideth immutable for ever: <lb></lb>Like as a Ship, which though it be mended one while in the Sail­<lb></lb>yard, another while in the Stern, and afterwards in other parts <lb></lb>it yet remains the ſame Ship as it was at firſt. </s>

<s>But tis to be ad­


<pb xlink:href="067/01/022.jpg" pagenum="492"></pb>vertized, that that Scripture doth not ſpeak of a Local Motion, <lb></lb>but of Mutations of another nature; as in the very ſubſtance, <lb></lb>quantity or quality of the Earth it ſelf. </s>

<s>But if it be ſaid, that <lb></lb>it is to be underſtood of a Local Motion, then it may be ex­<lb></lb>plained by the inſuing Maxime, that is to ſay, a reſpect being had <lb></lb>to the natural Place aſſigned it in the Univerſe, as ſhall be ſhewed <lb></lb>by and by.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg908"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>The Earth Se-<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>cundum Totum <emph type="italics"></emph>is <lb></lb>Immutable, <lb></lb>though not Immo­<lb></lb>vable.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>The fourth Axiome is this; That every Corporeal thing, mo­<lb></lb>veable or immoveable from its very firſt Creation, is alotted its <lb></lb>proper and natural place; and being drawn or removed from <lb></lb>thence, its motion is violent, and it hath a natural tendency to <lb></lb>move back thither again: alſo that nothing can be moved from <lb></lb>its natural place, <emph type="italics"></emph>ſecundum Totum<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; For moſt great and dreadſul <lb></lb>miſchiefs would follow from that perturbation of things in the <lb></lb>Univerſe. </s>

<s>Therefore neither the whole Earth, nor the whole <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg909"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>Water, nor the whole Air can <emph type="italics"></emph>ſecundum totum<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> be driuen or for­<lb></lb>ced out of their proper place, ſite, or Syſteme in the Univerſe, <lb></lb>in reſpect of the order and diſpoſition of other mundane Bodies. <lb></lb></s>

<s>And thus there is no Star (though Erratick) Orb or Sphere that <lb></lb>can deſert its natural place, although it may otherwiſe have ſome <lb></lb>kind of motion. </s>

<s>Therefore all things, how moveable ſoever, <lb></lb>are notwithſtanding ſaid to be ſtable and immoveable in their <lb></lb>proper place, according to the foreſaid ſenſe, <emph type="italics"></emph>i.e. </s>

<s>ſecundum to­<lb></lb>tum<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; For nothing hinders, but that <emph type="italics"></emph>ſecundum partes<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> they may <lb></lb>ſome waymove; which motion ſhall not be natural, but violent. <lb></lb></s>

<s>Therefore the Earth, although it ſhould be moveable, yet it <lb></lb>might be ſaid to be immoveable, according to the precedent <lb></lb>Maxime, for that its neither moved in a right Motion nor out of <lb></lb>the Courſe aſſigned it in its Creation for the ſtanding Rule of its <lb></lb>motion; but keep within its own ſite, being placed in that <lb></lb>which is called the Grand Orb, above <emph type="italics"></emph>Venus,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and beneath <emph type="italics"></emph>Mars,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg910"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>and being in the middle betwixt theſe (which according to the <lb></lb>common opinion is the Suns place) it equally and continually <lb></lb>moveth about the Sun, and the two other intermediate Planets, <lb></lb>namely <emph type="italics"></emph>Venus<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>Mercury,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and hath the Moon (which is another <lb></lb>Earth, but Ætherial, as <emph type="italics"></emph>Macrobius<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> after ſome of the ancient Phi­<lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg911"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>loſophers, will have it) about it ſelf. </s>

<s>From whence, inaſmuch as <lb></lb>ſhe perſiſteth uniformly in her Courſe, and never at any time <lb></lb>departeth from it, ſhe may be ſaid to be ſtable and immoveable: <lb></lb>and in the ſame ſenſe Heaven likewiſe, with all the Elements, <lb></lb>may be ſaid to be immoveable.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg909"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>The Earth can­<lb></lb>not<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Secundum To­<lb></lb>tum, <emph type="italics"></emph>remove out of <lb></lb>its Natural Place.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg910"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>The Natural <lb></lb>Place of the Earth.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg911"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>The Moon is an <lb></lb>Ætherial Body.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>The fifth Maxime followeth, being little different from the <lb></lb>former. </s>

<s>Amongſt the things created by God, ſome are of ſuch a <lb></lb>nature, that their parts may be <emph type="italics"></emph>ab invicem,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> or by turns, ſe­<lb></lb>parated from themſelves, and diſ-joyned from their Whole; 


<pb xlink:href="067/01/023.jpg" pagenum="493"></pb>others may not, at leaſt, taken <emph type="italics"></emph>collectively<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>: now thoſe are pe­<lb></lb>riſhable, but theſe perpetual. </s>

<s>The Earth therefore ſince it <lb></lb>is reckoned amongſt thoſe things that are permanent, as hath <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg912"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>been ſaid already, hath its parts, not diſſipable, nor <emph type="italics"></emph>ab invicem,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>ſeparable from its Centre (whereby its true and proper place is <lb></lb>aſſigned it) and from its whole, taken collectively: becauſe ac­<lb></lb>cording to its whole it is always preſerved, compact, united, and <lb></lb>cohærent in it ſelf, nor can its parts be ſeperated from the Cen­<lb></lb>tre, or from one another, unleſs it may ſo fall out <emph type="italics"></emph>per accidens,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>and violently in ſome of its parts; which afterwards, the obſtacle <lb></lb>being removed, return to their Natural Station ſpontaneouſly, <lb></lb>and without any impulſe. </s>

<s>In this Senſe therefore the Earth is <lb></lb>ſaid to be Immoveable, and Immutable: yea even the Sea, Aire, <lb></lb>Heaven, and any other thing (although otherwiſe moveable) ſo <lb></lb>long as its parts are not diſſipable and ſeperable, may be ſaid to <lb></lb>be Immoveable, at leaſt taken <emph type="italics"></emph>collectively.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> This Principle <lb></lb>or Maxim differeth from the precedent only in that this referrs <lb></lb>to the parts in order to <emph type="italics"></emph>Place,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and this, in order to the Whole.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg912"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>The Earths Cen­<lb></lb>tre keepeth it in <lb></lb>its Natural Place.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>From this Speculation another Secret is diſcovered. </s>

<s>For hence <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg913"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>it is manifeſt wherein the proper and genuine formality of the <lb></lb>Gravity aad Levity of Bodyes conſiſteth; a point which is not ſo <lb></lb>clearly held forth, nor ſo undeniably explained by the Peripate­<lb></lb>tick Phyloſophy. <emph type="italics"></emph>Gravity<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> therefore is nothing elſe according to <lb></lb>the Principles of this new Opinion, than a certain power and ap­<lb></lb>petite of the Parts to rejoyn with their Whole, and there to reſt <lb></lb>as in their proper place. </s>

<s>Which Faculty or Diſpoſition is by <lb></lb>Divine Providence beſtowed not only on the Earth, and Ter­<lb></lb>rene Bodies, but, as is believed, on Cœleſtial Bodies alſo, name­<lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg914"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>ly the Sun, Moon, and Starrs; all whoſe parts are by this Impul­<lb></lb>ſion connected, and conſerved together, cleaving cloſely to each <lb></lb>other, and on all ſides preſſing towards their Centre, until they <lb></lb>come to reſt there. </s>

<s>From which Concourſe and Compreſſion a <lb></lb>Sphærical and Orbicular Figure of the Cæleſtial Orbes is produ­<lb></lb>ced, wherein by this occult Quality naturally incident to <lb></lb>each of them they of themſelves ſubſiſt, and are alwayes preſer­<lb></lb>ved. </s>

<s>But <emph type="italics"></emph>Levity<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> is the Extruſion and Excluſion of a more te­<lb></lb>nuoſe and thin Body from the Commerce of one more Solid and <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg915"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>denſe, that is Heterogeneal to it, by vertue of Heat. </s>

<s>Where­<lb></lb>upon, as the Motion of Grave Bodies is <emph type="italics"></emph>Compreſſive,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> ſo the Mo­<lb></lb>tion of Light Bodies is <emph type="italics"></emph>Extenſive:<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> For its the propperty of Heat <lb></lb>to dilate and rarify thoſe things to which it doth apply, conjoine <lb></lb>and communicate it ſelf. </s>

<s>And for this reaſon we find Levity <lb></lb>and Gravity not only in reſpect of this our Tereſtrial Globe, and <lb></lb>the Bodies adjacent to it, but alſo in reſpect of thoſe Bodies <lb></lb>which are ſaid to be in the Heavens, in which thoſe parts which 


<pb xlink:href="067/01/024.jpg" pagenum="494"></pb>by reaſon of their proclivity make towards their Centre are <lb></lb>Grave, and thoſe that incline to the Circumference Light. </s>

<s>And <lb></lb>ſo in the Sun, Moon, and Starrs, there are parts as well Grave as <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg916"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>Light. </s>

<s>And conſequently Heaven it ſelf that ſo Noble Body, <lb></lb>and of a fifth Eſſence, ſhall not be conſtituted of a Matter diffe­<lb></lb>rent from that of the Elements, being free from all Mutation in <lb></lb>it&#039;s Subſtance, Quantity, and Quality: Nor ſo admirable and <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg917"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>excellent as <emph type="italics"></emph>Ariſtotle<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> would make us to believe; nor yet a ſolid <lb></lb>Body, and impermeable; and much leſſe (as the generality of <lb></lb>men verily believe) of an impenetrable and moſt obdurate Den­<lb></lb>ſity: but in it (as this Opinion will have it) Comets may be ge­<lb></lb>nerated; and the Sun it ſelf, as tis probable, exhaling or attract­<lb></lb>ing ſundry vapours to the ſurface of its Body, may perhaps pro­<lb></lb>duce thoſe Spots which were obſerved to be ſo various, and irre­<lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg918"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>gular in its <emph type="italics"></emph>Diſcus<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>: of which <emph type="italics"></emph>Galilæus<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> in a perticular ^{*} Treatiſe <lb></lb>hath moſt excellently and moſt accurately ſpoken; inſomuch, <lb></lb>that though it were not beſides my preſent purpoſe, yet it is con­<lb></lb>venient that I forbear to ſpeak any thing touching thoſe matters, <lb></lb>leaſt I ſhould ſeem to do that which he hath done before me: But <lb></lb>now if there be found in the Sacred Scriptures any Authority <lb></lb>contrary to theſe things, it may be ſalved by the foreſaid Argu­<lb></lb>ments Analogically applyed. </s>

<s>And further more it may be ſaid, <lb></lb>that that Solidity is to be ſo underſtood, <emph type="italics"></emph>as that it admits of no <lb></lb>vacuum, cleft, or penetration from whence the leaſt vacuity might <lb></lb>proceed<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> For the truth is, as that cannot be admitted in bodily <lb></lb>Creatures, ſo it is likewiſe repugnant to Heaven it ſelf, being <lb></lb>indeed a Body of its own Nature the moſt Rare of all o­<lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg919"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>thers, and tenuoſe beyond all Humane Conception, and happly <lb></lb>hath the ſame proportion to the Aire, as the Aire to the <lb></lb>Water.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg913"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>Gravity and Le­<lb></lb>vity of Bodies, <lb></lb>what it is.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg914"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>All Cœleſtial Bo­<lb></lb>dies have Gravity <lb></lb>and Levety.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg915"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>Compreſſive Ma­<lb></lb>tion, proper to <lb></lb>Gravity; the Ex­<lb></lb>tenſive, to Levity.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg916"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>Heaven is not <lb></lb>compoſed of a fift <lb></lb>Eſſence differing <lb></lb>from the matter of <lb></lb>inferior Bodies.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg917"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>Nor yet a Solid <lb></lb>or denſe Body but <lb></lb>Rare.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg918"></margin.target>* Delle Macchie <lb></lb>ſolarj.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg919"></margin.target>* <emph type="italics"></emph>Vnius Corporis <lb></lb>fimplicis, unus eſt <lb></lb>motus ſimplex, et <lb></lb>huic duæ ſpecies, <lb></lb>Rectus &amp; Circu­<lb></lb>laris: Rectus du­<lb></lb>plex à medio, &amp; <lb></lb>ad medium; pri­<lb></lb>mus levium, ut A­<lb></lb>eris &amp; Ignis: ſe­<lb></lb>cundus gravium, <lb></lb>ut Aquæ &amp; Ter­<lb></lb>ræ: Circularis, <lb></lb>quieſt circa medi­<lb></lb>um competit Cœlo, <lb></lb>quod neque eſt <lb></lb>grave, neque leve.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>Ariſt. <emph type="italics"></emph>de Cœlo.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>Lib. 1.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>It is clear alſo from theſe Principles how falſe theſe words of <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Ariſtotle<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> are, that: <emph type="italics"></emph>Of one ſimple Body, there is one ſimple Motion<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>and this is of two kindes, Right and Circular: the Right is two­<lb></lb>fold, from the medium, and to the medium; the firſt of Light Bo­<lb></lb>dyes, as the Aire and Fire: the ſecond of Grave Bodyes, as the <lb></lb>Water and Earth: the Circular, which is about the medium, be­<lb></lb>longeth to Heaven, which is neither Grave nor Light<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>: For all this <lb></lb>Philoſophy is now forſaken, and of it ſelf grown into diſ-eſteem; <lb></lb>for though it be received for an unqueſtionable truth in this new <lb></lb>Opinion, that to a ſimple body appertains one only ſimple Moti­<lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg920"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>on, yet it granteth no Motion but what is Circular, by which alone <lb></lb>aſimple body is conſerved in its naturall Place, and ſubſiſts in its <lb></lb>Unity, and is properly ſaid to move <emph type="italics"></emph>in loco<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> [<emph type="italics"></emph>in a place<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>:] whereby <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg921"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>it comes to paſs that a Body for this reaſon doth continue to move <lb></lb>in it ſelf, [<emph type="italics"></emph>or about its own axis<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>;] and although it have a Motion, 


<pb xlink:href="067/01/025.jpg" pagenum="495"></pb>yet it abideth ſtill in the ſame place, as if it were perpetually im­<lb></lb>moveable. </s>

<s>But right Motion, which is properly <emph type="italics"></emph>ad locum, [to a <lb></lb>place]<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> can be aſcribed only to thoſe things which are out of their <lb></lb>naturall place, being far from union with one another, and from <lb></lb>unity with their whole, yea that are ſeperated and divided from <lb></lb>it: Which being that it is contrary to the Nature and forme of <lb></lb>the Univerſe, it neceſſarily followeth, that right Motion doth in <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg922"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>ſhort ſute with thoſe things which are deſtitute of that perfection, <lb></lb>that according to their proper Nature belongeth to them, and <lb></lb>which by this ſame right Motion they labour to obtaine, untill <lb></lb>they are redintigrated with their Whole, and with one another, <lb></lb>and reſtored to their Naturall place; in which at the length, <lb></lb>having obtained their perfection, they ſettle and remaine immove­<lb></lb>able. </s>

<s>Therefore in right Motions there can be no Uniformity, <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg923"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>nor ſimplicity; for that they vary by reaſon of the uncertaine <lb></lb>Levity or Gravity of their reſpective Bodyes: for which cauſe <lb></lb>they do not perſevere in the ſame Velocity or Tardity to the end <lb></lb>which they had in the beginning. </s>

<s>Hence we ſee that thoſe things <lb></lb>whoſe weight maketh them tend downwards, do deſcend at firſt <lb></lb>with a ſlow Motion; but afterwards, as they approach neerer <lb></lb>and neerer to the Centre, they precipitate more and more ſwiftly. <lb></lb></s>

<s>And on the otherſide, thoſe things which by reaſon of their light­<lb></lb>neſs are carryed upwards (as this our Terreſtriall fire, which is no­<lb></lb>thing elſe but a ſmoak that burneth, and is inkindled into a flame) <lb></lb>are no ſooner aſcended on high, but, in almoſt the ſelf-ſame mo­<lb></lb>ment, they fly and vaniſh out of fight; by reaſon of the rare­<lb></lb>faction and extenſion, that they as ſoon as they acquire, are freed <lb></lb>from thoſe bonds which violently and againſt their own Nature <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg924"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>kept them under, and deteined them here below. </s>

<s>For which <lb></lb>reaſon, it is very apparent, that no Right Motion can be called <lb></lb>Simple, not only in regard that (as hath been ſaid) it is not <lb></lb>^{*} even and uniforme, but alſo becauſe it is mixt with the Circu­<lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg925"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>lar, which lurketh in the Right by an occult conſent, <emph type="italics"></emph>ſcilicet<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> by <lb></lb>reaſon of the Natural affection of the Parts to conforme unto <lb></lb>their Whole. </s>

<s>For when the Whole moveth Circularly, it is re­<lb></lb>quiſite likewiſe that the Parts, to the end that they may be uni­<lb></lb>ted to their Whole, (howbeit <emph type="italics"></emph>per accidens<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> they are ſometimes <lb></lb>moved with a Right Motion) do move (though not ſo appa­<lb></lb>rently) with a Circular Motion, as doth their Whole. </s>

<s>And thus <lb></lb>at length we have evinced that Circular Motion only is Simple, <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg926"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>Uniform and ^{*} Æquable, and of the ſame tenor [<emph type="italics"></emph>or rate<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>] for that <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg927"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>it is never deſtitute of its interne Cauſe: whereas on the contra­<lb></lb>ry, Right Motion, (which pertains to things both Heavy and <lb></lb>Light) hath a Cauſe that is imperfect and deficient, yea that ari­<lb></lb>ſeth from Defect it ſelf, and that tendeth to, and ſeeketh after 


<pb xlink:href="067/01/026.jpg" pagenum="496"></pb>nothing elſe but the end and termination of it ſelf: in regard <lb></lb>that Grave and Light Bodies, when once they have attained their <lb></lb>proper and Natural Place, do deſiſt from that Motion to which <lb></lb>they were incited by Levity and Gravity. </s>

<s>Therefore: ſince Cir­<lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg928"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>cular Motion is proper <emph type="italics"></emph>to the Whole,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and Right Motion <emph type="italics"></emph>to the <lb></lb>Parts,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> theſe differences are not rightly referred to Motion, ſo as <lb></lb>to call one Motion Right, another Circular, as if they were not <lb></lb>conſiſtent with one another: For they may be both together, and <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg929"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>that Naturally, in the ſame Body; no leſſe than it is equally <lb></lb>Natural for a Man to participate of Senſe and Reaſon, ſeeing <lb></lb>that theſe differences are not directly oppoſite to one another. <lb></lb></s>

<s>Hereupon Reſt and Immobility only are oppoſed to Motion; <lb></lb>and not one Species of Motion to another. </s>

<s>And for the other <lb></lb>differences <emph type="italics"></emph>à medio, ad medium,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>circa medium,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> they are di­<lb></lb>ſtinguiſhed not <emph type="italics"></emph>really,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> but only <emph type="italics"></emph>formally,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> as the Point, Line and <lb></lb>Superficies, none of which can be without the other two, or <lb></lb>without a Body. </s>

<s>Hence it appears, that in as much as this Phy­<lb></lb>loſophy differs from that of <emph type="italics"></emph>Ariſtotle,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> ſo in like manner doth this <lb></lb>New Coſmographical Syſtem vary from the Common one, that <lb></lb>hath been hitherto received. </s>

<s>But this by the way, upon occaſion <lb></lb>of explaining the Fifth Maxim: For as to the truth or falſhood <lb></lb>of theſe foregoing Poſitions (although I conceive them very pro­<lb></lb>bable) I am reſolved to determine nothing at preſent, neither <lb></lb>ſhall I make any farther enquiry into them.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg920"></margin.target>* <emph type="italics"></emph>Vide Coperni­<lb></lb>cum de Revolutio­<lb></lb>nibus Cœleſt.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg921"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>Simple Motion <lb></lb>peculiar to only <lb></lb>Simple Bodies.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg922"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>Right Motion <lb></lb>belongeth to Im­<lb></lb>perfect Bodies, and <lb></lb>that are out of <lb></lb>their natural Pla­<lb></lb>ces.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg923"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>Right Motion <lb></lb>cannot be Simple.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg924"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>Right Motion is <lb></lb>ever mixt with <lb></lb>the Circular.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg925"></margin.target>* <emph type="italics"></emph>æquabilis.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg926"></margin.target>* <emph type="italics"></emph>Even.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg927"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>Circular Mo­<lb></lb>tion is truly Sim­<lb></lb>ple and Perpetual.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg928"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>Circular Mo­<lb></lb>tion belongeth to <lb></lb>the Whole Body, <lb></lb>and the Right to <lb></lb>its parts.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg929"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>Circular and <lb></lb>Right Motion co­<lb></lb>incedent, and may <lb></lb>conſiſt together in <lb></lb>the ſame Body.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>The Sixth and Laſt Maxim is this. </s>

<s>Every thing is Simply deno­<lb></lb>minated ſuch as it is in compariſon of all things, or of many <lb></lb>things which make the greater number of that kinde, but not in <lb></lb>reſpect of a few which make but the leſſer part of them. </s>

<s>As, <lb></lb>for inſtance, a Veſſel ſhall not be called abſolutely Great be­<lb></lb>cauſe it is ſo whilſt it is compared with two or three others: but <lb></lb>it ſhall be ſaid to be great abſolutely, and will be ſo, if it ex­<lb></lb>ceed in magnitude all indivials, or the greater part of them. </s>

<s>Nor <lb></lb>again ſhall a Man be ſaid to be abſolutely Big, becauſe he is big­<lb></lb>ger than a Pigmey; nor yet abſolutely Little, becauſe leſſe than <lb></lb>a Gyant: but he ſhall be termed abſolutely Big or Little in com­<lb></lb>pariſon of the ordinary Stature of the greater part of Men. </s>

<s>Thus <lb></lb>the Earth cannot abſolutely be ſaid to be High or Low for that it <lb></lb>is found to be ſo in reſpect of ſome ſmall part of the Univerſe; nor <lb></lb>again ſhall it be abſolutely affirmed to be High, being compared <lb></lb>to the Centre of the World, or ſome few parts of the Univerſe, <lb></lb>more near to the ſaid Centre, as is the <emph type="italics"></emph>Sun, Mercury<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> or <emph type="italics"></emph>Venus<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>: <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg930"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>but it ſhall receive its abſolute denomination according as it ſhall <lb></lb>be found to be in compariſon of the greater number of the <lb></lb>Spheres and Bodies of the Univerſe. </s>

<s>The Earth therefore, in <lb></lb>compariſon of the whole Circuit of the Eighth Sphære which in­


<pb xlink:href="067/01/027.jpg" pagenum="497"></pb>cludeth all Corporeal Creatures, and in compariſon of <emph type="italics"></emph>Jupiter, <lb></lb>Mars,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>Saturn<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> together with the <emph type="italics"></emph>Moon,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and much more in <lb></lb>compariſon of other Bodies, (if any ſuch there be) above the <lb></lb>Eighth Sphere and eſpecially the Empyrial Heaven, may be truly <lb></lb>ſaid to be in the loweſt place of the World, and almoſt in the <lb></lb>Centre of it; nor can it he ſaid to be above any of them, except <lb></lb>the <emph type="italics"></emph>Sun, Mercury<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>Venus<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>: So that one may apply unto it the <lb></lb>name of an Infime and Low, but not a Supreme or Middle Body. <lb></lb></s>

<s>And ſo to come down from Heaven, eſpecially the Empyrian, to it <lb></lb>(as it is accepted in the Deſcent of Chriſt from Heaven to his Holy <lb></lb>Incarnation) and from it to go up to Heaven (as in Chriſts return <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg931"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>to Heaven in his Glorious Aſcention) is truly and properly to <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Deſcend<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> from the Circumference to the Centre, and to <emph type="italics"></emph>aſcend<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>from the parts which are neareſt to the Centre of the World <lb></lb>to its utmoſt Circumference. </s>

<s>This Maxim therefore may eaſily <lb></lb>and according to truth explain Theologicall Propoſitions: and <lb></lb>this is ſo much the more confirmed, in that (as I have obſerved) <lb></lb>almoſt all Texts of Sacred Scripture which oppoſe the Earth to <lb></lb>Heaven, are moſt conveniently and aptly underſtood of the Em­<lb></lb>pyrial Heaven (being the Higheſt of all the Heavens, and Spiritual <lb></lb>in reſpect of its end) but not of the inferiour or intermediate Hea­<lb></lb>vens, which are a Corporeal, and were framed for the benefit of <lb></lb>Corporeal Creatures: and thus when in the Plural Number <lb></lb>Heavens are mentioned, then all the Heavens promiſcuouſly and <lb></lb>without diſtinction are to be underſtood, as well the Empyrian <lb></lb>it ſelf as the Inferiour Heavens. </s>

<s>And this Expoſition indeed any <lb></lb>man (that doth but take notice of it) may find to be moſt true. <lb></lb></s>

<s>And ſo for this Reaſon the Third Heaveu into which St. <emph type="italics"></emph>Paul<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg932"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>was wrapt up, by this Maxim may be taken for the Empyrean: <lb></lb>if for the the Firſt Heaven we underſtand that immenſe Space of <lb></lb>Erratick and Moveable Bodies illuminated by the Sun, in which <lb></lb>are comprehended the Planets, as alſo the Earth moveable, and <lb></lb>the Sun immoveable, Who like a King upon his Auguſt Tribu­<lb></lb>nal, ſits with venerable Majeſty immoveable and conſtant in <lb></lb>Centre of all the Sphæres, and, with his Divine Beames, doth <lb></lb>bountifully exhilerate all Cœleſtial Bodies that ſtand in need of <lb></lb>his vital Light, for which they cravingly wander about him; and <lb></lb>doth liberally and on every ſide comfort and illuſtrate the Thea­<lb></lb>tre of the whole World, and all its parts, even the very leaſt, like <lb></lb>an immortal and perpetual Lamp of high and unſpeakable va­<lb></lb>lue. </s>

<s>The Second Heaven ſhall be the Starry Heaven, common­<lb></lb>ly called the Eighth Sphære, or the Firmament, wherein are all <lb></lb>the Fixed Starrs, which according to this Opinion of <emph type="italics"></emph>Pythagoras,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>is (like as the Sun and Centre) void of all Motion, the Centre <lb></lb>and utmoſt Circumference mutually agreeing with each other in 


<pb xlink:href="067/01/028.jpg" pagenum="498"></pb>Immobility. </s>

<s>And the Third ſhall be the Empyrean Heaven, that <lb></lb>is the Seat of the Bleſſed. </s>

<s>And in this manner we may come to <lb></lb>explain and underſtand that admirable Secret, and profound My­<lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg933"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>ſtery ænigmatically revealed by <emph type="italics"></emph>Plato<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> to <emph type="italics"></emph>Dionyſius<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> of <emph type="italics"></emph>Syracuſe<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>: <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg934"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>(a) All things are about the King of all things, Second things <lb></lb>about the ſecond, and Third things about the Third<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>: For that <lb></lb>God being the Centre of Spiritual things, the Sun, of Cor­<lb></lb>poreal, Chriſt, of thoſe that are Mixt, or made up of both, things <lb></lb>do doubtleſſe depend of that of theſe three Centres that is moſt <lb></lb>correſpondent and proportionable to them, and the Centre is <lb></lb>ever adjudged to be the nobler and worthier place: and therefore <lb></lb>in Animals the Heart, in Vegitables the Pith or Kernell wherein <lb></lb>the Seed lyeth that conſerveth their perpetuity, and virtually in­<lb></lb>cludes the whole Plant, are in the Midſt, and in the Centre: and <lb></lb>thus much ſhall ſuffice to have hinted at, ſince there may another <lb></lb>occaſion offer it ſelf for a larger Explication of theſe things. </s>

<s>By <lb></lb>this Maxim the Authorities and Arguments of the Third Fourth <lb></lb>and Fifth Claſſes are reſolved.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg930"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>The Earth in <lb></lb>what ſenſe it may <lb></lb>abſolutely be ſaid <lb></lb>to be in the loweſt <lb></lb>part of the World.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg931"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>Chriſt in his <lb></lb>Incarnation tru­<lb></lb>ly deſcended from <lb></lb>Heaven, and in <lb></lb>his Aſcenſion tru­<lb></lb>ly aſcended into <lb></lb>Heaven.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg932"></margin.target>2 Cor. </s>

<s>c. </s>

<s>12. v. <lb></lb></s>

<s>3. <emph type="italics"></emph>Whether in the <lb></lb>body or out of the <lb></lb>body, I cannot tell, <lb></lb>The Sun is King, <lb></lb>Heart and Lamp <lb></lb>of the World him­<lb></lb>ſelf being<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> <foreign lang="grc">αυταρκης</foreign><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>abſolutely indepen­<lb></lb>dent.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>)</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg933"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>The Ænignsa of <lb></lb>Plato.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg934"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(a) Circa omni­<lb></lb>um Regem ſunt <lb></lb>omnia. </s>

<s>&amp; Secun­<lb></lb>da circa Secun­<lb></lb>dum, et Tertia <lb></lb>circa Tertium: <lb></lb>Vide<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Theodo. </s>

<s>de <lb></lb>Græc. </s>

<s>affect. </s>

<s>curat. <lb></lb></s>

<s>lib. 

2. Steuch. </s>

<s>lib. <lb></lb></s>

<s>de Parennj. </s>

<s>Phi­<lb></lb>loſo.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>It may be added withall, that even the <emph type="italics"></emph>Sun, Mercury<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>Ve­<lb></lb>nus<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> (that is to ſay in reſpect of the Earth) are to be thought <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>aboue,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and not <emph type="italics"></emph>beneath<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> the Earth it ſelf, although in reſpect of <lb></lb>the Univerſe, yea and alſo abſolutely, they are <emph type="italics"></emph>below.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> The rea­<lb></lb>ſon is, becauſe in reſpect of the Earth they alwayes appear above <lb></lb>its Surface: and although they do not environe it, yet by the <lb></lb>Motion of the ſaid Earth they behold one while one part, another <lb></lb>while another part of its Circumference. </s>

<s>Since therefore thoſe <lb></lb>things which in a Sphærical Body are nearer to the Circumfe­<lb></lb>rence and more remote from the Cenrre are ſaid to be <emph type="italics"></emph>above,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> but <lb></lb>thoſe that are next adjoyning to the Centre are ſaid to be <emph type="italics"></emph>below<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; <lb></lb>it clearly followeth that whilſt the <emph type="italics"></emph>Sun, Mercury<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>Venus<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> are <lb></lb>not only turned towards the Surface and Circumference of the <lb></lb>ſaid Earth, but are at a very great diſtance without it, ſucceſſively <lb></lb>turned about it, and every way have a view of it, and are very <lb></lb>far remote from its Centre, they may, in reſpect of the ſaid Earth, <lb></lb>be ſaid to be <emph type="italics"></emph>above<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> it; as alſo on the other ſide, the Earth in <lb></lb>reſpect of them may be ſaid to be <emph type="italics"></emph>beneath<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>: howbeit on the con­<lb></lb>trary, in reſpect of the Univerſe, the Earth in reality is much <lb></lb>higher than they. </s>

<s>And thus is ſalved the Authority of <emph type="italics"></emph>Eccleſi-<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg935"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>aſtes<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> in many places, expreſſing thoſe things that are, or are done <lb></lb>on the Eeath in theſe words, <emph type="italics"></emph>Which are done, or which are under<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg936"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>the Sun,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> And in the ſame manner thoſe words are reduced to their <lb></lb>true Senſe wherein it is ſaid, That we are <emph type="italics"></emph>under the Sun,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>un­<lb></lb>der the Moon,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> whereupon Terrene things are expreſſed by the <lb></lb>name of <emph type="italics"></emph>Sublunary.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg935"></margin.target>Eccleſ. </s>

<s>c. </s>

<s>1. 2. 3. <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>and almoſt tho­<lb></lb>out.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg936"></margin.target>* <emph type="italics"></emph>Quod fiunt, vel <lb></lb>ſunt ſub ſole.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>The Sixth Claſſis threatneth a difficulty which is common as 


<pb xlink:href="067/01/029.jpg" pagenum="499"></pb>well to this of <emph type="italics"></emph>Copernicus,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> as to the Vulgar Opinion; ſo that they <lb></lb>are both alike concerned in the ſolution of it: But ſo far as it <lb></lb>oppoſeth that of <emph type="italics"></emph>Copernicus,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> its anſwer is eaſy from the Firſt <lb></lb>Maxim.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>But that which is added in the Fourth Claſſe, That it follow­<lb></lb>eth from this Opinion, that Hell (for that it is included by the <lb></lb>Earth, as is commonly held) doth move circularly about the <lb></lb>Sun, and in Heaven, and that ſo Hell it ſelf will be found to be <lb></lb>in Heaven; diſcovers, in my judgment, nothing but Ignorance <lb></lb>and Calumny, that inſinuate the belief of their Arguments ra­<lb></lb>ther by a corrupt ſenſe of the Words, than by ſolid Reaſons <lb></lb>taken from the boſome of the Nature of things. </s>

<s>For in this <lb></lb>place Heaven is no wiſe to be taken for Paradice, nor according <lb></lb>to the Senſe of Common Opinion, but (as hath been ſaid above) <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg937"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>according to the <emph type="italics"></emph>Copernican<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Hypotheſis, for the ſubtileſt and <lb></lb>Pureſt Aire, far more tenuous and rare than this of ours; where­<lb></lb>upon the Solid Bodies of the Stars, Moon, and Earth, in their <lb></lb>Circular and Ordinary Motions, do paſſe thorow it, (the Sphære <lb></lb>of Fire being by this Opinion taken away.) And as according <lb></lb>to the Common Opinion it was no abſurdity to ſay, That Hell <lb></lb>being demerged in the Centre of the Earth and of the World it <lb></lb>ſelf, hath Heaven and Paradice above and below it, yea and on <lb></lb>all ſides of it, and that it is in the middle of all the Cœleſtial <lb></lb>Bodies (as if it were poſited in a more unworthy place) ſo, nei­<lb></lb>ther in this will it be deemed an Error, if from the other Syſtem, <lb></lb>which differeth not much from the Vulgar one, thoſe or the like <lb></lb>things follow as do in that. </s>

<s>For both in that of <emph type="italics"></emph>Copernicus,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <lb></lb>the Vulgar Hypotheſis, Hell is ſuppoſed to be placed amongſt the <lb></lb>very dreggs of the Elements, and in the Centre of the Earth it <lb></lb>ſelf, for the confinement and puniſhment of the damned. </s>

<s>There­<lb></lb>fore we ought not for want of Reaſons to trifle away time in <lb></lb>vain and impertinent ſtrife about words, ſince their true Senſe <lb></lb>is clouded then with no obſcurity, and in regard that it is very <lb></lb>clear to any man indued with a refined Intellect, and that hath <lb></lb>but an indifferent judgment in the Liberal Arts, and eſpecially <lb></lb>in the Mathematicks, that the ſame, or not very different Gon­<lb></lb>ſequences do flow from both theſe Opinions.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg937"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>Heaven accord­<lb></lb>ing to Copernicus <lb></lb>is the ſame with <lb></lb>the moſt tenuous <lb></lb>Æther; but dif­<lb></lb>ferent from Para­<lb></lb>dice, which ſar­<lb></lb>paſſeth all the <lb></lb>Heavens.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>By theſe Maxims and their Interpretations it appears, that <lb></lb>the <emph type="italics"></emph>Pythagorick<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>Copernican<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Opinion is ſo probable, that its <lb></lb>poſſible it may exceed even the <emph type="italics"></emph>Ptolemaick<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> in probability; and <lb></lb>ſince there may be deduced from it a moſt ordinate Syſteme, and <lb></lb>a mroe admirable and myſterious Hypotheſis of the World <lb></lb>than from that of <emph type="italics"></emph>Ptolomy:<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> the Authorities of Sacred Scripture <lb></lb>and Theological Tenents in the mean while not oppoſing it, be­<lb></lb>ing opportunely and appoſitely (as I have ſhown how they may 


<pb xlink:href="067/01/030.jpg" pagenum="500"></pb>be) reconciled with it: And ſince that by it not only the Phœ­<lb></lb>nomena of all the Cœleſtial Bodies are moſt readily ſalved, but <lb></lb>alſo many Natural Reaſons are diſcovered, which could not o­<lb></lb>therwiſe, (but with extream difficulty) have been found out: <lb></lb>And ſince it, laſt of all, doth open a more eaſy way into Aſtro­<lb></lb>nomy and Phyloſophy, and rejecteth all thoſe ſuperfluous and <lb></lb>imaginary inventions produced by Aſtronomers to the end only, <lb></lb>that they might be able by them to render a reaſon of the ſo ma­<lb></lb>ny and ſo various Motions of the Cœleſtial Orbs.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>And who knows, but that in that admirable compoſure of the <lb></lb>Candleſtick which was to be placed in the Tabernacle of God, he <lb></lb>might out of his extraordinary love to us have been pleaſed to <lb></lb>ſhaddow forth unto us the Syſteme of the Univerſe, and more <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg938"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>eſpecially of the Planets? <emph type="italics"></emph>(a) Thou ſhalt make a Candleſtick of<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg939"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>pure Gold,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> (ſaith the Text;) <emph type="italics"></emph>of beaten work ſhall it be made: <lb></lb>his Shaft, and his Branches, his Bowls, his Knops, and his <lb></lb>Flowers (b) ſhall be of the ſame.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Here are five things deſcribed, the <lb></lb>Shaft of the Candleſtick in the midle, the Branches on the ſides, <lb></lb>the Bowls, the Knops and the Flowers. </s>

<s>And ſince there can be no <lb></lb>more Shafts but one, the Branches are immediatly deſcribed in <lb></lb>theſe <emph type="italics"></emph>(c)<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> words: <emph type="italics"></emph>Six Branches ſhall come out of the ſides of it: <lb></lb>three Branches out of the one ſide, and three Branches out of the <lb></lb>other ſide:<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Happly theſe fix Branches may point out to us ſix <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>(d)<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Heavens, which are moved about the Sun in this order; <emph type="italics"></emph>Saturn,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>the ſloweſt and moſt remote of all, finiſheth his courſe about the <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg940"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>Sun thorrow all the twelve Signes of the Zodiack in thirty Years: <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg941"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Jupiter,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> being nearer than he, in twelve Years: <emph type="italics"></emph>Mars,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> being yet <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg942"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>nearer than him, in two Years: The <emph type="italics"></emph>Earth,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> which is ſtill nearer <lb></lb>than he, doth perform the ſame Revolution, together with <lb></lb>the Orbe of the <emph type="italics"></emph>Moon,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> in the ſpace of a Year, that is in Twelve <lb></lb>Months: <emph type="italics"></emph>Venus,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> which is yet nearer than all theſe, in <emph type="italics"></emph>(e)<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 9 Months: <lb></lb>And laſt of all <emph type="italics"></emph>Mercury,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> whoſe vicinity to the Sun is the greateſt <lb></lb>of all, accompliſheth its whole converſion about the Sun in eighty <lb></lb>Dayes. </s>

<s>After the deſcription of the ſix Branches, the ſacred <lb></lb>Text proceeds to the deſcription of the Bowls, the Knops, and <lb></lb>the Flowers, ſaying, <emph type="italics"></emph>(f) Three Bowls made like unto Almonds, <lb></lb>with a Knop and a Flower in one Branch; and three Bowls made <lb></lb>like Almonds in the other Branch, with a Knop and a Flower: this <lb></lb>ſhall be the work of the ſix Branches that come out of the Shaft. <lb></lb></s>

<s>And in the Candleſtick ſhall be four Bowls made like unto Al­<lb></lb>monds, with their Knops and their Flowers: there ſhall be a knop <lb></lb>under two branches of the ſame, and a Knop under two Branches <lb></lb>of the ſame, and a Knop under two Branches of the ſame; which <lb></lb>together are ſix Branches, proceeding from one Shaft.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> The truth <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg943"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>is, the ſhallowneſſe of my underſtanding cannot fathome the 


<pb xlink:href="067/01/031.jpg" pagenum="501"></pb>depth of all the Myſteries that are couched in this moſt wiſe <lb></lb>diſpoſure of things: nevertheleſſe being amazed, and tranſported <lb></lb>with admiration, I will ſay; Who knows but that thoſe three <lb></lb>Bowls like unto Almonds to be repreſented on each of the <lb></lb>Branches of the Candleſtick may ſignifie thoſe Globes which are <lb></lb>apter (as is this our Earth) for the receiving than emitting of Influ­<lb></lb>ences? </s>

<s>Perhaps alſo they denote thoſe Globes of late diſcovered <lb></lb>by the help of the Optick Teleſcope, which participate with <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Saturn, Jupiter, Venus,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and poſſibly alſo with the other Planets? <lb></lb></s>

<s>Who knows likewiſe, but that there may be ſome occult propor­<lb></lb>tion between theſe Globes and thoſe Myſterious Knops and <lb></lb>Lilies inſinuated unto us in the ſacred Scriptures? </s>

<s>But this <lb></lb>ſhall here ſuffice to bound humane Preſumption, and to teach us <lb></lb>to exſpect with an Harpocratick ſilence from Time, the Indice of <lb></lb>Truth, a diſcovery of theſe Myſteries: <emph type="italics"></emph>(g) Solomon<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> made ten <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg944"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>Candleſticks by the ſame Patern of <emph type="italics"></emph>Moſes,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> which he placed, five <lb></lb>on one hand and five on another, in the Temple erected by him <lb></lb>in honour of the moſt High God; which very thing doth alſo, <lb></lb>without all queſtion, contain moſt abſtruſe ſigniſications. </s>

<s>More­<lb></lb>over, that Apple of the Knowledg of Good and Evil prohibited <lb></lb>our firſt Parents by God is not without a Myſtery; which ſome <lb></lb>ſay was an Indian Figg. </s>

<s>In which theſe things are to be obſerv­<lb></lb>ed: Firſt, That it is replete with many Kernels, every one of <lb></lb>which hath a particular Centre. </s>

<s>Secondly, Though of it ſelf it <lb></lb>be hard and ſolid, yet about its Circumference it is of a more rare <lb></lb>and tenuouſe ſubſtance; herein reſembling the Earth, which <lb></lb>though in its Centre, and thoſe parts which are neareſt to it, it <lb></lb>be ſtony, Metallick, and compact, yet the nearer one approacheth <lb></lb>to the Circumference, its parts are ſeen to be the more rare and <lb></lb>tenuouſe: and withall it hath another body, more rare than its <lb></lb>own, namely the Water, above which there is yet another, more <lb></lb>ſubtil than all the reſt of inferiour Bodyes, that is to ſay, <lb></lb>the Aire,</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg938"></margin.target>(a) Exod. </s>

<s>25. 31.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg939"></margin.target>(b) <emph type="italics"></emph>My Authour <lb></lb>following the vul­<lb></lb>gar Tranſlation, <lb></lb>which hath an E­<lb></lb>ligance in ſome <lb></lb>things beyond ours, <lb></lb>cites the words <lb></lb>thus,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Facies Can­<lb></lb>delabrum ducti­<lb></lb>le de auro mun­<lb></lb>diſſimo, Haſtile <lb></lb>ejus, &amp; Calamos, <lb></lb>&amp; Sphærulas, ac <lb></lb>Lilia, ex ipſo pro­<lb></lb>cedentia.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg940"></margin.target>(c) <emph type="italics"></emph>verſe<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 12.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg941"></margin.target>(d) <emph type="italics"></emph>or Spheres.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg942"></margin.target>(e) <emph type="italics"></emph>Though our <lb></lb>Authour ſpeaketh <lb></lb>here poſitively of <lb></lb>nine Months,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> &amp;c. <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Fathers are not a­<lb></lb>greed about the pe­<lb></lb>riod of this planet, <lb></lb>nor that of<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Mercu­<lb></lb>ry, <emph type="italics"></emph>as you may ſee <lb></lb>at large in<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Riccio­<lb></lb>lus, Almageſt. </s>

<s>nov. <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Tom. </s>

<s>1. part 1. l. <lb></lb></s>

<s>7. ſect. </s>

<s>3. cha. </s>

<s>11. <lb></lb>num. </s>

<s>11. page 627. <lb></lb>where he maketh<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>Venus <emph type="italics"></emph>to conſum­<lb></lb>mate her Revolu­<lb></lb>tion in neer 225 <lb></lb>dayes, or 7 1/2 Mon. <lb></lb></s>

<s>and<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Mecury <emph type="italics"></emph>in a­<lb></lb>bout 88 dayes, or 3 <lb></lb>Months: in which <lb></lb>he followeth<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Kepl. <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>in Epitome Aſtro­<lb></lb>nom. </s>

<s>p.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 760.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg943"></margin.target>(f) <emph type="italics"></emph>verſ.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 33, 34.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg944"></margin.target>(g) 1 Kings <emph type="italics"></emph>c.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 7. <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>v.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 49. 2 Chron. <emph type="italics"></emph>c.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>4. <emph type="italics"></emph>verſ.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 7.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>The ſame Repreſentation with that of the Indian Figg is held <lb></lb>forth to us by the <emph type="italics"></emph>Malum Punicum,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> or Pomegranate, with its <lb></lb>innumerable poly centrick Stones or Kernels, all which in the parts <lb></lb>more remote from their Centre, and nearer approaching towards <lb></lb>the Circumference, are of a ſubſtance ſo ſubtil and rare, that being <lb></lb>but lightly compreſſed, they in a manner wholly convert into a <lb></lb>moſt tenuoſe Liquor or juice: Of which fruit it pleaſed Divine <lb></lb>Wiſdom to make mention, and ordained that its Figure ſhould be <lb></lb>imbroidered and wrought with a needle in the <emph type="italics"></emph>ſacerdotal<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Garment <lb></lb>of <emph type="italics"></emph>Aaron: (h) Beneath<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> (ſaith God) <emph type="italics"></emph>upon the hem of it thou<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg945"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>ſhalt make Pomegranates of blew, and of purple, and of ſcarlet, <lb></lb>round about the border thereof; and Bells of gold between them<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>


<pb xlink:href="067/01/032.jpg" pagenum="502"></pb><emph type="italics"></emph>round about: a golden bell and a pomegranate, a golden bell and a <lb></lb>pomegranate, upon the hem of the Robe round about.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> And that this <lb></lb>was a Myſtical Repreſentation of the Worlds Effigies, is averred <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg946"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>by <emph type="italics"></emph>Solomon,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> ſaying; <emph type="italics"></emph>(i) For in the long (k) Garment that be <lb></lb>had on was the (l) whole World; and in the foure rows of the ſtones<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg947"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>was the Glory of the Fathers graven, and thy Majeſty in the Di-<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg948"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>adem of his Head.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg945"></margin.target>(h) Exod. </s>

<s>28. 33, <lb></lb>34, &amp; 39. v. </s>

<s>24, <lb></lb>25, 26.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg946"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(i)<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Sap. </s>

<s>c. </s>

<s>18. v. <lb></lb></s>

<s>24.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg947"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(k)<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Exod. </s>

<s>c. </s>

<s>28. <lb></lb>v. </s>

<s>6, 9. 17, 36.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg948"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(l)<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Or, <emph type="italics"></emph>totus Or­<lb></lb>bis Terrarum,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> as <lb></lb>the vulgar Tranſ­<lb></lb>lation hath it.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>The ſame likewiſe is ſignified to us by the Grape, and in like <lb></lb>manner by all other Fruits; but eſpecially the Figg, Grape, and <lb></lb>Pomegranate: whence theſe three are almoſt alwayes placed to­<lb></lb>gether in the Sacred Scriptures. </s>

<s>So <emph type="italics"></emph>Numb.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 20. the People of Iſra­<lb></lb>el complain againſt <emph type="italics"></emph>Moſes<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>Aaron: (m) Wherefore have you<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg949"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>made us to come up out of Egypt, to bring us into this evil place, <lb></lb>where there can grow no Seed, neither is there either Figgs, or <lb></lb>Vines, or Pomegranates<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>? </s>

<s>Intimating that theſe kinds of Fruits <lb></lb>were preferred by them for their excellency before all others. <lb></lb></s>

<s>And in <emph type="italics"></emph>Joel (n) The Vine is dryed up, and the Figg-tree languiſh-<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg950"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>eth, the Pomegranate-trce, the Palm-tree alſo, and the Apple-tree, <lb></lb>even all the Trees of the field are withered; becauſe joy is wither­<lb></lb>ed away from the Sons of Men.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Likewiſe in <emph type="italics"></emph>Haggai: (o) Is the<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg951"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>ſeed yet in the Bud? </s>

<s>and hath as yet the Vine and the Fig-tree, <lb></lb>and the Pomegranate, and the Olive-tree brought forth<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>? </s>

<s>In like <lb></lb>manner in <emph type="italics"></emph>Deuteronomie<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> the Land of Promiſe is commended to <lb></lb>be <emph type="italics"></emph>(p) A Land of Wheat, and Barly, and Vines in which grow,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg952"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Figg-trees, and Pomegranates, and Olive-trees,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> &amp;c. </s>

<s>And in the <lb></lb>Structure of the Temple undertaken by <emph type="italics"></emph>Solomon<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> upon Divine In­<lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg953"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>ſpiration the <emph type="italics"></emph>(q)<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Chapiters of the Pillars were adorned with ſeve­<lb></lb>ral rowes of Pomegranates: which particular is mentioned, not <lb></lb>in one but many places of Holy Writ. </s>

<s>Yea and ſometimes acci­<lb></lb>dentally and occaſionally the Holy hath Ghoſt ænigmatically re­<lb></lb>preſented this moſt admirable and Moſt Wiſe Sructure of the <lb></lb>World, the Order of the Heavens, and the diſpoſure of Crea­<lb></lb>tures Spiritual and Corporeal by Emblems, Parables, and Figures, <lb></lb>leaſt they ſhould be as it were dazled and blinded, by the reful­<lb></lb>gent ſplendor of ſo excellent an Object. </s>

<s>Hence we ſee, that in <lb></lb>theſe Doctrinal &amp; Dubious Points we may diſcourſe in ſuch man­<lb></lb>ner by help of the Holy Scripture as is meet for the underſtanding <lb></lb>of the Prophets; which ſeeing they are very obſcure, they ſhall be <lb></lb>fully underſtood, and may be aptly applyed only then when they <lb></lb>ſhall be fulfilled, and not before: So alſo when once the true <lb></lb>Syſteme of the Univerſe is found out, then, and not till then, the <lb></lb>meaning of theſe Figures, and Ænigma&#039;s ſhall be made known <lb></lb>unto us: Thus before the coming of the Son of God had diſco­<lb></lb>vered unto us the Myſtery of the Holy Trinity, none were able <lb></lb>to comprehend or imagine what was concealed under thoſe 


<pb xlink:href="067/01/033.jpg" pagenum="503"></pb>words; <emph type="italics"></emph>(r) In Principio creavit Elohim Cœlum &amp; Terram:<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> for <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg954"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>that they did not ſee how the Noun Plural <emph type="italics"></emph>Elohim<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> (which is as much <lb></lb>as to ſay <emph type="italics"></emph>Dij,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> [Gods] ſhould be joyned with the Verb Singular, <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Creavit<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>: But the Myſtery of the Unity of Eſſence and Trinity <lb></lb>of Perſons in God being revealed, it was preſently known, that <lb></lb>the Singular Number, <emph type="italics"></emph>Creavit,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> had reference to the Unity of Eſ­<lb></lb>ſence, (in regard that the Works of the Trinity <emph type="italics"></emph>ad extra<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> are in­<lb></lb>diviſible) and the Plural, <emph type="italics"></emph>Elohim,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> to the Perſons. </s>

<s>Who, I pray, <lb></lb>in elder times could have found out this Myſtery? </s>

<s>And thus the <lb></lb>Name of God is thrice repeated in <emph type="italics"></emph>Pſal. </s>

<s>67. (s) God, even our<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg955"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>God ſhall bleſſe us, God ſhall bleſſe us, &amp;c.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Which at firſt might <lb></lb>ſeem a Pleonaſme, and ſuperfluous repetition; but afterwards it <lb></lb>was evident that <emph type="italics"></emph>David<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> did there ſet out the Benedictions of ſe­<lb></lb>veral Perſons implyed, to wit, the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt. <lb></lb></s>

<s>Innumerable Examples of the like kind may be found in the Sa­<lb></lb>cred Leaves. </s>

<s>Therefore, to conclude, I will ſay with ^{*}<emph type="italics"></emph>David,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg956"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Pſal.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 92. <emph type="italics"></emph>Oh Lord how glorious are thy Works! thy thoughts <lb></lb>are very deep: an unwiſeman knoweth not, and a fool doth not <lb></lb>underſtand theſe things.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg949"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(m)<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Numb. c. &gt;20. <lb></lb>v. 5.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg950"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(n)<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Joel c. </s>

<s>1. v. </s>

<s>12.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg951"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(o)<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Hagg. c. 2. <lb></lb>v. 19.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg952"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(p)<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Deut. c. 8. v. 8.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg953"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(q)<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 1 Kings c 7. <lb></lb>v. 20. &amp; 2 Kings <lb></lb>c. 25. v. 17. &amp; <lb></lb>2 Chro. c. 3. v. 15, <lb></lb>16. &amp; c. 4. v. 
12. <lb></lb>13. &amp; Jerem. c. <lb></lb>52. v. 21, 22.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg954"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(r)<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Gen. c. 1. v. 1</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg955"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(s) P<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>ſal. 67. v. 6 <lb></lb>7.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg956"></margin.target>* Pſal. 92 v. 536.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>Theſe are the particulars that I have thought fit to offer, as <lb></lb>a Divine, concerning the not-improbable Opinion of the Mobili­<lb></lb>ty of the Earth and Stability of the Sun: which I hope will be <lb></lb>acceptable to you, Reverend Sir, out of the love and diligence <lb></lb>wherewith you perſue Virtue and Learning. </s>

<s>But (to the end <lb></lb>that you may alſo receive an account of my other Studies) I <lb></lb>hope very ſhortly to publiſh in Print my Second Tome ^{*}<emph type="italics"></emph>Of the In-<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg957"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>ſtitutions of all Learnings,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> which ſhall containe all the Liberall <lb></lb>Arts, as I have already ſignified in that <emph type="italics"></emph>Syntax,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>Spicimen<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> by <lb></lb>me heretofore put forth, and publiſhed under your Name. </s>

<s>The <lb></lb>other five following Tomes by me promiſed (which ſhall treat of <lb></lb>Phyloſophy and Theology) are not altogether ſo forward, ne­<lb></lb>vertheleſs they will be ſpeedily finiſhed. </s>

<s>In the mean time there <lb></lb>will come forth my Book <emph type="italics"></emph>Concerning ^{*} Oracles,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> now finiſhed, to­<lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg958"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>gether with a Treatiſe ^{*} <emph type="italics"></emph>Of Artificial Divination.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> And for a <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg959"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>pledge thereof, I ſend you at this time annexed to this Epiſtle a <lb></lb>Tract ^{*} <emph type="italics"></emph>Concerning Natural Coſmological Divination,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> or of Natu­<lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg960"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>ral Prognoſticks, and Preſages of the Changes oſ Weather, and <lb></lb>other things which fall within the compaſſe of Natue. </s>

<s>God grant <lb></lb>you all Happineſſe.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg957"></margin.target>* <emph type="italics"></emph>Inſtitutionum<lb></lb>omnium Doctri­<lb></lb>narum.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg958"></margin.target>* <emph type="italics"></emph>De Oraculis.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg959"></margin.target>* <emph type="italics"></emph>De Divinatio­<lb></lb>ne artificioſa.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg960"></margin.target>* <emph type="italics"></emph>De Divinatio­<lb></lb>ne Naturali Coſ­<lb></lb>mologica.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="head">

<s><emph type="italics"></emph>Moſt Reverend Sir<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s><emph type="italics"></emph>NAPLES,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> from the Covent <lb></lb>of the <emph type="italics"></emph>Carmelites,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Jan. <lb></lb></s>

<s>6. 1615.</s></p><p type="main">

<s><emph type="italics"></emph>Your Moſt Humble Servant<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s><emph type="italics"></emph>PAOLO ANTONIO FOSCARINI.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="head">

<s>FINIS.</s></p><pb xlink:href="067/01/034.jpg"></pb><p type="head">

<s><emph type="italics"></emph>Imprimatur,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> P. ANT. GHIBERT, <emph type="italics"></emph>Vic. Gen.</s><emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><s>JOANNES LONGUS <emph type="italics"></emph>Can. &amp; Cur. Archiep. <lb></lb>Neap.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> THEOL. <emph type="italics"></emph>Vidit.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p> 		</chap>		</body>		<back></back>	</text></archimedes>