<?xml version="1.0"?>
<archimedes xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" >      <info>
	<author>Galilei, Galileo and others</author>
	<title>Doctrine of the Holy Fathers</title>
	<date>1661</date>
	<place>London</place>
	<translator>Salusbury, Thomas</translator>
	<lang>en</lang>
	<cvs_file>galil_doctr_066_en_1661.xml</cvs_file>
	<cvs_version></cvs_version>
	<locator>066.xml</locator>
</info>      <text>          <front> <section>	<pb xlink:href="066/01/001.jpg"></pb><p type="head">

<s>THE <lb></lb>Ancient and Modern <lb></lb>DOCTRINE <lb></lb>OF <lb></lb>Holy Fathers, <lb></lb>AND <lb></lb>Iudicious Divines,</s></p><p type="head">

<s>CONCERNING</s></p><p type="head">

<s>The raſh citation of the Teſtimony of SACRED <lb></lb>SCRIPTURE, in Concluſions meerly Natural, and <lb></lb>that may be proved by Senſible Experiments, and <lb></lb>Neceſſary Demonſtrations.</s></p><p type="head">

<s>Written, ſome years ſince, to Gratifie The moſt SERENE <lb></lb>CHRISTINA LOTHARINGA, <emph type="italics"></emph>Arch­<lb></lb>Dutcheſs<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> of <emph type="italics"></emph>TVSCANR<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>;</s></p><p type="head">

<s>By GALILÆO GALILÆI, A Gentleman of <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Florence,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and Chief Philoſopher and Mathematician to <lb></lb>His moſt Serene Highneſs the Grand <emph type="italics"></emph>DVKE.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="head">

<s><emph type="italics"></emph>And now rendred into Engliſh from the Italian,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>BY <lb></lb>THOMAS SALUSBURY.</s></p><p type="main">

<s><emph type="italics"></emph>Naturam Rerum invenire, difficile; &amp; ubi inveneris, indicare <lb></lb>in vulgus, nefas.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Plato.</s></p><p type="head">

<s><emph type="italics"></emph>LONDON,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>Printed by WILLIAM LEYBOURN, 1661.</s></p>       </section>  </front>          <body>            <chap><pb xlink:href="066/01/002.jpg" pagenum="427"></pb><p type="head">

<s>TO <lb></lb>Her moſt Serene <lb></lb>HIGHNES <lb></lb>THE <lb></lb>Gran Ducheſs Mother.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>Some years ſince, as Your moſt Serene Highneſs well <lb></lb>knoweth, I did diſcover many particulars in Hea­<lb></lb>ven that had been unſeen and unheard of untill <lb></lb>this our Age; which, as well for their Novelty, as <lb></lb>for certain conſequences which depend upon <lb></lb>them, claſhing with ſome Phyſical Propoſitions commonly recei­<lb></lb>ved by the Schools, did ſtir up againſt me no ſmall number of <lb></lb>ſuch as profeſſed the vulgar Philoſophy in the Univerſities; as if <lb></lb>I had with my own hand newly placed theſe things in Heaven to <lb></lb>obſcure and diſturb Nature and the Sciences: who forgetting <lb></lb>that the multitude of Truths contribute, and concur to the inve­<lb></lb>ſtigation, augmentation, and eſtabliſhment of the Arts, and not to <lb></lb>their diminution, and deſtruction; and at the ſame time ſhewing <lb></lb>themſelves more affectionate to their own Opinions, than to <lb></lb>Truth, went about to deny, and to diſprove thoſe Novelties; of <lb></lb>which their very ſenſe, had they but pleaſed to have intenſly be­<lb></lb>held them, would have rendered them thorowly aſſured. </s>

<s>And <lb></lb>to this purpoſe they alledged ſundry things, and publiſhed cer­<lb></lb>tain Papers fraughted with vain diſcourſes; and which was a <lb></lb>more groſs errour, interwoven with the atteſtations of the Sacred <lb></lb>Scriptures, taken from places by them not rightly underſtood, <lb></lb>and which did not any thing concern the point for which they <lb></lb>were produced Into which errour perhaps they would not <lb></lb>have run, if they had but been advertiſed of a moſt profitable <lb></lb>Document which S. <emph type="italics"></emph>Auguſtine<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> giveth us, concerning our pro­<lb></lb>ceeding warily, in making poſitive determinations in points that <pb xlink:href="066/01/003.jpg" pagenum="428"></pb>are obſcure and hard to be underſtood by the meer help of <lb></lb>ratiocination; where treating (as we) of a certain natural conclu­<lb></lb>ſion concerning Celeſtial Bodies, he thus writes: <emph type="italics"></emph>(a) But now<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg818"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>having evermore a reſpect to the moderation of pious Gravity, <lb></lb>we ought to believe nothing unadviſedly in a doubtful point; leſt <lb></lb>we conceive a prejudice againſt that, in favour to our Errour, <lb></lb>which Truth hereafter may diſcover to be no wiſe contrary to the <lb></lb>Sacred Books either of the Old, or New Teſtament.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg818"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(a) Nunc au­<lb></lb>tem, ſervatâ ſem­<lb></lb>per moderatione piæ <lb></lb>gravitatis, nihil <lb></lb>credere de re ob­<lb></lb>ſcurâ temerè de­<lb></lb>bemus, ne fortè, <lb></lb>quod poſtea veritas <lb></lb>patefecerit, quam­<lb></lb>vis Libris Sanct is, <lb></lb>ſive Teſtamenti <lb></lb>Veteris, ſive No­<lb></lb>vi, nisllo modo eſſe <lb></lb>poſſit adverſum, <lb></lb>tamen propter a­<lb></lb>morem noſtri erro­<lb></lb>ris, oderimus.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>It hath ſince come to paſs, that Time hath by degrees diſco­<lb></lb>vered to every one the truths before by me indicated: and to­<lb></lb>gether with the truth of the fact, a diſcovery hath been made of <lb></lb>the difference of humours between thoſe who ſimply and with­<lb></lb>out paſſion did refuſe to admit ſuch like <emph type="italics"></emph>Phænomena<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> for true, and <lb></lb>thoſe who to their incredulity had added ſome diſcompoſed af­<lb></lb>fection: For as thoſe who were better grounded in the Science of <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg819"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>Aſtronomy, and Natural Philoſophy, became ſatisfied upon my <lb></lb>firſt ntimation of the news; ſo all thoſe who ſtood not in the <lb></lb>Negative, or in doubt for any other reaſon, but becauſe it was <lb></lb>an unlookt-for-Novelty, and becauſe they had not an occaſion of <lb></lb>ſeeing a ſensible experiment thereof, did by degrees come to ſa­<lb></lb>risfie themſelves: But thoſe, who beſides the love they bore to <lb></lb>their firſt Errour, have I know not what imaginary intereſs to <lb></lb>render them diſaffected; not ſo much towards the things, as to­<lb></lb>wards the Author of them, not being able any longer to deny <lb></lb>them, conceal themſelves under an obſtinate ſilence; and being <lb></lb>exaſperated more than ever by that whereby thoſe others were <lb></lb>ſatisfied and convinced, they divert their thoughts to other pro­<lb></lb>jects, and ſeek to prejudice me ſome other wayes: of whom I <lb></lb>proreſs that I would make no more account than I have done of <lb></lb>thoſe who heretofore have contradicted me (at whom I alwaies <lb></lb>laugh, as being aſſured of the iſſue that the buſineſs is to have) <lb></lb>but that I ſee that thoſe new Calumnies and Perſecutions do not <lb></lb>determine in our greater or leſier Learning (in which I will ſcarce <lb></lb>pretend to any thing) but extend ſo far as to attempt to aſperſe <lb></lb>me with Crimes which ought to be, and are more abhorred by me <lb></lb>than Death it ſelf: Nor ought I to content my ſelf that they <lb></lb>are known to be unjuſt by thoſe onely who know me and them, <lb></lb>but by all men whatſoever. </s>

<s>They perſiſting therefore in their <lb></lb>firſt Reſolution, Of ruining me and whatſoever is mine, by all <lb></lb>imaginable waies; and knowing how that I in my Studies of <lb></lb>Aſtronomy and Philoſophy hold, as to the Worlds Syſteme, <lb></lb>That the Sun, without changing place, is ſituate in the Centre <lb></lb>of the Converſion of the Celeſtial Orbes; and that the Earth, <lb></lb>convertible about its own Axis, moveth it ſelf about the Sun: <lb></lb>And moreover underſtanding, that I proceed to maintain this Po­<pb xlink:href="066/01/004.jpg" pagenum="429"></pb>ſition, not onely by refuting the Reaſons of <emph type="italics"></emph>Ptolomy<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>Ariſto­<lb></lb>tle,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> but by producing many on the contrary; and in particular, <lb></lb>ſome Phyſical pertaining to Natural Effects, the cauſes of which <lb></lb>perhaps can be by no other way aſſigned; and others Aſtrono­<lb></lb>mical depending upon many circumſtances and encounters of <lb></lb>new Diſcoveries in Heaven, which manifeſtly confute the Ptolo­<lb></lb>maick Syſteme, and admirably agree with and confirm this other <lb></lb>Hypotheſis: and poſſibly being aſhamed to ſee the known truth <lb></lb>of other Poſitions by me aſſerted, different from thoſe that have <lb></lb>been commonly received; and therefore diſtruſting their de­<lb></lb>fence ſo long as they ſhould continue in the Field of Philoſo­<lb></lb>phy: for theſe reſpects, I ſay, they have reſolved to try whe­<lb></lb>ther they could make a Shield for the fallacies of their Argu­<lb></lb>ments of the Mantle of a feigned Religion, and of the Autho­<lb></lb>rity of the Sacred Scriptures, applyed by them with little judg­<lb></lb>ment to the confutation of ſuch Reaſons of mine as they had <lb></lb>neither underſtood, nor ſo much as heard.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg819"></margin.target>Lib_{+} 2. Geneſi <lb></lb>ad Literam in <lb></lb>fine.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>And firſt, they have indeavoured, as much as in them lay, to <lb></lb>divulge an opiniou thorow the Univerſe, that thoſe Propoſitions <lb></lb>are contrary to the Holy Letters, and conſequently Damnable <lb></lb>and Heretical: And thereupon perceiving, that for the moſt <lb></lb>part, the inclination of Mans Nature is more prone to imbrace <lb></lb>thoſe enterprizes, whereby his Neighbour may, although un­<lb></lb>juſtly, be oppreſſed, than thoſe from whence he may receive <lb></lb>juſt incouragement; it was no hard matter to find thoſe Com­<lb></lb>plices, who for ſuch (that is, for Damnable and Heretical) did <lb></lb>from their Pulpits with unwonted confidence preach it, with but <lb></lb>an unmerciful and leſs conſiderate injury, not only to this Do­<lb></lb>ctrine, and to its followers, but to all Mathematicks and Ma­<lb></lb>thematicians together. </s>

<s>Hereupon aſſuming greater confidence, <lb></lb>and vainly hoping that that Seed which firſt took root in their un­<lb></lb>ſound mindes, might ſpread its branches, and aſcend towards <lb></lb>Heaven, they went ſcattering rumours up and down among the <lb></lb>People, That it would, ere long be condemned by Supreme Au­<lb></lb>thority: and knowing that ſuch a <emph type="italics"></emph>Cenſure<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> would ſupplant <lb></lb>not onely theſe two Concluſions of the Worlds Syſteme, but <lb></lb>would make all other Aſtronomical and Phyſical Obſervations <lb></lb>that have correſpondence and neceſſary connection therewith to <lb></lb>become damnable, to facilitate the buſineſs they ſeek all they <lb></lb>can to make this opinion (at leaſt among the vulgar) to ſeem new, <lb></lb>and peculiar to my ſelf, not owning to know that <emph type="italics"></emph>Nicholas Coper­<lb></lb>nicus<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> was its Authour, or rather Reſtorer and Confirmer: a per­<lb></lb>ſon who was not only a Catholick, but a Prieſt, Canonick, and <lb></lb>ſo eſteemed, that there being a Diſpute in the <emph type="italics"></emph>Lateran Council,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>under <emph type="italics"></emph>Leo<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> X. touching the correction of the Eccleſiaſtick Ca­<pb xlink:href="066/01/005.jpg" pagenum="430"></pb>lendar, he was ſent for to <emph type="italics"></emph>Rome<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> from the remoteſt parts of <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Germany,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> for to aſſiſt in this Reformation, which for that time <lb></lb>was left imperfect, onely becauſe as then the true meaſure of <lb></lb>the Year and Lunar Moneth was not exactly known: whereupon <lb></lb>it was given him in charge by the Biſhop of <emph type="italics"></emph>Sempronia,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> at that <lb></lb>time Super-intendent in that Affair, to ſearch with reiterated <lb></lb>ſtudies and pains for greater light and certainty, touching thoſe <lb></lb>Cœleſtial Motions. </s>

<s>Upon which, with a Labour truly <emph type="italics"></emph>Atlantick<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>and with his admirable Wit, ſetting himſelf again to that Study, <lb></lb>he made ſuch a progreſs in theſe Sciences, and reduced the <lb></lb>knowledge of the Cœleſtial Motions to ſuch exactneſſe, that he <lb></lb>gained the title of an Excellent <emph type="italics"></emph>Aſtronomer.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> And, according <lb></lb>unto his Doctrine, not only the Calendar hath been ſince regu­<lb></lb>lated, but the Tables of all the Motions of the Planets have al­<lb></lb>ſo been calculated: and having reduced the ſaid Doctrine into <lb></lb>ſix Books, he publiſhed them to the World at the inſtance of <lb></lb>the Cardinal of <emph type="italics"></emph>Capua,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and of the Biſhop of <emph type="italics"></emph>Culma.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> And in <lb></lb>regard that he had re-aſſumed this ſo laborious an enterprize by <lb></lb>the order of The Pope; he dedicated his Book <emph type="italics"></emph>De Revolutioni­<lb></lb>bus Cœleſtibus<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> to His Succeſſour, namely <emph type="italics"></emph>Paul<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> III. which, being <lb></lb>then alſo Printed, hath been received by The Holy Church, and <lb></lb>read and ſtudied by all the World, without any the leaſt um­<lb></lb>brage of ſcruple that hath ever been conceived at his Doctrine; <lb></lb>The which, whilſt it is now proved by manifeſt Experiments and <lb></lb>neceſſary Demonſtrations to have been well grounded, there <lb></lb>want not perſons that, though they never ſaw that ſame Book in­<lb></lb>tercept the reward of thoſe many Labours to its Authour, by <lb></lb>cauſing him to be cenſured and pronounced an Heretick; and <lb></lb>this, only to ſatisfie a particular diſpleaſure conceived, without <lb></lb>any cauſe, againſt another man, that hath no other intereſt in <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Copernicus,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> but only as he is an approver of his Doctrine.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>Now in regard of theſe falſe aſperſions, which they ſo unjuſtly <lb></lb>ſeek to throw upon me, I have thought it neceſſary for my juſti­<lb></lb>fication before the World (of whoſe judgment in matters of <lb></lb>Religion and Reputation I ought to make great eſteem) to <lb></lb>diſcourſe concerning thoſe Particulars, which theſe men produce <lb></lb>to ſcandalize and ſubvert this Opinion, and in a word, to con­<lb></lb>demn it, not only as falſe, but alſo as Heretical; continually <lb></lb>making an Hipocritical Zeal for Religion their Shield; going a­<lb></lb>bout moreover to intereſt the Sacred Scriptures in the Diſpute, <lb></lb>and to make them in a certain ſenſe Miniſters of their deceiptful <lb></lb>purpoſes: and farthermore deſiring, if I miſtake not, contrary to <lb></lb>the intention of them, and of the Holy Fathers to extend (that I <lb></lb>may not ſay abuſe) their Authority, ſo as that even in Concluſions <lb></lb>meerly Natural, and not <emph type="italics"></emph>de Fide,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> they would have us altogether <pb xlink:href="066/01/006.jpg" pagenum="431"></pb>leave Senſe and Demonſtrative Reaſons, for ſome place of Scri­<lb></lb>pture which ſometimes under the apparent words may contain <lb></lb>a different ſenſe. </s>

<s>Now I hope to ſhew with how much <lb></lb>greater Piety and Religious Zeal I proceed, than they do, in that <lb></lb>I propoſe not, that the Book of <emph type="italics"></emph>Copernicus<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> is not to be condemn­<lb></lb>ed, but that it is not to be condemned, as they would have it; <lb></lb>without underſtanding it, hearing it, or ſo much as ſeeing it; <lb></lb>and eſpecially he being an Author that never treateth of matters <lb></lb>of Religion or Faith; nor by Reaſons any way depending on the <lb></lb>Authority of Sacred Scripoures whereupon he may have erroni­<lb></lb>ouſly interpreted them; but alwaies inſiſts upon Natural Conclu­<lb></lb>ſions belonging to the Celeſtial Motions, handled with Aſtrono­<lb></lb>mical and Geometrical Demonſtrations. </s>

<s>Not that he had not a <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg820"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>reſpect to the places of the Sacred Leaves, but becauſe he knew <lb></lb>very well that his ſaid Doctrine being demonſtrated, it could <lb></lb>not contradict the Scriptures, rightly, and according to their true <lb></lb>meaning underſtood. </s>

<s>And therefore in the end of his Epiſtle <lb></lb>Dedicatory, ſpeaking to The Pope, he ſaith thus: <emph type="italics"></emph>(b) If there <lb></lb>ſhould chance to be any Matæologiſts, who though ignorant in all <lb></lb>the Mathematicks, yet pretending a skill in thoſe Learnings, <lb></lb>ſhould dare, upon the authority of ſome place of Scripture wreſted <lb></lb>to their purpoſe, to condemn and cenſure this my Hypotheſis, I <lb></lb>value them not, but ſhall ſlight their inconſiderate Judgement. </s>

<s>For <lb></lb>it is not unknown, that<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Lactantius (<emph type="italics"></emph>otherwiſe a Famous Author, <lb></lb>though mean Mathematician) writeth very childiſhly touching the <lb></lb>Form of the Earth, when he ſcoffs at thoſe who affirm the Earth to <lb></lb>be in Form of a Globe. </s>

<s>So that it ought not to ſeem ſtrange to the <lb></lb>Ingenious, if any ſuch ſhould likewiſe now deride us. </s>

<s>The Ma­<lb></lb>thematicks are written for Mathematitians, to whom (if I deceive <lb></lb>not my ſelf) theſe Labours of mine ſhall ſeem to add ſomething, <lb></lb>as alſo to the Common-weale of the Church, whoſe Government is <lb></lb>now in the hands of Your Holineſs.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg820"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(c) Si fort aſſeerunt <lb></lb>Matæologi, qui <lb></lb>cum omnium Ma­<lb></lb>thematicum igna­<lb></lb>ri ſint, tamen de tis <lb></lb>judicium aſſu­<lb></lb>munt, propter ali­<lb></lb>quem locum Scri­<lb></lb>ptur æ, malè ad ſu­<lb></lb>um propoſitum, de­<lb></lb>tortum, auſi fue­<lb></lb>rint hoc meum in­<lb></lb>ſtitutum reprehen­<lb></lb>dere ac inſectari, <lb></lb>illos nihil moror, <lb></lb>adeò ut etiam illo­<lb></lb>rum judicium, tan­<lb></lb>guam temera ium <lb></lb>contemnam. </s>

<s>Non <lb></lb>enim obſcurum eſt, <lb></lb>Lact antium, cele­<lb></lb>lebrem alioqui <lb></lb>Scriptorem, ſed <lb></lb>Mathematicum <lb></lb>parvum, admodum <lb></lb>pueriliter de forma <lb></lb>Terræ loqui, cùm <lb></lb>deridet eos, qui <lb></lb>Terram, Globi for­<lb></lb>mam habere prodi­<lb></lb>derunt. </s>

<s>Itaque non <lb></lb>debet mirum vide­<lb></lb>ri ſtudioſis, ſi qui <lb></lb>tales, nos ettam ri­<lb></lb>debunt. </s>

<s>Mathema­<lb></lb>ta Mathematicis <lb></lb>ſcribuntur; quibus <lb></lb>&amp; hi noſtri labo­<lb></lb>res, (ſi me non fal­<lb></lb>lit opinio) vide­<lb></lb>buntur etiam Rei­<lb></lb>publicæ Eccleſia­<lb></lb>ſticæ conducere a­<lb></lb>liquid, cujus Prin­<lb></lb>cipatum Tua San­<lb></lb>ctitas nunc teness.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>And of this kinde do theſe appear to be who indeavour to <lb></lb>perſwade that <emph type="italics"></emph>Copernicus<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> may be condemned before his Book is <lb></lb>read; and to make the World believe that it is not onely lawfull <lb></lb>but commendable ſo to do, produce certain Authorities of the <lb></lb>Scripture, of Divines, and of Councils; which as they are by me <lb></lb>had in reverence, and held of Supream Authority, inſomuch that <lb></lb>I ſhould eſteem it high temerity for any one to contradict them <lb></lb>whilſt they are uſed according to the In ſtitutes of Holy Church, <lb></lb>ſo I believe that it is no errour to ſpeak, ſo long as one hath rea­<lb></lb>ſon to ſuſpect that a perſon hath a deſire, for ſome concern of <lb></lb>his own, to produce and alledge them, to purpoſes different from <lb></lb>thoſe that are in the moſt Sacred intention of The Holy Church. <lb></lb></s>

<s>Therefore I not onely proteſt (and my ſincerity ſhall manifeſt it <pb xlink:href="066/01/007.jpg" pagenum="432"></pb>ſelf) that I intend to ſubmit my ſelf freely to renounce thoſe et­<lb></lb>rors, into which, through ignorance, I may run in this Diſcourſe <lb></lb>of matters pertaining to Religion; but I farther declare, that I <lb></lb>deſire not in theſe matters to engage diſpute with any one, al­<lb></lb>though it ſhould be in points that are diſputable: for my end <lb></lb>endeth onely to this, That if in theſe conſiderations, beſides my <lb></lb>own profeſſion, amongſt the errours that may be in them, there <lb></lb>be any thing apt to give others an hint of ſome Notion beneficial <lb></lb>to the Holy Church, touching the determining about the <emph type="italics"></emph>Coper­<lb></lb>nican<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Syſteme, it may be taken and improved as ſhall ſeem beſt <lb></lb>to my Superiours: If not, let my Book be torn and burnt; for <lb></lb>that I do neither intend, nor pretend to gain to my ſelf any fruit <lb></lb>from my writings, that is not Pious and Catholick. </s>

<s>And more­<lb></lb>over, although that many of the things that I obſerve have been <lb></lb>ſpoken in my own hearing, yet I ſhall freely admit and grant to <lb></lb>thoſe that ſpake them, that they never ſaid them, if ſo they <lb></lb>pleaſe, but confeſs that I might have been miſtaken: And <lb></lb>therefore what I ſay, let it be ſuppoſed to be ſpoken not by them, <lb></lb>but by thoſe which were of this opinion.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>The motive therefore that they produce to condemn the Opi­<lb></lb>nion of the Mobility of the Earth, and Stability of the Sun, is, that <lb></lb>reading in the Sacred Leaves, in many places, that the Sun mo­<lb></lb>veth, that the Earth ſtandeth ſtill; and the Scripture not being <lb></lb>capable of lying, or erring, it followeth upon neceſſary conſe­<lb></lb>quence, that the Poſition of thoſe is Erronious and Heretical, who <lb></lb>maintain that the Sun of it ſelf is immoveable, and the Earth <lb></lb>moveable.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>Touching this Reaſon I think it fit in the firſt place, to con­<lb></lb>ſider, That it is both piouſly ſpoken, and prudently affirmed, That <lb></lb>the Sacred Scripture can never lye, when ever its true meaning is <lb></lb>underſtood: Which I believe none will deny to be many times <lb></lb>very abſtruce, and very different from that which the bare ſound <lb></lb>of the words ſignifieth. </s>

<s>Whence it cometh to paſs, that if ever <lb></lb>any one ſhould conſtantly confine himſelf to the naked Gram­<lb></lb>matical Sence, he might, erring himſelf, make not only Contra­<lb></lb>dictions and Propoſitions remote from Truth to appear in the <lb></lb>Scriptures, but alſo groſs Hereſies and Blaſphemies: For that we <lb></lb>ſhould be forced to aſſign to God feet, and hands, and eyes, yea <lb></lb>more corporal and humane affections, as of Anger, of Repen­<lb></lb>tance, of Hatred, nay, and ſometimes the Forgetting of things <lb></lb>paſt, and Ignorance of thoſe to come: Which Propoſitions, like <lb></lb>as (ſo the Holy Ghoſt affirmeth) they were in that manner pro­<lb></lb>nounced by the Sacred Scriptures, that they might be accommo­<lb></lb>dated to the Capacity of the Vulgar, who are very rude and un­<lb></lb>learned; ſo likewiſe, for the ſakes of thoſe that deſerve to be di­<pb xlink:href="066/01/008.jpg" pagenum="433"></pb>ſtinguiſhed from the Vulgar, it is neceſſary that grave and skilful <lb></lb>Expoſitors produce the true ſenſes of them, and ſhew the parti­<lb></lb>cular Reaſons why they are dictated under ſuch and ſuch words. <lb></lb></s>

<s>And this is a Doctrine ſo true and common amongſt Divines, <lb></lb>that it would be ſuperfluous to produce any atteſtation <lb></lb>thereof.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>Hence methinks I may with much more reaſon conclude, that <lb></lb>the ſame holy Writ, when ever it hath had occaſion to pronounce <lb></lb>any natural Concluſion, and eſpecially, any of thoſe which are <lb></lb>more abſtruce, and difficult to be underſtood, hath not failed to <lb></lb>obſerve this Rule, that ſo it might not cauſe confuſion in the <lb></lb>mindes of thoſe very people, and render them the more contu­<lb></lb>macious againſt the Doctrines that were more ſublimely myſteri­<lb></lb>ous: For (like as we have ſaid, and as it plainly appeareth) out <lb></lb>of the ſole reſpect of condeſcending to Popular Capacity, the <lb></lb>Scripture hath not ſcrupled to ſhadow over moſt principal and <lb></lb>fundamental Truths, attributing, even to God himſelf, qualities <lb></lb>extreamly remote from, and contrary unto his Eſſence. </s>

<s>Who <lb></lb>would poſitively affirm that the Scripture, laying aſide that re­<lb></lb>ſpect, in ſpeaking but occaſionally of the Earth, of the Water, of <lb></lb>the Sun, or of any other Creature, hath choſen to confine it <lb></lb>ſelf, with all rigour, within the bare and narrow literal ſenſe of <lb></lb>the words? </s>

<s>And eſpecially, in mentioning of thoſe Crea­<lb></lb>tures, things not at all concerning the primary Inſtitution of <lb></lb>the ſame Sacred Volume, to wit, the Service of God, and the <lb></lb>ſalvation of Souls, and in things infinitely beyond the appre­<lb></lb>henſion of the Vulgar?</s></p><p type="main">

<s>This therefore being granted, methinks that in the Diſcuſſion <lb></lb>of Natural Problemes, we ought not to begin at the authority <lb></lb>of places of Scripture; but at Senſible Experiments and Ne­<lb></lb>ceſſary Demonſtrations: For, from the Divine Word, the <lb></lb>Sacred Scripture and Nature did both alike proceed; the firſt, <lb></lb>as the Holy Ghoſts Inſpiration; the ſecond, as the moſt obſer­<lb></lb>vant Executrix of Gods Commands: And moreover it being <lb></lb>convenient in the Scriptures (by way of condeſcenſion to the <lb></lb>underſtanding of all men) to ſpeak many things different, in <lb></lb>appearance; and ſo far as concernes the naked ſigniſication of <lb></lb>the words, from abſolute truth: But on the contrary, Nature <lb></lb>being inexorable and immutable, and never paſſing the bounds <lb></lb>of the Laws aſſigned her, as one that nothing careth whether <lb></lb>her abſtruſe reaſons and methods of operating be, or be not ex­<lb></lb>poſed to the Capacity of Men; I conceive that that, concer­<lb></lb>ning Natural Effects, which either Senſible Experience ſets be­<lb></lb>fore our eyes, or Neceſſary Demonſtrations do prove unto us, <lb></lb>ought not, upon any account, to be called into queſtion, much <pb xlink:href="066/01/009.jpg" pagenum="434"></pb>leſs condemned upon the teſtimony of Texts of Scripture, which <lb></lb>may, under their words, couch Senſes ſeemingly contrary there­<lb></lb>to; In regard that every Expreſſion of Scripture is not tied to <lb></lb>ſo ſtrict conditions, as every Effect of Nature: Nor doth God <lb></lb>leſs admirably diſcover himſelf unto us in Nature&#039;s Actions, than <lb></lb>in the Scriptures Sacred Dictions. </s>

<s>Which peradventure <emph type="italics"></emph>Tertul-<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg821"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>lian<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> intended to expreſs in thoſe words<emph type="italics"></emph>: (c) We conclude, God <lb></lb>is known; firſt, by Nature, and then again more particularly <lb></lb>known by Doctrine: by Nature, in his Works; by Doctrine, in his <lb></lb>Word preached.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg821"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>Nos definimus, <lb></lb>Deum, primò N.­<lb></lb>tura cognoſcen­<lb></lb>dum; Deinde, Do­<lb></lb>ctrina recognoſcen­<lb></lb>dum: Natura ex <lb></lb>operibus; Doctri­<lb></lb>na ex pr ædicatio­<lb></lb>nibus.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>But I will not hence affirm, but that we ought to have an ex­<lb></lb>traordinary eſteem for the Places of Sacred Scripture, nay, being <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg822"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>come to a certainty in any Natural Concluſions, we ought <lb></lb>to make uſe of them, as moſt appoſite helps to the true Expo­<lb></lb>ſition of the ſame Scriptures, and to the inveſtigation of thoſe <lb></lb>Senſes which are neceſſarily conteined in them, as moſt true, and <lb></lb>concordant with the Truths demonſtrated.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg822"></margin.target>Tertul. </s>

<s>adver. <lb></lb></s>

<s>Marcion. </s>

<s>lib. 

1. <lb></lb>cap. 

18.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>This maketh me to ſuppoſe, that the Authority of the Sacred <lb></lb>Volumes was intended principally to perſwade men to the be­<lb></lb>lief of thoſe Articles and Propoſitions, which, by reaſon they <lb></lb>ſurpaſs all humane diſcourſe, could not by any other Science, or <lb></lb>by any other means be made credible, than by the Mouth of <lb></lb>the Holy Spirit it ſelf. </s>

<s>Beſides that, even in thoſe Propoſitions, <lb></lb>which are not <emph type="italics"></emph>de Fide,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> the Authority of the ſame Sacred Leaves <lb></lb>ought to be preferred to the Authority of all Humane Sciences <lb></lb>that are not written in a Demonſtrative Method, but either with <lb></lb>bare Narrations, or elſe with probable Reaſons; and this I hold <lb></lb>to be ſo far convenient and neceſſary, by how far the ſaid Di­<lb></lb>vine Wiſdome ſurpaſſeth all humane Judgment and Conjecture. <lb></lb></s>

<s>But that that ſelf ſame God who hath indued us with Senſes, <lb></lb>Diſcourſe, and Underſtanding hath intended, laying aſide the <lb></lb>uſe of theſe, to give the knowledg of thoſe things by other means, <lb></lb>which we may attain by theſe, ſo as that even in thoſe Natural <lb></lb>Concluſions, which either by Senſible Experiments or Neceſſary <lb></lb>Demonſtrations are ſet before our eyes, or our Underſtanding, we <lb></lb>ought to deny Senſe and Reaſon, I do not conceive that I am <lb></lb>bound to believe it; and eſpecially in thoſe Sciences, of which <lb></lb>but a ſmall part, and that divided into Concluſions is to be <lb></lb>found in the Scripture: Such as, for inſtance, is that of <emph type="italics"></emph>Aſtro­<lb></lb>nomy,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> of which there is ſo ſmall a part in Holy Writ, that it doth <lb></lb>not ſo much as name any of the Planets, except the Sun and the <lb></lb>Moon, and once or twice onely <emph type="italics"></emph>Venus<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> under the name of <emph type="italics"></emph>Luci­<lb></lb>fer.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> For if the Holy Writers had had any intention to perſwade <lb></lb>People to believe the Diſpoſitions and Motions of the Cœleſtial <lb></lb>Bodies; and that conſequently we are ſtill to derive that know­<pb xlink:href="066/01/010.jpg" pagenum="435"></pb>ledge from the Sacred Books they would not, in my opinion, have <lb></lb>ſpoken ſo little thereof, that it is as much as nothing, in compa­<lb></lb>riſon of the infinite admirable Concluſions, which in that Sci­<lb></lb>ence are comprized and demonſtrated Nay, that the Authours <lb></lb>of the Holy Volumes did not only not pretend to teach us the <lb></lb>Conſtitutions and Motions of the Heavens and Stars, their Fi­<lb></lb>gures, Magnitudes, and Diſtances, but that intentionally (al­<lb></lb>beit that all theſe things were very well known unto them) they <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg823"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>forbore to ſpeak of them, is the opinion of the Moſt Holy &amp; Moſt <lb></lb>Learned Fathers: and in S. <emph type="italics"></emph>Auguſtine<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> we read the following words. <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>(c) It is likewiſe commonly asked, of what Form and Figure <lb></lb>we may believe Heaven to be, according to the Scriptures: For <lb></lb>many contend much about thoſe matters, which the greater pru­<lb></lb>dence of our Authors hath forborn to ſpeak of, as nothing further­<lb></lb>ing their Learners in relation to ableſſed life; and, (which is <lb></lb>the chiefeſt thing) taking up much of that time which ſhould be <lb></lb>ſpent in holy exerciſes. </s>

<s>For what is it to me whether Heaven, as <lb></lb>a Sphere, doth on all ſides environ the Earth, a Maſs ballanced in <lb></lb>the middle of the World; or whether like a Diſh it doth onely cover <lb></lb>or overcaſt the ſame? </s>

<s>But becauſe belief of Scripture is urged for <lb></lb>that cauſe, which we have oft mentioned, that is, That none through <lb></lb>ignorance of Divine Phraſes, when they ſhall find any thing of this <lb></lb>nature in, or hear any thing cited out of our Bibles which may ſeem <lb></lb>to oppoſe manifeſt Concluſions, ſhould be induced to ſuſpect their <lb></lb>truth, when they admoniſh, relate, &amp; deliver more profitable matters <lb></lb>Briefly be it ſpoken, touching the Figure of Heaven, that our Au­<lb></lb>thors knew the truth: But the H. </s>

<s>Spirit would not, that men ſhould <lb></lb>learn what is profitable to none for ſalvation.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg823"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(c) Quæri etiam<lb></lb>ſolet, quæ forma &amp; <lb></lb>figura Cæli cre­<lb></lb>denda ſit ſecun­<lb></lb>dum Scripturas <lb></lb>noſtras: Multi e­<lb></lb>nim multum diſ­<lb></lb>put ant de iis rebus, <lb></lb>quas majori pru­<lb></lb>dentia noſtri Auto­<lb></lb>res omiſerunt, ad <lb></lb>beatam vitam non <lb></lb>profutur as diſcen­<lb></lb>libus, &amp; occupan­<lb></lb>tes (quod prius eſt) <lb></lb>multum prolixa, <lb></lb>&amp; rebus ſalubri­<lb></lb>bus impendenda <lb></lb>temporum ſpatia. <lb></lb></s>

<s>Quid enim ad me <lb></lb>pertinet, utrum <lb></lb>Cælum, ſicut Sphæ­<lb></lb>ra, undique conclu­<lb></lb>dat Terram, in <lb></lb>media. </s>

<s>Mundi mo­<lb></lb>le libratam; an <lb></lb>eam ex una par­<lb></lb>te deſuper, ve­<lb></lb>lut diſcus, ope­<lb></lb>riat? </s>

<s>Sed quia de Fide agitur S cripiurærum, propter illam cauſam, quam non ſemel commemoravimus, Ne ſcilicet <lb></lb>quiſquam eloquia divina non intelligens, cum de his rebus tale aliquid vel invenerit in Libris Noſtris, vel ex illis <lb></lb>audiverit, quod perceptis aſſertionibus adver ſari videatur, nullo modo eis, cetera utilia monentibus, vel narrantibus, <lb></lb>vel pranuntiantibus, credat: Breviter diſcendum eſt, de figura Cæli, hoc ſciſſe Autores noſtros, quod verit as ha­<lb></lb>bet: Sed Spiritum Dei, qui per ipſos loquebstur, noluiſſe iſta docere homines, nulli ad ſalutem profutura.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> D. <lb></lb>Auguſt. </s>

<s>Lib. 2. De Gen. </s>

<s>ad literam, Cap. </s>

<s>9. Idem etiam legitur apud <emph type="italics"></emph>Petrum Lombardum<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Magiſtrum Sententiarum.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>And the ſame intentional ſilence of theſe ſacred Penmen in <lb></lb>determining what is to be believed of theſe accidents of the Ce­<lb></lb>leſtial Bodies, is again hinted to us by the ſame Father in the en­<lb></lb>ſuing 10. Chapter upon the Queſtion, Whether we are to believe <lb></lb>that Heaven moveth, or ſtandeth ſtill, in theſe words: <emph type="italics"></emph>(d) There<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg824"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>are ſome of the Brethren that ſtart a queſtion concerning the motion <lb></lb>of Heaven, Whether it be fixed, or moved: For if it be moved <lb></lb>(ſay they) how is it a Firmament? </s>

<s>If it ſtand ſtill, how do theſe <lb></lb>Stars which are held to be fixed go round from Eaſt to Weſt, the <lb></lb>more Norchern performing ſhorter Circuits near the Pole; ſo that <lb></lb>Heaven, if there be another Pole, to us unknown, may ſeem to re­<lb></lb>volve upon ſome other Axis; but if there be not another Pole, it <lb></lb>may be thought to move as a Diſcus? </s>

<s>To whom I reply, That<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><pb xlink:href="066/01/011.jpg" pagenum="436"></pb><emph type="italics"></emph>theſe points require many ſubtil and profound Reaſons, for the <lb></lb>making out whether they be really ſo, or no; the undertakeing and <lb></lb>diſeuſſing of which is neither conſiſtent with my leaſure, nor their <lb></lb>duty, vvhom I deſire to inſtruct in the neceſſary matters more di­<lb></lb>rectly conducing to their ſalvation, and to the benefit of The Holy <lb></lb>Church.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg824"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(d) De Motu <lb></lb>etiam Cæli, non­<lb></lb>nulli fratres quæ­<lb></lb>ſtionem movent, u­<lb></lb>trum ſtet, an mo­<lb></lb>veatur; quia ſi mo­<lb></lb>vetur, inquiunt, <lb></lb>quomodo Firma­<lb></lb>mentum eſt? </s>

<s>Si <lb></lb>autem ſtat, quomo­<lb></lb>do Sydera quæ in<lb></lb>ipſo fixa credun­<lb></lb>tur, ab Oriente in <lb></lb>Occidentem circum<lb></lb>eunt, Septentrio­<lb></lb>nalibus breviores <lb></lb>gyros juxta cardi­<lb></lb>nem perag entibus; <lb></lb>ut Cælum, ſi est a­<lb></lb>lius nobis occultus <lb></lb>cardo, ex alio ver­<lb></lb>tice, ſicut Sphæra; <lb></lb>ſi autem nullus a­<lb></lb>lius cardo eſt, vel <lb></lb>uti diſcus rotari <lb></lb>videatur? </s>

<s>Quibus <lb></lb>reſpondeo, Multum <lb></lb>ſubtilibus &amp; labo­<lb></lb>rioſis rationibus <lb></lb>iſta perquiri, ut ve­<lb></lb>re percipiatur, u­<lb></lb>trum ita, an non <lb></lb>ita ſit, quibus ine­<lb></lb>undis atque tra­<lb></lb>ctandis, nec mihi <lb></lb>jam tempus eſt, nec <lb></lb>illis eſſe debet, quos <lb></lb>ad ſalutem ſuam, <lb></lb>è Sanctæ Eccleſiæ <lb></lb>neceſſaria utilitate <lb></lb>cupimus informa­<lb></lb>ri:<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>From which (that we may come nearer to our particular caſe) <lb></lb>it neceſſarily followeth, that the Holy Ghoſt not having intend­<lb></lb>ed to teach us, whether Heaven moveth or ſtandeth ſtill; nor <lb></lb>whether its Figure be in Form of a Sphere, or of a Diſcus, or di­<lb></lb>ſtended <emph type="italics"></emph>in Planum<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>: Nor whether the Earth be contained in the <lb></lb>Centre of it, or on one ſide; he hath much leſs had an intention <lb></lb>to aſſure us of other Concluſions of the ſame kinde, and in ſuch <lb></lb>a manner, connected to theſe already named, that without the <lb></lb>dedermination of them, one can neither affirm one or the other <lb></lb>part; which are, The determining of the Motion and Reſt of the <lb></lb>ſaid Earth, and of the Sun. </s>

<s>And if the ſame Holy Spirit hath <lb></lb>purpoſely pretermitted to teach us thoſe Propoſitions, as nothing <lb></lb>concerning his intention, that is, our ſalvation; how can it be af­<lb></lb>firmed, that the holding of one part rather than the other, ſhould <lb></lb>be ſo neceſſary, as that it is <emph type="italics"></emph>de Fide,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and the other erronious? <lb></lb></s>

<s>Can an Opinion be Heretical, and yet nothing concerning the <lb></lb>ſalvation of ſouls? </s>

<s>Or can it be ſaid that the Holy Ghoſt purpo­<lb></lb>ſed not to teach us a thing that concerned our ſalvation? </s>

<s>I might <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg825"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>here inſert the Opinion of an Eccleſiaſtical ^{*} Perſon, raiſed to the <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg826"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>degree of <emph type="italics"></emph>Eminentiſſimo,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> to wit, <emph type="italics"></emph>That the intention of the Holy <lb></lb>Ghoſt, is to teach us how we ſhall go to Heaven, and not how Hea­<lb></lb>ven goeth.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg825"></margin.target>* Card. </s>

<s>Baronius.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg826"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>Spiritu ſancti <lb></lb>mentem fuiſſe, nos <lb></lb>docere, quomodo ad <lb></lb>Cælum eatur: non <lb></lb>autem, quomodo <lb></lb>Cælum gradiatur.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>Cardinal. </s>

<s>Bar.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>But let us return to conſider how much neceſſary Demonſtra­<lb></lb>tions, and ſenſible Experiments ought to be eſteemed in Natural <lb></lb>Concluſions; and of what Authority Holy and Learned Divines <lb></lb>have accounted them, from whom amongſt an hundred other atte­<lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg827"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>ſtations, we have theſe that follow: <emph type="italics"></emph>(e) We must alſo carefully <lb></lb>heed and altogether avoid in handling the Doctrine of<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Moſes, <emph type="italics"></emph>to <lb></lb>avouch or ſpeak any thing affirmatively and confidently which <lb></lb>contradicteth the manifeſt Experiments and Reaſons of Philoſo­<lb></lb>phy, or other Sciences. </s>

<s>For ſince all Truth is agreeable to Truth, <lb></lb>the Truth of Holy Writ cannot be contrary to the ſolid Reaſons <lb></lb>and Experiments of Humane Learning.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg828"></arrow.to.target></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg827"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(e) Illud etiam <lb></lb>diligenter caven­<lb></lb>dum, &amp; emnino <lb></lb>fugiendum eſt, ne <lb></lb>in tractanda<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Mo­<lb></lb>ſis <emph type="italics"></emph>Dectrina, quic­<lb></lb>quam affirmate &amp; <lb></lb>aſſeveranter ſen­<lb></lb>tiamus &amp; dica­<lb></lb>mus, quod repug­<lb></lb>net manifeſtis ex­<lb></lb>perimentis &amp; rationibus Philoſophiæ, vel aliarum Diſciplinarum. </s>

<s>Namque cum Verum omne ſemper cum Vero <lb></lb>congruat, non poteſt Verit as Sacrarum Litterarum, Veris Rationibus &amp; Experimentis Humanarum Doctrina­<lb></lb>rum eſſe contraria.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Perk. in Gen. circa Principium.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg828"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(f) Si manife­<lb></lb>ſtæ certæque Rati­<lb></lb>oni, velut ſancta­<lb></lb>rum Litterarum <lb></lb>objicitur autori­<lb></lb>ritas, non intelli­<lb></lb>git, qui hoc facit; <lb></lb>&amp; non Scripturæ <lb></lb>ſenſum (ad quem <lb></lb>penetrare non po­<lb></lb>tuit) ſed ſuum po­<lb></lb>tius objicit verita­<lb></lb>ti: nec id quod in <lb></lb>sa, ſed quod in ſe­<lb></lb>ipſo velue pro ea<lb></lb>invenit, opponit.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>And in St. <emph type="italics"></emph>Auguſtine<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> we read: <emph type="italics"></emph>(f) If any one ſhall object <lb></lb>the Authority of Sacred Writ, againſt clear and manifeſt Reaſon, <lb></lb>he that doth ſo, knows not what he undertakes: For he objects<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><pb xlink:href="066/01/012.jpg" pagenum="437"></pb><emph type="italics"></emph>againſt the Truth, not the ſenſe of the Scripture (which is be­<lb></lb>yond his comprehenſion) but rather his own; not what is in it, but <lb></lb>what, finding it in himſelf, he fancyed to be in it.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>This granted, and it being true, (as hath been ſaid) that two <lb></lb>Truths cannot be contrary to each other, it is the office of a <lb></lb>Judicious Expoſitor to ſtudy to finde the true Senſes of Sacred <lb></lb>Texts, which undoubtedly ſhall accord with thoſe Natural Con­<lb></lb>cluſions, of which manifeſt Senſe and Neceſſary Demonſtrations </s></p><p type="main">

<s><arrow.to.target n="marg829"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>had before made us ſure and certain. </s>

<s>Yea, in regard that the <lb></lb>Scriptures (as hath been ſaid) for the Reaſons alledged, admit in <lb></lb>many places Expoſitions far from the Senſe of the words; and <lb></lb>moreover, we not being able to affirm, that all Interpreters <lb></lb>ſpeak by Divine Inſpiration; For (if it were ſo) then there <lb></lb>would be no difference between them about the Senſes of the <lb></lb>ſame places; I ſhould think that it would be an act of great pru­<lb></lb>dence to make it unlawful for any one to uſurp Texts of Scri­<lb></lb>pture, and as it were to force them to maintain this or that Natu­<lb></lb>rall Concluſion for truth, of which Sence, &amp; Demonſtrative, and <lb></lb>neceſſary Reaſons may one time or other aſſure us the contrary. <lb></lb></s>

<s>For who will preſcribe bounds to the Wits of men? </s>

<s>Who will <lb></lb>aſſert that all that is ſenſible and knowable in the World is al­<lb></lb>ready diſcovered and known? </s>

<s>Will not they that in other points <lb></lb>diſagree with us, confeſs this (and it is a great truth) that <emph type="italics"></emph>Ea <lb></lb>quæ ſcimus, ſint minima pars eorum quæ ignoramus<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>? </s>

<s>That thoſe <lb></lb>Truths which we know, are very few, in compariſon of thoſe <lb></lb>which we know not? </s>

<s>Nay more, if we have it from the Mouth <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg830"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>of the Holy Ghoſt, that <emph type="italics"></emph>Deus tradidit Mundum diſputationi <lb></lb>eorum, ut non inveniat homo opus, quod operatus eſt Deus ab <lb></lb>initio ad finem:<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> One ought not, as I conceive, to ſtop the way <lb></lb>to free Philoſophating, touching the things of the World, and of <lb></lb>Nature, as if that they were already certainly found, and all ma­<lb></lb>nifeſt: nor ought it to be counted raſhneſs, if one do not fit <lb></lb>down ſatisfied with the opinions now become as it were com­<lb></lb>mune; nor ought any perſons to be diſpleaſed, if others do not <lb></lb>hold, in natural Diſputes to that opinion which beſt pleaſeth <lb></lb>them; and eſpecially touching Problems that have, for thouſands <lb></lb>of years, been controverted amongſt the greateſt Philoſophers, as is <lb></lb>the Stability of the Sun, and Mobility of the Earth, an opinion <lb></lb>held by <emph type="italics"></emph>Pythagoras,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and by his whole Sect; by <emph type="italics"></emph>Heraclides Pon­<lb></lb>ticus,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> who was of the ſame opininion; by <emph type="italics"></emph>Phylolaus,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> the Maſter <lb></lb>of <emph type="italics"></emph>Plato<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; and by <emph type="italics"></emph>Plato<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> himſelf, as <emph type="italics"></emph>Ariſtotle<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> relateth, and of <lb></lb>which <emph type="italics"></emph>Plutarch<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> writeth in the life of <emph type="italics"></emph>Numa,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> that the ſaid <emph type="italics"></emph>Plato,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>when he was grown old, ſaid, It is a moſt abſurd thing to think <lb></lb>otherwiſe: The ſame was believed by <emph type="italics"></emph>Ariſtarchus Samius,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> as <lb></lb>we have it in <emph type="italics"></emph>Archimedes<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; and probably by <emph type="italics"></emph>Archimedes<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> him­<pb xlink:href="066/01/013.jpg" pagenum="438"></pb>ſelf; by <emph type="italics"></emph>Nicetas<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> the Philoſopher, upon the teſtimony of <emph type="italics"></emph>Scicero,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>and by many others. </s>

<s>And this opinion hath, finally, been am­<lb></lb>plified, and with many Obſervations and Demonſtrations con­<lb></lb>firmed by <emph type="italics"></emph>Nicholaus Copernicus.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> And <emph type="italics"></emph>Seneca,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> a moſt eminent <lb></lb>Philoſopher, in his Book <emph type="italics"></emph>De Cometis,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> advertizeth us that we <lb></lb>ought, with great diligence, ſeek for an aſſured knowledge, <lb></lb>whether it be Heaven, or the Earth, in which the Diurnal Con­<lb></lb>verſion reſides.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg829"></margin.target>Epiſt. </s>

<s>7. ad Mar­<lb></lb>cellinum.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg830"></margin.target>Eccleſiaſt. </s>

<s>cap. 

3.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>And for this cauſe, it would probably be prudent and proſi­<lb></lb>table counſel, if beſides the Articles which concern our Salvati­<lb></lb>on, and the eſtabliſhment of our Faith (againſt the ſtability of <lb></lb>which there is no fear that any valid and ſolid Doctrine can e­<lb></lb>ver riſe up) men would not aggregate and heap up more, with­<lb></lb>out neceſſity: And if it be ſo, it would certainly be a prepoſte­<lb></lb>rous thing to introduce ſuch Articles at the requeſt of perſons <lb></lb>who, beſides that we know not that they ſpeak by inſpiration <lb></lb>of Divine Grace, we plainly ſee that there might be wiſhed in <lb></lb>them the underſtanding which would be neceſſary firſt to enable <lb></lb>them to comprehend, and then to diſcuſs the Demonſtrations <lb></lb>wherewith the ſubtiler Sciences proceed in confirming ſuch like <lb></lb>Concluſions. </s>

<s>Nay, more I ſhould ſay, (were it lawful to ſpeak <lb></lb>my judgment freely on this Argument) that it would haply <lb></lb>more ſuit with the <emph type="italics"></emph>Decorum<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and Majeſty of thoſe Sacred Vo­<lb></lb>lumes, if care were taken that every ſhallow and vulgar Writer <lb></lb>might not authorize his Books (which are not ſeldome grounded <lb></lb>upon fooliſh fancies) by inſerting into them Places of Holy Scri­<lb></lb>pture, interpreted, or rather diſtorted to Senſes as remote from <lb></lb>the right meaning of the ſaid Scripture, as they are neer to deri­<lb></lb>riſion, who not without oſtentation flouriſh out their Writings <lb></lb>therewith. </s>

<s>Examples of ſuch like abuſes there might many be <lb></lb>produced, but for this time I will confine my ſelf to two, not <lb></lb>much beſides theſe matters of <emph type="italics"></emph>Aſtronomy:<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> One of which, is that <lb></lb>of thoſe Pamphlets which were publiſhed againſt the <emph type="italics"></emph>Medicean<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>Planets, of which I had the fortune to make the diſcovery; a­<lb></lb>gainſt the exiſtence of which there were brought many places of <lb></lb>Sacred Sctipture: Now, that all the World ſeeth them to be <lb></lb>Planets, I would gladly hear with what new interpretations <lb></lb>thoſe very Antagoniſts do expound the Scripture, and excuſe their <lb></lb>own ſimplicity. </s>

<s>The other example is of him who but very <lb></lb>lately hath Printed againſt <emph type="italics"></emph>Aſtronomers<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>Philoſophers,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> that <lb></lb>the Moon doth not receive its light from the Sun, but is of its own <lb></lb>nature reſplendent: which imagination he in the cloſe confirm­<lb></lb>eth, or, to ſay better, perſwadeth himſelf that he confirmeth by <lb></lb>ſundry Texts of Scripture, which he thinks cannot be reconciled <lb></lb>unleſſe his opinion ſhould be true and neceſſary. </s>

<s>Nevertheleſſe, <pb xlink:href="066/01/014.jpg" pagenum="439"></pb>the Moon of it ſelf is Tenebroſe, and yet it is no leſſe lucid than <lb></lb>the Splendor of the Sun.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>Hence it is manifeſt, that theſe kinde of Authors, in regard they <lb></lb>did not dive into the true Sence of the Scriptures, would (in caſe <lb></lb>their authority were of any great moment) have impoſed a neceſ­<lb></lb>ſity upon others to believe ſuch Concluſions for true as were re­<lb></lb>pugnant to manifeſt Reaſon, and to Senſe. </s>

<s>Which abuſe <emph type="italics"></emph>Deus <lb></lb>avertat,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> that it do not gain Countenance and Authority; for if it <lb></lb>ſhould, it would in a ſhort time be neceſſary to proſcribe and in­<lb></lb>hibit all the Contemplative Sciences. </s>

<s>For being that by nature <lb></lb>the number of ſuch as are very unapt to underſtand perfectly <lb></lb>both the Sacred Scriptures, and the other Sciences is much great­<lb></lb>er than that of the skilfull and intelligene; thoſe of the firſt ſort <lb></lb>ſuperficially running over the Scriptures, would arrogate to them­<lb></lb>ſelves an Authority of decreeing upon all the Queſtions in Na­<lb></lb>ture, by vertue of ſome Word by them miſonderſtood, and pro­<lb></lb>duced by the Sacred Pen-men to another purpoſe: Nor would <lb></lb>the ſmall number of the Intelligent be able to repreſs the furious <lb></lb>Torrent of thoſe men, who would finde ſo many the more fol­<lb></lb>lowers, in that the gaining the reputation of Wiſe men without <lb></lb>pains or Study, is far more grateful to humane Nature, than the <lb></lb>conſuming our ſelves with reſtleſs contemplations about the moſt <lb></lb>painfull Arts. </s>

<s>Therefore we ought to return infinite thanks to <lb></lb>Almighty God, who of his Goodneſs freeth us from this fear, in <lb></lb>that he depriveth ſuch kinde of perſons of all Authority and, re­<lb></lb>poſeth the Conſulting, Reſolving, and Decreeing upon ſo im­<lb></lb>portant Determinations in the extraordinary Wiſdom and Can­<lb></lb>dor of moſt Sacred Fathers; and in the Supream Authority of <lb></lb>thoſe, who being guided by his Holy Spirit, cannot but determin <lb></lb>Holily: So ordering things, that of the levity of thoſe other men, <lb></lb>there is no account made. </s>

<s>This kinde of men are thoſe, as I be­<lb></lb>lieve, againſt whom, not without Reaſon, Grave, and Holy Wri­<lb></lb>ters do ſo much inveigh; and of whom in particular S. <emph type="italics"></emph>Hierom<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg831"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>writeth: <emph type="italics"></emph>(g) This<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> (Scilicet <emph type="italics"></emph>the Sacred Scripture) the talking <lb></lb>old woman, the doting old man, the talkative Sophiſter, all venture <lb></lb>upon, lacerate, teach, and that before they have learnt it. </s>

<s>Others <lb></lb>induced by Pride, diving into hard words, Philoſophate amongſt <lb></lb>Women, touching the Holy Scriptures. </s>

<s>Others (Oh ſhame­<lb></lb>ful!) Learn of Women what they teach to Men; and, as if this <lb></lb>were nothiug, in a certain facility of words, I may ſay of confi­<lb></lb>dence, expound to others what they underſtand not themſelves. </s>

<s>I <lb></lb>forbear to ſpeak of thoſe of my own Profeſſion, who, if after Hu­<lb></lb>mane Learning they chance to attain to the Holy Scriptures, and <lb></lb>tickle the ears of the people with affected and Studied expreſſions, <lb></lb>they affirm that all they ſay, is to be entertained as the Law of God<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; <pb xlink:href="066/01/015.jpg" pagenum="440"></pb><emph type="italics"></emph>and not ſtooping to learn what the Prophets and Apoſtles held, <lb></lb>they force incongruous teſtimonies to their own Senſe: As if it <lb></lb>were the genuine, and not corrupt way of teaching to deprave Sen­<lb></lb>tences, and Wreſt the Scripture according to their own ſingular and <lb></lb>contradictory humour.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg831"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(g) Hanc (Sci­<lb></lb>licer Sacram Scri­<lb></lb>pturam) garrula <lb></lb>arus, hanc deli­<lb></lb>rus ſenex hanc So­<lb></lb>phiſta verboſus, <lb></lb>h<gap></gap> univerſi præ­<lb></lb>ſumunt, lacerant, <lb></lb>docent, anteguans <lb></lb>diſcant. </s>

<s>Alij, <lb></lb>addacto ſupercilio, <lb></lb>grandia verba <lb></lb>trutinantes, inter <lb></lb>mulierculas, de <lb></lb>Sacris Litteris <lb></lb>Philoſophantur. <lb></lb></s>

<s>Alij diſcunt, prob <lb></lb>pudor! à fæminis, <lb></lb>quod viros docent, <lb></lb>&amp; ne parum hoc <lb></lb>ſit, quadam faci­<lb></lb>litate verborum, <lb></lb>imo audaciâ, ediſ­<lb></lb>ſerunt aliis, quod <lb></lb>ipſi non intelli­<lb></lb>gunt. </s>

<s>Taceo de <lb></lb>mei ſimilibus, qui <lb></lb>ſi fortè ad Scriptu­<lb></lb>ras Sanctas, poſt <lb></lb>ſeculares litteras <lb></lb>venerint, &amp; ſer­<lb></lb>mone compoſito, <lb></lb>aurem populi mul­<lb></lb>ſerint; quicquid <lb></lb>dixerint, hoc le­<lb></lb>gem Dei putant: <lb></lb>nec ſcire dignan­<lb></lb>tur, quid Prophe­<lb></lb>tæ, quid Apoſtoli <lb></lb>ſenſerint, ſed ad <lb></lb>ſenſum ſuum, in­<lb></lb>congrua aptant te­<lb></lb>ſtimonia: Quaſi <lb></lb>grande ſit, &amp; non <lb></lb>vitiociſſimum do­<lb></lb>cendi genus, de­<lb></lb>pravare ſententi­<lb></lb>as, &amp; ad volun­<lb></lb>tatem ſuam Scri­<lb></lb>pturamtrahere re­<lb></lb>pugnantem.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Je­<lb></lb>ron. </s>

<s>Epiſt. </s>

<s>ad <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Paul.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 103.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>I will not rank among theſe ſame ſecular Writers any <emph type="italics"></emph>Theo­<lb></lb>logiſts,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> whom I repute to be men of profound Learning, and ſo­<lb></lb>ber Manners, and therefore hold them in great eſteem and vene­<lb></lb>ration: Yet I cannot deny but that I have a certain ſcruple in <lb></lb>my mind, and conſequently am deſirous to have it removed, <lb></lb>whilſt I hear that they pretend to a power of conſtraining others <lb></lb>by Authority of the Scriptures to follow that opinion in Natu­<lb></lb>ral Diſputations, which they think moſt agreeth with the Texts <lb></lb>of that: Holding withall, that they are not bound to anſwer <lb></lb>the Reaſons and Experiments on the contrary: In Explication <lb></lb>and Confirmation of which their judgement they ſay, That <emph type="italics"></emph>The­<lb></lb>ologie<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> being the Queen of all the Sciences, ſhe ought not upon <lb></lb>any account to ſtoop to accomodate her ſelf to the Poſitions of <lb></lb>the reſt, leſs worthy, and inferior to her: But that they ought <lb></lb>to refer themſelves to her (as to their Supream Empereſs) and <lb></lb>change and alter their Concluſions, according to <emph type="italics"></emph>Theological<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>Statutes and Decrees. </s>

<s>And they further add, That if in the <lb></lb>inferior Science there ſhould be any Concluſion certain by ver­<lb></lb>tue of Demonſtrations or experiments, to which there is found <lb></lb>in Scripture another Concluſion repugnant; the very Profeſſors <lb></lb>of that Science ought of themſelves to reſolve their Demonſtrati­<lb></lb>ons, and diſcover the falacies of their own Experiments, without <lb></lb>repairing to Theologers and Textuaries, it not ſuiting (as hath <lb></lb>been ſaid) with the dignity of <emph type="italics"></emph>Theologie<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> to ſtoop to the inveſtiga­<lb></lb>tion of the falacies of the inferior Sciences: But it ſufficeth her, <lb></lb>to determine the truth of the Concluſion with her abſolute Au­<lb></lb>thority, and by her infallibility. </s>

<s>And then the Natural Conclu­<lb></lb>ſions in which they ſay that we ought to bide by the meer Au­<lb></lb>thority of the Scripture, without gloſſing, or expounding it to <lb></lb>Senſes different from the Words, they affirm to be Thoſe of <lb></lb>which the Scripture ſpeaketh alwaies in the ſame manner; and <lb></lb>the Holy Fathers all receive, and expound to the ſame <lb></lb>Senſe.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>Now as to theſe Determinations, I have had occaſion to conſi­<lb></lb>der ſome particulars (which I will purpoſe) for that I was made <lb></lb>cautious thereof, by thoſe who underſtand more than I in theſe <lb></lb>buſineſſes, and to whoſe judgments I alwaies ſubmit my ſelf. <lb></lb></s>

<s>And firſt I could ſay, that there might poſſibly a certain kinde of <lb></lb>equivocation interpoſe, in that they do not diſtinguiſh the prehe­<lb></lb>minences whereby Sacred <emph type="italics"></emph>Theologie<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> meriteth the Title of Queen. <pb xlink:href="066/01/016.jpg" pagenum="441"></pb>For it might be called ſo, either becauſe that that which is taught <lb></lb>by all the other Sciences, is found to be comprized and demonſtra­<lb></lb>ted in it, but with more excellent means, and with more ſublime <lb></lb>Learning; in like manner, as for example; The Rules of meaſuring <lb></lb>of Land, &amp; of Accountantſhip are much more excellently contain­<lb></lb>ed in the Arithmatick and Geometry of <emph type="italics"></emph>Euclid,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> than in the Practi­<lb></lb>ſes of Surveyours and Accomptants: Or becauſe the Subject about <lb></lb>which <emph type="italics"></emph>Theologie<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> is converſant, excelleth in Dignity all the other <lb></lb>Subjects, that are the Matters of other Sciences: As alſo becauſe <lb></lb>its Documents are divulged by nobler waies. </s>

<s>That the Title <lb></lb>and Authority of Queen belongeth to <emph type="italics"></emph>Theologie<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> in the firſt <lb></lb>Senſe, I think that no Theologers will affirm, that have but any <lb></lb>in-ſight into the other Sciences; of which there are none (as I be­<lb></lb>lieve) that will ſay that Geometry, Aſtronomy Muſick, and Me­<lb></lb>dicine are much more excellently and exactly contained in the <lb></lb>Sacred Volumes, than in the Books of <emph type="italics"></emph>Archimedes,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> in <emph type="italics"></emph>Ptolomy,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> in <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Boetius,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and in <emph type="italics"></emph>Galen.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Therefore it is probable that the Regal <lb></lb>Preheminence is given her upon the ſecond account, namely, By <lb></lb>reaſon of the Subject, and the admirable communicating of the <lb></lb>Divine Revelations in thoſe Concluſions which by other means <lb></lb>could not be conceived by men, and which chiefly concern the <lb></lb>acquiſt of eternal Beatitude. </s>

<s>Now if <emph type="italics"></emph>Theologie<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> being conver­<lb></lb>ſant about the loftieſt Divine Contemplation, and reſiding for <lb></lb>Dignity in the Regal Throne of the Sciences, (whereby ſhe be­<lb></lb>cometh of higheſt Authority) deſcendeth not to the more mean <lb></lb>and humble Speculations of the inferior Sciences: Nay; (as hath <lb></lb>been declared above) hath no regard to them, as not concerning <lb></lb>Bearitude; the Profeſſors thereof ought not to arrogate to them­<lb></lb>ſelves the Authority to determin of Controverſies in thoſe Pro­<lb></lb>feſſions which have been neither practiſed nor ſtudied by them. <lb></lb></s>

<s>For this would be as if an Abſolute Prince, knowing that he <lb></lb>might freely command, and cauſe himſelf to be obeyed, ſhould <lb></lb>(being neither Phiſitian nor Architect) undertake to adminiſter <lb></lb>Medicines, and erect Buildings after his own faſhion, to the great <lb></lb>endangering af the lives of the poor Patients, and to the manifeſt <lb></lb>deſtruction of the Edifices.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>Again, to command the very Profeſſors of <emph type="italics"></emph>Aſtronomy,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> that <lb></lb>they of themſelves ſee to the confuting of their own Obſerva­<lb></lb>tions and Demonſtrations, as thoſe that can be no other but <lb></lb>Falacies and Sophiſmes, is to enjoyn a thing beyond all poſſibi­<lb></lb>lity of doing: For it is not onely to command them that they do <lb></lb>not ſee that which they ſee, and that they do not underſtand <lb></lb>that which they underſtand; but that in ſeeking, they finde the <lb></lb>contrary of that which they happen to meet with. </s>

<s>Therefore be­<lb></lb>fore that this is to be done, it would be neceſſary that they were <pb xlink:href="066/01/017.jpg" pagenum="442"></pb>ſhewed the way how to make the Powers of the Soul to command <lb></lb>one another, and the inferior the Superior; ſo that the imaginati­<lb></lb>on and will might, and ſhould believe contrary to what the Intel­<lb></lb>lect underſtands: I ſtill mean in Propoſitions purely Natural, and <lb></lb>which are not <emph type="italics"></emph>de Fide,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and not in the Supernatural, which are <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>de Fide.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>I would entreat theſe Wiſe and Prudent Fathers, that they <lb></lb>would withal diligence conſider the difference that is between <lb></lb>Opinable and Demonſtrative Doctrines: To the end, that well <lb></lb>weighing in their minds with what force Neceſſary Illations ob­<lb></lb>lige, they might the better aſcertain themſelves, that it is not in <lb></lb>the Power of the Profeſſors of Demonſtrative Sciences to change <lb></lb>their Opinions at pleaſure, and apply themſelves one while to <lb></lb>one ſide, and another while to another; and that there is a great <lb></lb>difference between commanding a Methametitian or a Philoſo­<lb></lb>pher, and the diſpoſing of a Lawyer or a Merchant; and that the <lb></lb>demonſtrated Concluſions touching the things of Nature and of <lb></lb>the Heavens cannot be changed with the ſame facility, as the <lb></lb>Opinions are touching what is lawful or not in a Contract, Bar­<lb></lb>gain, or Bill of Exchange. </s>

<s>This difference was well underſtood <lb></lb>by the Learned and Holy Fathers, as their having been at great <lb></lb>pains to confute many Arguments, or to ſay better, many Phi­<lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg832"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>loſophical Fallacies, doth prove unto us; and as may expreſly be <lb></lb>read in ſome of them, and particularly we have in S. <emph type="italics"></emph>Auguſtine<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>the following words: <emph type="italics"></emph>(g) This is to be held for an undoubt­<lb></lb>ed Truth, That we may be confident, that whatever the Sages of <lb></lb>this World have demonſtrated touching Natural Points, is no waies <lb></lb>contrary to our Bibles: And in caſe they teach any thing in their <lb></lb>Books that is contrary to the Holy Scriptures, we may without any <lb></lb>ſcruple conclude it to be moſt falſe; And aceording to our ability <lb></lb>let us make the ſame appear: And let us ſo keep the Faith of our <lb></lb>Lord, in whom are hidden all the Treaſures of Wiſdom; that we <lb></lb>be neither ſeduced with the Loquacity of falſe Philoſophy, nor <lb></lb>ſcared by the ſuperſtition of a counterfeit Religion.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg832"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(g) Hoc indu­<lb></lb>bitanter tenendum <lb></lb>eſt, ut quicquid <lb></lb>Sapientes hujus <lb></lb>Mundi, de Natu­<lb></lb>ra rerum veraci­<lb></lb>ter demonſtrare <lb></lb>potuerint, oſtenda­<lb></lb>mus, noſtris libris <lb></lb>non eſſe contrari­<lb></lb>um: quicquid au­<lb></lb>tem illi, in ſuis vo­<lb></lb>lumintbus, contra­<lb></lb>rium Sacris Lit­<lb></lb>teris docent, ſine <lb></lb>ulla dubitatione <lb></lb>credamus, id falſiſ­<lb></lb>ſimum eſſe, &amp; quo­<lb></lb>quo modo poſſu­<lb></lb>mus, etiam oſten­<lb></lb>damus; atque it a <lb></lb>teneamus Fidem <lb></lb>Domini noſtri, in <lb></lb>quaſunt abſconditi <lb></lb>omnes theſauri <lb></lb>Sapientiæ, ut ne­<lb></lb>que falſæ Philoſo­<lb></lb>phiæ loquacitate <lb></lb>ſeducamur, neque <lb></lb>ſimulata Religio­<lb></lb>nis ſuperſtitione <lb></lb>terreamur.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>From which words, I conceive that I may collect this Do­<lb></lb>ctrine, namely, That in the Books of the Wiſe of this World, <lb></lb>there are contained ſome Natural truths that are ſolidly demon­<lb></lb>ſtrated, and others again that are barely taught; and that as to <lb></lb>the firſt ſort, it is the Office of wiſe Divines to ſhew that they <lb></lb>are not contrary to the Sacred Scriptures; As to the reſt, taught, <lb></lb>but not neceſſarily demonſtrated, if they ſhall contain any thing <lb></lb>contrary to the Sacred Leaves, it ought to be held undoubtedly <lb></lb>falſe, and ſuch it ought by all poſſible waies to be demon­<lb></lb>ſtrated.<lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg833"></arrow.to.target></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg833"></margin.target>Gen. </s>

<s>ad Litteram. <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>lib<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> I. Cap. 

25.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>If therefore Natural Concluſions veritably demonſtrated, are <pb xlink:href="066/01/018.jpg" pagenum="443"></pb>not to be poſtpoſed to the Places of Scripture, but that it ought <lb></lb>to be ſhewn how thoſe Places do not interfer with the ſaid Con­<lb></lb>cluſions; then its neceſſary before a Phyſical Propoſition be <lb></lb>condemned, to ſhew that it is not neceſſarily demonſtrated; and <lb></lb>this is to be done not by them who hold it to be true, but by thoſe <lb></lb>who judge it to be falſe. </s>

<s>And this ſeemeth very reaſonable, <lb></lb>and agreeable to Nature; that is to ſay, that they may much <lb></lb>more eaſily find the fallacies in a Diſcourſe, who believe it to be <lb></lb>falſe, than thoſe who account it true and concludent. </s>

<s>Nay, in <lb></lb>this particular it will come to paſſe, that the followers of this o­<lb></lb>pinion, the more that they ſhall turn over Books, examine the <lb></lb>Arguments, repeat the Obſervations, and compare the Experi­<lb></lb>ments, the more ſhall they be confirmed in this belief. </s>

<s>And your <lb></lb>Highneſs knoweth what happened to the late Mathematick Pro­<lb></lb>feſſor in the Univerſity of <emph type="italics"></emph>Piſa,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Who betook himſelf in his old <lb></lb>age to look into the Doctrine of <emph type="italics"></emph>Copernicus,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> with hope that he <lb></lb>might be able ſolidly to confute it (for that he held it ſo far to <lb></lb>be falſe, as that he had never ſtudied it) but it was his fortune, <lb></lb>that as ſoon as he had underſtood the grounds, proceedings, and <lb></lb>demonſtrations of <emph type="italics"></emph>Copernicus,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> he found himſelf to be perſwaded, <lb></lb>and of an oppoſer became his moſt confident Defender. </s>

<s>I <lb></lb>might alſo nominate other ^{*} Mathematicians, who being moved </s></p><p type="main">

<s><arrow.to.target n="marg834"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>by my laſt Diſcoveries, have confeſſed it neceſsary to change the <lb></lb>formerly received Conſtitution of the World, it not being able <lb></lb>by any means to ſubſiſt any longer.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg834"></margin.target>* P. </s>

<s>Clavius the <lb></lb>Jeſuite.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>If for the baniſhing this Opinion and Hypotheſis out of the <lb></lb>World, it were enough to ſtop the mouth of one alone, as it <lb></lb>may be they perſwade themſelves who meaſuring others judge­<lb></lb>ments by their own, think it impoſſible that this Doctrine ſhould <lb></lb>be able to ſubſiſt and finde any followers, this would be very ea­<lb></lb>ſie to be done, but the buſineſs ſtandeth otherwiſe: For to <lb></lb>execute ſuch a determination, it would be neceſſary to prohibite <lb></lb>not onely the Book of <emph type="italics"></emph>Copernicus,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and the Writings of the o­<lb></lb>ther Authors that follow the ſame opinion, but to interdict the <lb></lb>whole Science of <emph type="italics"></emph>Aſtronomy<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; and which is more, to forbid men <lb></lb>looking towards Heaven, that ſo they might not ſee <emph type="italics"></emph>Mars<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Venus<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> at one time neer to the Earth, and at another farther off, <lb></lb>with ſuch a difference that the latter is found to be fourty times, <lb></lb>and the former ſixty times bigger in ſurface at one time than at <lb></lb>another; and to the end, that the ſame <emph type="italics"></emph>Venus<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> might not be <lb></lb>diſcovered to be one while round, and another while forked, with <lb></lb>moſt ſubtil hornes: and many other ſenſible Obſervations which <lb></lb>can never by any means be reconciled to the <emph type="italics"></emph>Ptolomaick<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Syſteme, <lb></lb>but are unanſwerable Arguments for the <emph type="italics"></emph>Copernican.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>But the prohibiting of <emph type="italics"></emph>Copernicus<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> his Book, now that by many <pb xlink:href="066/01/019.jpg" pagenum="444"></pb>new Obſervations, and by the application of many of the Lear­<lb></lb>ned to the reading of him, his Hypotheſis and Doctrine doth <lb></lb>every day appear to be more true, having admitted and tolerated <lb></lb>it for ſo many years, whilſt he was leſſe followed, ſtudied, and <lb></lb>confirmed, would ſeem, in my judgment, an affront to Truth, <lb></lb>and a ſeeking the more to obſcure and ſuppreſſe her, the more <lb></lb>ſhe ſheweth her ſelf clear and perſpicuous.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>The aboliſhing and cenſuring, not of the whole Book, but <lb></lb>onely ſo much of it as concerns this particular opinion of the <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Earths Mobility,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> would, if I miſtake not, be a greater detriment <lb></lb>to ſouls, it being an occaſion of great ſcandal, to ſee a Poſition <lb></lb>proved, and to ſee it afterwards made an Hereſie to believe it.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>The prohibiting of the whole Science, what other would it <lb></lb>be but an open contempt of an hundred Texts of the Holy Scri­<lb></lb>ptures, which teach us, That the Glory, and the Greatneſſe of <lb></lb>Almighty God is admirably diſcerned in all his Works, and di­<lb></lb>vinely read in the Open Book of Heaven? </s>

<s>Nor let any one <lb></lb>think that the Lecture of the lofty conceits that are written in <lb></lb>thoſe Leaves finiſh in only beholding the Splendour of the Sun, <lb></lb>and of the Stars, and their riſing and ſetting, (which is the term <lb></lb>to which the eyes of bruits and of the vulgar reach) but there <lb></lb>are couched in them myſteries ſo profound, and conceipts ſo ſub­<lb></lb>lime, that the vigils, labours, and ſtudies of an hundred and an <lb></lb>hundred acute Wits, have not yet been able thorowly to dive <lb></lb>into them after the continual diſquiſition of ſome thouſands of <lb></lb>years. </s>

<s>But let the Unlearned believe, that like as that which <lb></lb>their eyes diſcern in beholding the aſpect of a humane body, is <lb></lb>very little in compariſon of the ſtupendious Artifices, which an <lb></lb>exquiſite and curious Anatomiſt or Philoſopher finds in the ſame <lb></lb>when he is ſearching for the uſe of ſo many Muſcles, Tendons, <lb></lb>Nerves, and Bones; and examining the Offices of the Heart, <lb></lb>and of the other principal Members, ſeeking the ſeat of the vi­<lb></lb>tal Faculties, noting and obſerving the admirable ſtructures of <lb></lb>the Inſtruments of the Senſes, and, without ever making an end <lb></lb>of ſatisfying his curioſity and wonder, contemplating the Re­<lb></lb>ceptacles of the Imagination, of the Memory, and of the Un­<lb></lb>derſtanding; So that which repreſents it ſelf to the meer ſight, <lb></lb>is as nothing in compariſon and proportion to the ſtrange Won­<lb></lb>ders, that by help of long and accurate Obſervations the Wit <lb></lb>of Learned Men diſcovereth in Heaven. </s>

<s>And this is the ſub­<lb></lb>ſtance of what I had to conſider touching this particular.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>In the next place, as to thoſe that adde, That thoſe Natural <lb></lb>Propoſitions of which the Scripture ſtill ſpeaks in one conſtant <lb></lb>tenour, and which the Fathers all unanimouſly receive in the <lb></lb>ſame ſenſe, ought to be accepted according to the naked and <pb xlink:href="066/01/020.jpg" pagenum="445"></pb>literal ſenſe of the Words, without gloſſes and interpretations; <lb></lb>and received and held for moſt certain and true; and that con­<lb></lb>ſequently the Mobility of the Sun, and Stability of the Earth, <lb></lb>as being ſuch, are <emph type="italics"></emph>de Fide<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> to be held for true, and the contrary <lb></lb>opinion to be deemed Heretical: I ſhall propoſe to conſidera­<lb></lb>tion, in the firſt place, That of Natural Propoſitions, ſome there <lb></lb>are, of which all humane Science and Diſcourſe can furniſh us <lb></lb>only with ſome plauſible opinion, and probable conjecture ra­<lb></lb>ther than with any certain and demonſtrative knowledge; as for <lb></lb>example, whether the Stars be animated: Others there are, of <lb></lb>which we have, or may confidently believe that we may have, <lb></lb>by Experiments, long Obſervations, and Neceſſary Demonſtra­<lb></lb>tions an undubitable aſſurance; as for inſtance, whether the <lb></lb>Earth and Heavens move, or not; whether the Heavens are <lb></lb>Spherical, or otherwiſe. </s>

<s>As to the firſt ſort, I doubt not in the <lb></lb>leaſt, that if humane Ratiocinations cannot reach them, and <lb></lb>that conſequently there is no Science to be had of them, but on­<lb></lb>ly an Opinion or Belief, we ought fully and abſolutely to com­<lb></lb>ply with the meer Verbal Senſe of the Scripture: But as to the <lb></lb>other Poſitions, I ſhould think (as hath been ſaid above) That <lb></lb>we are firſt to aſcertain our ſelves of the fact it ſelf, which will <lb></lb>aſſiſt us in finding out the true ſenſes of the Scriptures; which <lb></lb>ſhall moſt certainly be found to accord with the fact demonſtra­<lb></lb>ted, for two truths can never contradict each other. </s>

<s>And <lb></lb>this I take to be a Doctrine orthodox and undoubted, for that I <lb></lb>ſinde it written in Saint <emph type="italics"></emph>Auguſtine,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> who ſpeaking to our point <lb></lb>of the Figure of Heaven, and what it is to be believed to be, in <lb></lb>regard that which Aſtronomers affirm concerning it ſeemeth to <lb></lb>be, contrary to the Scripture, (they holding it to be rotund, <lb></lb>and the Scripture calling it as it were a ^{*} Curtain, determi­<lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg835"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>neth that we are not at all to regard that the Scripture contra­<lb></lb>dicts Aſtronomers; but to believe its Authority, if that which <lb></lb>they ſay ſhall be falſe, and founded, only on the conjectures of <lb></lb>humane infirmity: but if that which which they affirm be pro­<lb></lb>ved by indubitable Reaſons, this Holy Father doth not ſay, <lb></lb>that the Aſtronomers are to be enjoyned, that they themſelves <lb></lb>reſolving and renouncing their Demonſtrations do declare their <lb></lb>Concluſion to be falſe, but ſaith, that it ought to be de­<lb></lb>monſtrated, That what is ſaid in Scripture of a Curtain is not <lb></lb>contrary to their true Demonſtrations. </s>

<s>Theſe are his words: <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg836"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>(h) But ſome object; How doth it appear, that the ſaying in our <lb></lb>Bibles,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Who ſtretcheth out the Heaven as a Curtain, <emph type="italics"></emph>maketh <lb></lb>not againſt thoſe who maintain the Heavens to be in figure of a <lb></lb>Sphere? </s>

<s>Let it be ſo, if that be falſe which they affirme: For <lb></lb>that is truth which is ſpoke by Divine Authority, rather than<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>


<pb xlink:href="066/01/021.jpg" pagenum="446"></pb><emph type="italics"></emph>that which proceeds from Humane Inſirmity. </s>

<s>But if peradven­<lb></lb>ture they ſhould be able to prove their Poſition by ſuch Experiments <lb></lb>as puts it out of queſtion, it is to be proved, that what is ſaid in <lb></lb>Scripture concerning a Curtain, doth in no wiſe contradict <lb></lb>their manifeſt Reaſons.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg835"></margin.target>* <emph type="italics"></emph>Pelle,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> a Skin in <lb></lb>the Original, out <lb></lb>in our Bibles a <lb></lb>Curtain.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg836"></margin.target>(h) <emph type="italics"></emph>Sed ait ali­<lb></lb>quis, quomodo non <lb></lb>eſt coutrarium iis, <lb></lb>qui figur am Sphæ­<lb></lb>ræ Cœlo tribunt, <lb></lb>quod ſcriptum eſt <lb></lb>en Libris Noſtris,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>Qui extendit Cœ­<lb></lb>lum, ſicut pellem? <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Stt ſane contrari­<lb></lb>um, ſi falſum eſt, <lb></lb>quod illi dicunt: <lb></lb>hoc enim verum <lb></lb>eſt, quod Divina <lb></lb>dicit authoritas, <lb></lb>potius quans illud, <lb></lb>quod humana in­<lb></lb>firmitas conjicit. <lb></lb></s>

<s>Sed ſi forte illud <lb></lb>talibus illi docu­<lb></lb>mentis probare po­<lb></lb>tuerint, at dubi­<lb></lb>tari inde non debe­<lb></lb>at; demonſtrandum <lb></lb>eſt, hoc quod apud <lb></lb>nos eſt de Pelle di­<lb></lb>ctum, veris illis <lb></lb>rationibus non eſſe <lb></lb>contrarium.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>He proceedeth afterwards to admoniſh us that we ought to be <lb></lb>no leſs careful and obſervant in reconciling a Text of Scripture <lb></lb>with a demonſtrated Natural Propoſition, than with another <lb></lb>Text of Scripture which ſhould ſound to a contrary Senſe. </s>

<s>Nay <lb></lb>methinks that the circumſpection of this Saint is worthy to be ad­<lb></lb>mired and imitated, who even in obſcure Concluſions, and of <lb></lb>which we may aſſure our ſelves that we can have no knowledge <lb></lb>or Science by humane demonſtration, is very reſerved in deter­<lb></lb>mining what is to be believed, as we ſee by that which he wri­<lb></lb>teth in the end of his ſecond Book, <emph type="italics"></emph>de Geneſi ad Litteram,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> ſpeak­<lb></lb>ing, whether the Stars are to be believed animate: <emph type="italics"></emph>(i) Which<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg837"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>particular, although (at preſent) it cannot eaſily be comprehended, <lb></lb>yet I ſuppoſe in our farther Progreſs of bandling the Scriptures, <lb></lb>we may meet with ſome more pertinent places, upon which it will <lb></lb>be permitted us (if not to determin any thing for certain, yet) to <lb></lb>ſuggeſt ſomewhat concerning this matter, according to the dictates <lb></lb>of Sacred Authority. </s>

<s>But now, the moderation of pious gravity <lb></lb>being alwaies obſerved, we ought to receive nothing raſhly in <lb></lb>a doubtful point, leaſt perhaps we reject that out of reſpect to <lb></lb>our Errour, which hereafter Truth may diſcover, to be in no <lb></lb>wiſe repugnant to the Sacred Volumes of the Old and New Te­<lb></lb>ſtament.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg837"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(i) Quod licet in <lb></lb>praſenti facile non <lb></lb>poſſit comprehendi; <lb></lb>arbitror tamen, in <lb></lb>proceſſis tract an­<lb></lb>dærum Scriptura­<lb></lb>rum, opportuntora <lb></lb>loca poſſe occurre­<lb></lb>re, ubinobis de hac <lb></lb>re, ſecundum San­<lb></lb>ctæ auctoritatis <lb></lb>Litteras, etſi non <lb></lb>oſtendere certum <lb></lb>aliquid, tamen cre­<lb></lb>dere licebit. </s>

<s>Nunc <lb></lb>autem, ſervat â <lb></lb>ſemper moderatio­<lb></lb>ne piæ gravitatis, <lb></lb>nihil credere dere <lb></lb>obſcura temere <lb></lb>debemus; ne fortè, <lb></lb>quoà poſtea verit as <lb></lb>patefecerit, quam­<lb></lb>vis Libris San­<lb></lb>ctis, ſive Teſta­<lb></lb>menti veteris, ſive, <lb></lb>novi nullo modo eſ­<lb></lb>ſe poſſit æeverſum, <lb></lb>tamen propter a­<lb></lb>morem noſtri er­<lb></lb>roris, oderimus.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>By this and other places (if I deceive not my ſelf) the intent <lb></lb>of the Holy Fathers appeareth to be, That in Natural queſtions, <lb></lb>and which are not <emph type="italics"></emph>de Fide,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> it is firſt to be conſidered, whether <lb></lb>they be indubitably demonſtrated, or by ſenſible Experiments <lb></lb>known; or whether ſuch a knowledge and demonſtration is to be <lb></lb>had; which having obtained, and it being the gift of God, it <lb></lb>ought to be applyed to find out the true Sences of the Sacred Pa­<lb></lb>ges in thoſe places, which in appearance might ſeem to ſpeak to <lb></lb>a contrary meaning: Which will unqueſtionably be pierced into <lb></lb>by Prudent Divines, together with the occaſions that moved the <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg838"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>Holy Ghoſt, (for our exerciſe, or for ſome other reaſon to me un­<lb></lb>known) to veil it ſelf ſometimes under words of different ſigni­<lb></lb>fications.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg838"></margin.target>Id. </s>

<s>D Aug. </s>

<s>in <lb></lb>Gen. <emph type="italics"></emph>ad Lute­<lb></lb>ram,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> lib. 

1. <emph type="italics"></emph>in fine.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>As to the other point, Of our regarding the Primary Scope of <lb></lb>thoſe Sacred Volumes, I cannot think that their having ſpoken <lb></lb>alwaies in the ſame tenour, doth any thing at all diſturb this <lb></lb>Rule. </s>

<s>For if it hath been the Scope of the Scripture by way of <lb></lb>condeſcention to the capacity of the Vulgar at any time, to ex­


<pb xlink:href="066/01/022.jpg" pagenum="447"></pb>preſs a Propoſition in words, that bear a ſenſe different from the <lb></lb>Eſſence of the ſaid Propoſition; why might it not have obſerved <lb></lb>the ſame, and for the ſame reſpect, as often as it had occaſion to <lb></lb>ſpeak of the ſame thing? </s>

<s>Nay I conceive, that to have done <lb></lb>otherwiſe, would but have encreaſed the confuſion, and dimi­<lb></lb>niſhed the credit that theſe Sacred Records ought to have a­<lb></lb>mongſt the Common People.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>Again, that touching the Reſt and Motion of the Sun and <lb></lb>Earth, it was neceſſary, for accommodation. </s>

<s>to Popular Capa­<lb></lb>city, to aſſert that which the Litteral ſenſe of the Scripture im­<lb></lb>porteth, experience plainly proveth: For that even to our dayes <lb></lb>people far leſs rude, do continue in the ſame Opinion upon Rea­<lb></lb>ſons, that if they were well weighed and examined, would be <lb></lb>found to be extream trivial, and upon Experiments, either whol­<lb></lb>ly falſe, or altogether beſides the purpoſe. </s>

<s>Nor is it worth <lb></lb>while to go about to remove them from it, they being incapable <lb></lb>of the contrary Reaſons that depend upon too exquiſite Obſer­<lb></lb>vations, and too ſubtil Demonſtrations, grounded upon Abſtra­<lb></lb>ctions, which, for the comprehending of them, require too ſtrong <lb></lb>an Imagination. </s>

<s>Whereupon, although that the Stability of <lb></lb>Heaveu, and Motion of the Earth ſhould be more than certain <lb></lb>and demonſtrated to the Wiſe; yet nevertheleſs it would be <lb></lb>neceſſary, for the conſervation of credit amongſt the Vulgar, to <lb></lb>affirm the contrary: For that of a thouſand ordinary men, that <lb></lb>come to be queſtioned concerning theſe particulars, its probab e <lb></lb>that there will not be found ſo much as one that will not an­<lb></lb>ſwer that he thinketh, and ſo certainly he doth, that the Sun <lb></lb>moveth, and the Earth ſtandeth ſtill. </s>

<s>But yet none ought to <lb></lb>take this common Popular Aſſent to be any Argument of the <lb></lb>truth of that which is affirmed: For if we ſhould examine <lb></lb>theſe very men touching the grounds and motives by which they <lb></lb>are induced to believe in that manner; and on the other ſide <lb></lb>ſhould hear what Experiments and Demonſtrationslperſwade <lb></lb>thoſe few others to believe the contrary, we ſhould finde theſe <lb></lb>latter to be moved by moſt ſolid Reaſons, and the former by <lb></lb>ſimple appearances, and vain and ridiculous occurrences. </s>

<s>That <lb></lb>therefore it was neceſſary to aſſign Motion to the Sun, and Reſt <lb></lb>to the earth, leſt the ſhallow capacity of the Vulgar ſhould be <lb></lb>confounded, amuſed, and rendred obſtinate and contumacious, <lb></lb>in giving credit to the principal Articles, and which are abſolute­<lb></lb>ly <emph type="italics"></emph>de fide,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> it is ſufficiently obvious. </s>

<s>And if it was neceſſary ſo <lb></lb>to do, it is not at all to be wondred at, that it was with extraor­<lb></lb>dinary Wiſdom ſo done, in the Divine Scriptures.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>But I will alledge further, That not onely a reſpect to the <lb></lb>Incapacity of the Vulgar, but the current Opinion of thoſe times 


<pb xlink:href="066/01/023.jpg" pagenum="448"></pb>made the Sacred Writers, in the points that were not neceſſary <lb></lb>to ſalvation, to accommodate themſelves more to the received <lb></lb>uſe, than to the true Eſſence of things: Of which S. <emph type="italics"></emph>Hierom<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>treating, writeth: <emph type="italics"></emph>(k) As if many things were not ſpoken in<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg839"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>the Holy Scriptures according to the judgement of thoſe times <lb></lb>in which they were acted, and not according to that which <lb></lb>truth contained.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> And elſewhere, the ſame Saint: <emph type="italics"></emph>(l) It is the cu­<lb></lb>ſtome for the Pen-men of Scripture, to deliver their Judgments in <lb></lb>many things, according to the common received opinion that their <lb></lb>times had of them.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> And ^{*} S. <emph type="italics"></emph>Thomas Aquinas<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> in <emph type="italics"></emph>Job<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> upon thoſe <lb></lb>words, <emph type="italics"></emph>Qui extendit Aquilonem ſuper vacuum, &amp; appendit<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg840"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Terram ſuper nihilum<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>: Noteth that the Scripture calleth that <lb></lb>ſpace <emph type="italics"></emph>Vacuum<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>Nihilum,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> which imbraceth and invironeth the <lb></lb>Earth, and which we know, not to be empty, bat filled with Air; <lb></lb>Nevertheleſſe, ſaith he, The Scripture to comply with the appre­<lb></lb>henſion of the Vulgar, who think that in that ſame ſpace there <lb></lb>is nothing, calleth it <emph type="italics"></emph>Vacuum<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>Nihilum.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Here the words of <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg841"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>S. <emph type="italics"></emph>Thomas, Quod de ſuperiori Hæmiſphærio Cœli nibil nobis ap­<lb></lb>paret, niſi ſpatium aëre plenum, quod vulgares homines reputant <lb></lb>Vacnum; loquitur enim ſecundum exiſtimationem vulgarium ho­<lb></lb>minum, prout eſt mos in Sacra Scriptura.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Now from this Place <lb></lb>I think one may very Logically argue, That the Sacred Scripture <lb></lb>for the ſame reſpect had much more reaſon to phraſe the Sun mo­<lb></lb>veable, and the Earth immoveable. </s>

<s>For if we ſhould try the ca­<lb></lb>pacity of the Common People, we ſhould find them much more <lb></lb>unapt to be perſwaded of the ſtability of the Sun, and Motion <lb></lb>of the Earth, than that the ſpace that environeth it is full of Air. <lb></lb></s>

<s>Therefore if the ſacred Authors, in this point, which had not ſo <lb></lb>much difficulty to be beat into the capacity of the Vulgar, have <lb></lb>notwithſtanding forborn to attempt perſwading them unto it, it <lb></lb>muſt needs ſeem very reaſonable that in other Propoſitions much <lb></lb>more abſtruſe they have obſerved the ſame ſtile. </s>

<s>Nay <emph type="italics"></emph>Copernicus<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>himſelf, knowing what power an antiquated cuſtome and way <lb></lb>of conceiving things become familiar to us from our infancy <lb></lb>hath in our Fancy, that he might not increaſe confuſion and dif­<lb></lb>ficulty in our apprehenſions, after he had firſt demonſtrated, <lb></lb>That the Motions which appear to us to belong to the Sun, or to <lb></lb>the Firmament, are really in the Earth; in proceeding after­<lb></lb>wards to reduce rhem into Tables, and to apply them to uſe, he <lb></lb>calleth them the Motions of the Sun, and of the Heaven that is <lb></lb>above the Planets; expreſly terming them the Riſing and Set­<lb></lb>ting of the Sun and Stars; and mutations in the obliquity of <lb></lb>the Zodiack, and variations in the points of the Equinoxes, the <lb></lb>Middle Motion, <emph type="italics"></emph>Anomalia, Proſthaphæreſis<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> of the Sun; and ſuch <lb></lb>other things; which do in reality belong to the Earth: But be­


<pb xlink:href="066/01/024.jpg" pagenum="449"></pb>cauſe being joyned to it, and conſequently having a ſhare in eve­<lb></lb>ry of its motions, we cannot immediately diſcern them in her, but <lb></lb>are forced to refer them to the Celeſtial Bodies in which they <lb></lb>appear; therefore we call them as if they were made there, where <lb></lb>they ſeem to us to be made. </s>

<s>Whence it is to be noted how ne­<lb></lb>neſſary it is to accommodate our diſcourſe to our old and accu­<lb></lb>ſtomed manner of underſtanding.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg839"></margin.target>(k) <emph type="italics"></emph>Quaſi non <lb></lb>multa in Scriptu­<lb></lb>ris Sanctis dican­<lb></lb>tur juxta opinio­<lb></lb>nem illius tempor is <lb></lb>quo geſt a referant, <lb></lb>&amp; non juxta quod <lb></lb>rei veritas contine­<lb></lb>bat.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> D. Hiero. </s>

<s>in c. <lb></lb></s>

<s>28. Jerem.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg840"></margin.target>(l) <emph type="italics"></emph>Conſuctudi­<lb></lb>nis Scripturarum <lb></lb>eſt, ut opinionem <lb></lb>multarum rerum <lb></lb>ſic narret Hiſtori­<lb></lb>cus, quomodo eo <lb></lb>tempore ab omni­<lb></lb>bus credebatur.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> In <lb></lb>cap. 

13. Matth.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg841"></margin.target>* D. Thomas, in <lb></lb>cap. </s>

<s>26. Job. </s>

<s>v. </s>

<s>7.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>That, in the next place, the common conſent of Fathers, in re­<lb></lb>ceiving a Natural Propoſition of Scripture, all in the ſame ſenſe <lb></lb>ought to Authorize it ſo far, as to make it become a matter of <lb></lb>Faith to believe it to be ^{*} ſo, I ſhould think that it ought at moſt <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg842"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>to be underſtood of thoſe Concluſions onely, which have beenby <lb></lb>the ſaid Fathers diſcuſſed, and ſifted with all poſſible diligence, <lb></lb>and debated on the one ſide, and on the other, and all things in <lb></lb>the end concurring to diſprove the one, and prove the other. </s>

<s>But <lb></lb>the Mobility of the Earth, and Stability of the Sun, are not of <lb></lb>this kinde; For, that the ſaid Opinion was in thoſe times total­<lb></lb>ly buried, and never brought amongſt the Queſtions of the Schools, <lb></lb>and not conſidered, much leſs followed by any one: So that it is to <lb></lb>be believed that it never ſo much as entered into the thought of <lb></lb>the Fathers to diſpute it, the Places of Scripture, their own Opinion, <lb></lb>and the aſſent of men having all concurred in the ſame judgement, <lb></lb>without the contradiction of any one, ſo far as we can finde.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg842"></margin.target>* Namely, ac­<lb></lb>cording to the Lit­<lb></lb>teral Senſe.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>Beſides, it is not enough to ſay that the Fathers all admit the <lb></lb>ſtability of the Earth, &amp;c. </s>

<s>Therefore to believe it is a matter of <lb></lb>Faith: But its neceſſary to prove that they have condemned the <lb></lb>contrary Opinion: For I may affirm and bide by this, That their <lb></lb>not having occaſion to make ſatisfaction upon the ſame, and to <lb></lb>diſcuſs it, hath made them to omit and admit it, onely as cur­<lb></lb>rent, but not as reſolved and proved And I think I have very <lb></lb>good Reaſon for what I ſay; For either the Fathers did make <lb></lb>reflection upon this Concluſion as controverted, or not: If not, <lb></lb>then they could determin nothing concerning it no not in their <lb></lb>private thoughts; and their incogitance doth not oblige us to <lb></lb>receive thoſe Precepts which they have not, ſo much as in their <lb></lb>intentions enjoyned. </s>

<s>But if they did reflect and conſider there­<lb></lb>on, they would long ſince have condemned it, if they had judged <lb></lb>it erroneous; which we do not find that they have done. </s>

<s>Nay, after <lb></lb>that ſome Divines have began to conſider it, we find that they <lb></lb>have not deem&#039;d it erroneous; as we read in the Commentaries of <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Didacus a Stunica<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> upon <emph type="italics"></emph>Job,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> in <emph type="italics"></emph>Cap. 

9, v. </s>

<s>6.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> on the words, <emph type="italics"></emph>Qui com­<lb></lb>movet Terram de loco ſuo,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> &amp;c. </s>

<s>Where he at large diſcourſeth upon <lb></lb>the <emph type="italics"></emph>Copernican<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Hypotheſis, and concludeth, <emph type="italics"></emph>That the Mobility <lb></lb>of the Earth, is not contrary to Scripture.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>Withal, I may juſtly queſtion the truth of that determination, <lb></lb>namely, That the Church enjoyneth us to hold ſuch like Natural 


<pb xlink:href="066/01/025.jpg" pagenum="450"></pb>Concluſions as matters of Faith, onely becauſe they bear the <lb></lb>ſtamp of an unanimous Interpretation of all the Fathers: And <lb></lb>I do ſuppoſe that it may poſſibly be, that thoſe who hold in this <lb></lb>manner, might poſſibly have gone about in favour of their own <lb></lb>Opinion, to have amplified the Decretal of the Councils; which <lb></lb>I cannot finde in this caſe to prohibit any other, ſave onely, <emph type="italics"></emph>Per­<lb></lb>verting to Senſes contrary to that of Holy Church, or of the <lb></lb>concurrent conſent of Fathers, thoſe places, and thoſe onely that <lb></lb>do pertain either to Faith or Manners, or concern our edification <lb></lb>in the Doctrine of Chriſtianity: And thus ſpeaks the Council of <lb></lb>Trent. </s>

<s>Seſſ.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 4. But the Mobility or Stability of the Earth, or <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg843"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>of the Sun, are not matters of Faith, nor contrary to Manners, <lb></lb>nor is there any one, that for the ſtabliſhing of this Opinion, <lb></lb>will pervert places of Scripture in oppoſition to the Holy Church, <lb></lb>or to the Fathers: Nay, Thoſe who have writ of this Doctrine, <lb></lb>did never make uſe of Texts of Scripture; that they might leave <lb></lb>it ſtill in the breaſts of Grave and Prudent Divines to interpret <lb></lb>the ſaid Places, according to their true meaning.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg843"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>Concil. </s>

<s>Trid. </s>

<s>Seſſ.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>4.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>And how far the Decrees of Councills do comply with the Ho­<lb></lb>ly Fathers in theſe particulars, may be ſufficiently manifeſt, in <lb></lb>that they are ſo far from enjoyning to receive ſuch like Natural <lb></lb>Concluſions for matters of Faith, or from cenſuring the contrary <lb></lb>Opinions as erronious; that rather reſpecting the Primitive and <lb></lb>primary intention of the Holy Church, they do adjudge it un­<lb></lb>profitable to be buſied in examining the truth thereof. </s>

<s>Let <lb></lb>your Highneſs be pleaſed to hear once again what S. <emph type="italics"></emph>Auguſtine<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>anſwers to to thoſe Brethren who put the Queſtion, Whether it <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg844"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>be true that Heaven moveth, or ſtandeth ſtill? (*) <emph type="italics"></emph>To theſe I <lb></lb>anſwer, That Points of this nature require a curious and pro­<lb></lb>found examination, that it may truly appear whether they be <lb></lb>true or falſe; a work inconſiſtent with my leaſure to under­<lb></lb>take or go thorow with, nor is it any way neceſſary for thoſe, <lb></lb>whom we deſire to inform of the things that more nearly <lb></lb>concern their own ſalvation and The Churches Be­<lb></lb>nefit.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg844"></margin.target>(*) <emph type="italics"></emph>His re­<lb></lb>ſpondeo, multum <lb></lb>ſubüliter, &amp; labo­<lb></lb>rioſis ratiombus, <lb></lb>iſta perquirere, ut <lb></lb>vere percipiatur, <lb></lb>ntrum ita, an non <lb></lb>ita ſit: quibus in­<lb></lb>eundis atque tra­<lb></lb>ctandis, nec mihi <lb></lb>jam tempus eſt, <lb></lb>nec illis eſſe debet, <lb></lb>quos ad ſalutem <lb></lb>ſuam, Sanctæ Ec­<lb></lb>cleſiæ neceſſariam <lb></lb>utilitatem cupi <lb></lb>mus informari.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>But yet although in Natural Propoſitions we were to take the <lb></lb>reſolution of condemning or admitting them from Texts of Scri­<lb></lb>pture unanimouſly expounded in the ſame Senſe by all the Fa­<lb></lb>thers, yet do I not ſee how this Rule can hold in our Caſe; for that <lb></lb>upon the ſame Places we read ſeveral Expoſitions in the Fathers; <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg845"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>(m) Dionyſius Areopagita<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> ſaying, <emph type="italics"></emph>That the Primum Mobile, and <lb></lb>not the Sun ſtand ſtill.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Saint <emph type="italics"></emph>Auguſtine<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> is of the ſame Opinion; <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>(n) All the Celeſtial Bodies were immoveable.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> And with them <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg846"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>concurreth <emph type="italics"></emph>Abulenſis.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> But which is more, amongſt the Jewiſh <lb></lb>Authors (whom <emph type="italics"></emph>Joſephus<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> applauds) ſome have held, <emph type="italics"></emph>(o) That<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>


<pb xlink:href="066/01/026.jpg" pagenum="451"></pb><emph type="italics"></emph>The Sun did not really ſtand ſtill, but ſeemed ſo to do, during the<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg847"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>ſhort time in which Iſrael gave the overthrow to their Enemies.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>So for the Miracle in the time of <emph type="italics"></emph>Hezekiah, Paulus Burgenſis<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> is of <lb></lb>opinion that it was not wrought on the Sun, but on the Diall. <lb></lb></s>

<s>But that, in ſhort, it is neceſſary to Gloſſe and Interpret the <lb></lb>words of the Text in <emph type="italics"></emph>Joſhua,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> when ever the Worlds Syſteme <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg848"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>is in diſpute, I ſhall ſhew anon. </s>

<s>Now finally, granting to theſe <lb></lb>Gentlemen more than they demand, to wit, That we are whol­<lb></lb>ly to acquieſce in the judgment of Judicious Divines, and that <lb></lb>in regard that ſuch a particular Diſquiſition is not found to <lb></lb>have been made by the Ancient Fathers, it may be undertaken <lb></lb>by the Sages of our Age, who having firſt heard the Experiments, <lb></lb>Obſervations, Reaſons, and Demonſtrations of Philolophers and <lb></lb>Aftronomers, on the one ſide, and on the other (ſeeing that the <lb></lb>Controverſie is about Natural Problems, and Neceſſary <emph type="italics"></emph>Dilem­<lb></lb>ma&#039;s,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and which cannot poſſibly be otherwiſe than in one of <lb></lb>the two manners in controverſie) they may with competent cer­<lb></lb>tainty determine what Divine Inſpirations ſhall dictate to them. <lb></lb></s>

<s>But that without minutely examining and diſcuſſing all the Rea­<lb></lb>ſons on both ſides; and without ever comming to any certainty <lb></lb>of the truth of the Caſe, ſnch a Reſolution ſhould be taken, Is <lb></lb>not to be hoped from thoſe who do not ſtick to hazzard the Ma­<lb></lb>jeſty and Dignity of the Sacred Scripture, in defending the re­<lb></lb>putation of their vain Fancies; Nor to be feared from thoſe <lb></lb>who make it their whole buſineſſe, to examine with all in­<lb></lb>tenſneſs, what the Grounds of this Doctrine are; and that only <lb></lb>in an Holy Zeal for Truth, the Sacred Scriptures, and for the <lb></lb>Majeſty, Dignity, and Authority, in which every Chriſtian <lb></lb>ſhould indeavour to have them maintained. </s>

<s>Which Dignity, <lb></lb>who ſeeth not that it is with greater Zeal deſired and procured <lb></lb>by thoſe who, abſolutely ſubmitting themſelves to the Holy <lb></lb>Church, deſire, not that this, or that opinion may be prohibi­<lb></lb>ted, but onely that ſuch things may be propoſed to conſidera­<lb></lb>tion, as may the more aſcertain her in the ſafeſt choice, than by <lb></lb>thoſe who being blinded by their particular Intereſt, or ſtimula­<lb></lb>ted by malitious ſuggeſtions, preach that ſhe ſhould, without <lb></lb>more ado, thunder out Curſes, for that ſhe had power ſo to do: <lb></lb>Not conſidering that all that may be done is not alwayes conve­<lb></lb>nient to be done. </s>

<s>The Holy Fathers of old were not of this <lb></lb>opinion, but rather knowing of how great prejudice, and how <lb></lb>much againſt the primary intent of the Catholick Church, it <lb></lb>would be to go about from Texts of Scripture to decide Natu­<lb></lb>ral Concluſions, touching which, either Experiments or neceſſary <lb></lb>Demonſtrations, might in time to come evince the contrary, of <lb></lb>that which the naked ſenſe of the Words ſoundeth, they have 


<pb xlink:href="066/01/027.jpg" pagenum="452"></pb>not only proceeded with great circumſpection, but have left the <lb></lb>following Precepts for the inſtruction of others. <emph type="italics"></emph>(p) In points<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg849"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>obſcure and remote from our Sight, if we come to read any thing <lb></lb>out of Sacred Writ, that, with a<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Salvo <emph type="italics"></emph>to the Faith that we have <lb></lb>imbued, may correſpond with ſeveral conſtructions, let us not ſo <lb></lb>farre throw our ſelves upon any of them with a precipitous ob­<lb></lb>ſtinacy, as that if, perhaps the Truth being more diligently ſearch&#039;t <lb></lb>into, it ſhould juſtly fall to the ground, we might fall together <lb></lb>with it: and ſo ſhew that we contend not for the ſenſe of Divine <lb></lb>Scriptures, but our own, in that we would have that which is <lb></lb>our own to be the ſenſe of Scriptures, when as we ſhould ra­<lb></lb>ther deſire the Scriptures meaning to be ours.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg845"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(m) Non Solem, ſed <lb></lb>Primum Mobile <lb></lb>immotum conſti­<lb></lb>tiſſe<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>: Dioniſ. <lb></lb></s>

<s>Areop.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg846"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(n) Omnia cor­<lb></lb>pora Cæleſtia, im­<lb></lb>mota ſubſtitiſſe<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>:</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg847"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(o) Solem re­<lb></lb>vera non ſubſtitiſ­<lb></lb>ſe immorum, ſed <lb></lb>pro brevi tempore, <lb></lb>intra quod Iſræeli­<lb></lb>tæ, hoſtes ſuos fu­<lb></lb>derunt, id ita vi­<lb></lb>ſum eſſe.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg848"></margin.target>Iſa. Cap. 

38.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg849"></margin.target>(p) <emph type="italics"></emph>In rebus ob­<lb></lb>ſouris, atque a no­<lb></lb>ſtris oculis remi­<lb></lb>tiſſimis, ſiqua inde <lb></lb>ſcripta etiam divi­<lb></lb>næ legerimus, quæ <lb></lb>poſſint ſalva fide, <lb></lb>qua imbuimur, a­<lb></lb>liis atque altis pa­<lb></lb>rere ſentextiis, in <lb></lb>nullam earum nos <lb></lb>præcipiti affirma­<lb></lb>tione ita projici­<lb></lb>amus, ut ſi forte <lb></lb>ailigentiùs diſcuſ­<lb></lb>ſa veritas <expan abbr="eã">eam</expan> recte <lb></lb>labefact averit, corruamus: non pro ſententia Divinarum Scripturarum, ſed pro noſtra ita dimicantes, ut eam <lb></lb>velimus Scripturarum eſſe, quæ noſtra eſt, cum potius eam quæ Scripturarum eſt, noſtram eſſe velle debeamus,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>Divus Auguſtin. </s>

<s>in Gen. </s>

<s>ad Litteram, lib. 

2. c. </s>

<s>18. &amp; <expan abbr="ſeq.">ſeque</expan></s></p><p type="main">

<s>He goeth on, and a little after teacheth us, that no Propoſi­<lb></lb>tion can be againſt the Faith, unleſſe firſt it be demonſtrated <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg850"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>falſe; ſaying, <emph type="italics"></emph>(q) Tis not all the while contrary to Faith, until it <lb></lb>be diſproved by moſt certain Truth, which if it ſhould ſo be, the Holy <lb></lb>Scripture affirm&#039;d it not, but Humane Ignorance ſuppoſed it.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>Whereby we ſee that the ſenſes which we impoſe on Texts of <lb></lb>Scripture, would be falſe, when ever they ſhould diſagree with <lb></lb>Truths demonſtrated. </s>

<s>And therefore we ought, by help of de­<lb></lb>monſtrated Truth, to ſeek the undoubted ſenſe of Scripture: <lb></lb>and not according to the ſound of the words, that may ſeem <lb></lb>true to our weakneſſe, to go about, as it were, to force Na­<lb></lb>ture, and to deny Experiments and Neceſſary Demonſtra­<lb></lb>tions.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg850"></margin.target>(q) <emph type="italics"></emph>Tam diu non <lb></lb>eſt extra fidem, do­<lb></lb>nec Veritate cer­<lb></lb>tiſſima refellatur. <lb></lb></s>

<s>Quod ſi fæctum <lb></lb>fuerit, non hoc ha­<lb></lb>bebut Divina Scri­<lb></lb>ptura, ſed hoc ſen­<lb></lb>ſer at humana Ig­<lb></lb>norantia.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Ibid.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>Let Your Highneſſe be pleaſed to obſerve farther, with how <lb></lb>great circumſpection this Holy Man proceedeth, before he af­<lb></lb>firmeth any Interpretation of Scripture to be ſure, and in ſuch <lb></lb>wiſe certain, as that it need not fear the encounter of any diffi­<lb></lb>culty that may procure it diſturbance, for not contenting <lb></lb>himſelf that ſome ſenſe of Scripture agreeth with ſome Demon­<lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg851"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>ſtration, he ſubjoynes. <emph type="italics"></emph>(r) But if right Reaſon ſhall demon­<lb></lb>ſtrate this to be true, yet is it queſtionable whether in theſe words <lb></lb>of Sacred Scripture the Pen-man would have this to be under­<lb></lb>ſtood, or ſomewhat elſe, no leſſe true. </s>

<s>And in caſe the Context <lb></lb>of his Words ſhall prove that he intended not this, yet will not <lb></lb>that which he would have to be underſtood be therefore falſe, but <lb></lb>moſt true, aad that which is more profitable to be known.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg851"></margin.target>(r) <emph type="italics"></emph>Si autem <lb></lb>hoc verum eſſe ve­<lb></lb>ra ratio demon­<lb></lb>ſtraverit, adhuc <lb></lb>incertum erit, u­<lb></lb>trum hoc in illis <lb></lb>verbis Sanctorum <lb></lb>Librorum, Scrip­<lb></lb>tor ſentiri volue­<lb></lb>rit, an aliquid a­<lb></lb>liud non minus ve­<lb></lb>rum. </s>

<s>Quod ſi cætera contextio ſermonis non hoc eum voluiſſe probaverit, non ideo falſum erit aliud, quod ipſe <lb></lb>intelligi voluit, ſed &amp; verum, &amp; quod utilius cognoſcatur.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>But that which increaſeth our wonder concerning the cir­


<pb xlink:href="066/01/028.jpg" pagenum="453"></pb>cumſpection, wherewith this Pious Authour proceedeth, is, <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg852"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>that not truſting to his obſerving, that both Demonſtrative <lb></lb>Reaſons, and the ſenſe that the words of Scripture and the reſt <lb></lb>of the Context both precedent and ſubſequent, do conſpire to <lb></lb>prove the ſame thing, he addeth the following words.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg852"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(ſ) Si autem con­<lb></lb>textio Scripturæ, <lb></lb>hoc voluiſſe intel­<lb></lb>ligi Scriptorem, <lb></lb>non repugnaverit, <lb></lb>adhuc reſtabit <lb></lb>quærere, utrum &amp; <lb></lb>aliud non potuerit.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s><emph type="italics"></emph>(ſ) But if the Context do not hold forth any thing that may<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg853"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>diſprove this to be the Authors Senſé, it yet remains to enquire, <lb></lb>Whether the other may not be intended alſo.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> And not yet reſolving <lb></lb>to accept of one Senſe, or reject another, but thinking that he <lb></lb>could never uſe ſufficient caution, he proceedeth: <emph type="italics"></emph>(t) But if <lb></lb>ſo be we finde that the other may be alſo meant, it will be doubted <lb></lb>which of them he would have to ſtand; or which in probability he <lb></lb>may be thought to aim at, if the true circumſtances on both ſides be <lb></lb>weighed.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> And laſtly, intending to render a Reaſon of this his <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg854"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>Rule, by ſhewing us to what perils thoſe men expoſe the Scri­<lb></lb>ptures, and the Church; who, more reſpecting the ſupport of <lb></lb>their own errours, than the Scriptures Dignity, would ſtretch its <lb></lb>Authority beyond the Bounds which it preſcribeth to it ſelf, he <lb></lb>ſubjoyns the enſuing words, which of themſelves alone might <lb></lb>ſuffice to repreſs and moderate the exceſſive liberty, which ſome <lb></lb>think that they may aſſume to themſelves: <emph type="italics"></emph>(u) For it many <lb></lb>times falls out, that a Chriſtian may not ſo fully underſtand a <lb></lb>Point concerning the Earth, lieaven, and the reſt of this Worlds <lb></lb>Elements; the Motion, Converſion, Magnitude, and Diſtances of <lb></lb>the Stars, the certain defects of the Sun and Moon, the Revoluti­<lb></lb>ons of Years and Times, the Nature of Animals, Fruits, Stones, <lb></lb>and other things of like nature, as to defend the ſame by right <lb></lb>Reaſon, or make it out by Experiments. </s>

<s>But its too great an ab­<lb></lb>ſurdity, yea moſt pernicious, and chiefly to be avoided, to let an <lb></lb>Infidel finde a Chriſtian ſo ſtupid, that he ſhould argue theſe mat­<lb></lb>ters; as if they were according to Chriſtian Doctrine; and make <lb></lb>him (as the Proverb ſaith) ſcarce able to contain his laughter, ſee­<lb></lb>ing him ſo far from the Mark Nor is the matter ſo much that one <lb></lb>in an errour ſhould be laught at, but that our Authors ſhould be <lb></lb>thought by them that are without, to be of the ſame Opinion, and to <lb></lb>the great prejudice of thoſe, whoſe ſalvation we wait for, ſenſurcd <lb></lb>and rejected as unlearned. </s>

<s>For when they ſhal confute any one of the <lb></lb>Chriſtians in that matter, which they themſelvs thorowly under­<lb></lb>ſtand, and ſhall thereupon expreſs their light eſteem of our Books; <lb></lb>how ſhall theſe Volumes be believed touching the Reſurrection of <lb></lb>the Dead, the Hope of eternal Life, and the Kingdom of Heaven; <lb></lb>when, as to theſe Points which admit of preſent Demonſtration, <lb></lb>or undoubted Reaſons, they conceive them to be falſly written.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p>


<pb xlink:href="066/01/029.jpg" pagenum="454"></pb><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg853"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(t) Quod ſi &amp; <lb></lb>aliud potuiſſe inve­<lb></lb>nerimus, incertum <lb></lb>erit; quidnam eo­<lb></lb>rum ille voluerit: <lb></lb>aut utrumque vo­<lb></lb>luiſſe non inconve­<lb></lb>nienter creditur, ſi <lb></lb>utriuſque ſententiæ <lb></lb>certa circumſt an­<lb></lb>tia ſufragatur.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg854"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(u) Plerumque <lb></lb>enim accidit, at a­<lb></lb>liquid de Terra, de<lb></lb>Celo, de ceter is hu­<lb></lb>jus mundi elemen­<lb></lb>tis, de motu, con­<lb></lb>verſione, vel ctiam <lb></lb>magnitudine &amp; <lb></lb>intervallis Syde­<lb></lb>rum, de certis de­<lb></lb>fectibus Solis, &amp; <lb></lb>Lunæ, de eircuiti­<lb></lb>bus annorum &amp; <lb></lb>temporum; de Na­<lb></lb>turis animalium, <lb></lb>fruticum, lapidum, <lb></lb>atque bujuſmodi <lb></lb>ceter is, etiam non <lb></lb>Chriſtianus ita no­<lb></lb>verit, ut cirtiſſima <lb></lb>ratione vel experi­<lb></lb>entiâ teneat. </s>

<s>Tur­<lb></lb>pe autem eſt nimis <lb></lb>&amp; pernicioſum, ae <lb></lb>maxime caven­<lb></lb>dum, at Chriſtia­<lb></lb>num de his rebus <lb></lb>quaſi ſecundum <lb></lb>Chriſtianaslitter as <lb></lb>loquentem, ita de­<lb></lb>lirare quilibet in­<lb></lb>fiàelis audiat, ut, <lb></lb>quemadmodum di­<lb></lb>citur, toto Cælo er­<lb></lb>ræreconſpiciens, <expan abbr="ri-ſũtenere">ri­<lb></lb>ſuntenere</expan> vix poſſit: <lb></lb>&amp; non tam mole­<lb></lb>ſtum eſt, quod er­<lb></lb>rans homo deride­<lb></lb>retur, ſed quod au­<lb></lb>ctores noſtri, ab tis <lb></lb>qui foris ſunt, ta­<lb></lb>lia ſenſiſſe credun­<lb></lb>tur, &amp; cum magno exitio eorum, de quorum ſalute ſatagimus, tanquam indocti reprehenduntur atque reſpuuntur. <lb></lb></s>

<s>Cum enim quemquam de numero Chriſtiano um eainre, quam ip ſi optime norunt, deprehenderint, &amp; venam ſenten­<lb></lb>tiam ſuam de noſtris libris aſſerent; quo pacto illis Libris credituri ſunt, de Reſurrectione Mortuorum, &amp; de ſpe<lb></lb>vit æ eternæ, Regnoque Celorum; quando de his rebus quas jam experiri, vel indubitatis rationibus percipere potuerunt<lb></lb>fallaciter putaverint eſſe conſcriptos.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>And how much the truly Wiſe and Prudent Fathers are diſ­<lb></lb>pleaſed with theſe men, who in defence of Propoſitions which <lb></lb>they do not underſtand, do apply, and in a certain ſenſe pawn <lb></lb>Texts of Scripture, and afterwards go on to encreaſe their firſt <lb></lb>Errour, by producing other places leſs underſtood than the for­<lb></lb>mer. </s>

<s>The ſame Saint declareth in the expreſſions following: <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg855"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>(x) What trouble and ſorrow weak undertakers bring upon <lb></lb>their knowing Brethren, is not to be expreſſed; ſince when they <lb></lb>begin to be told and convinced of their falſe and unſound Opinion, <lb></lb>by thoſe who have no reſpect for the Authority of our Scriptures, <lb></lb>in defence of what through a fond Temerity, and moſt manifeſt fal­<lb></lb>ſity, they have urged; they fall to citing the ſaid Sacred Books <lb></lb>for proof of it, or elſe repeat many words by heart out of them, <lb></lb>which they conceive to make for their purpoſe; not knowing <lb></lb>either what they ſay, or whereof they affirm.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg855"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>(y) Quid enim <lb></lb>moleſtiæ, triſtiæque <lb></lb>ingerant prudenti­<lb></lb>bus fratribus, te­<lb></lb>nerarij præſumpto­<lb></lb>res, ſatis dici non <lb></lb>poteſt, cum, ſi <lb></lb>quando de falſa &amp; <lb></lb>prava opinione ſua <lb></lb>reprehendi &amp; con­<lb></lb>vinci cæperint, ab <lb></lb>iis qui noſtrorum <lb></lb>librorum auctori­<lb></lb>tate, &amp; aperliſſima <lb></lb>falfitate dixerunt, <lb></lb>eoſdnm libros San­<lb></lb>ctos, unde id pro­<lb></lb>bent, proferre co­<lb></lb>nantur; vel etiam <lb></lb>memoriter, quæ ad <lb></lb>teſtimonium vale­<lb></lb>re arbitrantur, <lb></lb>multa inde verba <lb></lb>pronunciant, non <lb></lb>intelligentes, neque <lb></lb>quæ loquuntur, ne­<lb></lb>que de quibus af­<lb></lb>firmant.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>In the number of theſe we may, as I conceive, account thoſe, <lb></lb>who, being either unwilling or unable to underſtand the De­<lb></lb>monſtrations and Experiments, wherewith the Author and fol­<lb></lb>lowers of this Opinion do confirm it, run upon all occaſions to <lb></lb>the Scriptures, not conſidering that the more they cite them, and <lb></lb>the more they perſiſt in affirming that they are very clear, and <lb></lb>do admit no other ſenſes, ſave thoſe which they force upon <lb></lb>them, the greater injury they do to the Dignity of them (if we <lb></lb>allowed that their judgments were of any great Authority) in <lb></lb>caſe that the Truth coming to be manifeſtly known to the con­<lb></lb>trary, ſhould occaſion any confuſion, at leaſt to thoſe who are <lb></lb>ſeparated from the Holy Church; of whom yet ſhe is very ſolici­<lb></lb>tous, and like a tender Mother, deſirous to recover them again <lb></lb>into her Lap. </s>

<s>Your Highneſs therefore may ſee how præpoſterouſ­<lb></lb>ly thoſe Perſons proceed, who in Natural Diſputations do range <lb></lb>Texts of Scripture in the Front for their Arguments; and ſuch <lb></lb>Texts too many times, as are but ſuperficially underſtood by them.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>But if theſe men do verily think, &amp; abſolutely believe that they <lb></lb>have the true ſence of Such a particular place of Scripture, it muſt <lb></lb>needs follow of conſequence, that they do likewiſe hold for certain, <lb></lb>that they have found the abſolute truth of that Natural Concluſi­<lb></lb>on, which they intend to diſpute:</s>

<s> And that withall, they do know <lb></lb>that they have a great advantage of their Adverſary, whoſe Lot it <lb></lb>is to defend the part that is falſe; in regard that he who maintain­<lb></lb>eth the Truth, may have many ſenſible experiments, and many ne­<lb></lb>ceſſary Demonſtrations on his ſide; whereas his Antagoniſt can <lb></lb>make uſe of no other than deceitful appearances, <emph type="italics"></emph>Paralogiſms<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Sophiſms.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Now if they keeping within natural bounds, &amp; produ­<lb></lb>cing no other Weapons but thoſe of Philoſophy, pretend however, <lb></lb>to have ſo much advantage of their Enemy; why do they after­


<pb xlink:href="066/01/030.jpg" pagenum="455"></pb>wards in coming to engage, preſently betake themſelves to a Wea­<lb></lb>pon inevitable &amp; dreadful to terrifie their Opponent with the ſole <lb></lb>beholding of it? </s>

<s>But if I may ſpeak the truth, I believe that they are <lb></lb>the firſt that are affrighted, and that perceiving themſelves unable <lb></lb>to bear up againſt the aſſaults of their Adverſary, go about to find <lb></lb>out ways how to keep them far enough off, forbidding unto them <lb></lb>the uſe of the Reaſon which the Divine Bounty had vouchſafed <lb></lb>them, &amp; abuſing the moſt equitable Authority of ſacred Scripture, <lb></lb>which rightly underſtood and applyed, can never, according to <lb></lb>the common Maxime of Divines, oppoſe the Manifeſt Experi­<lb></lb>ments, or Neceſſary Demonſtrations. </s>

<s>But theſe mens running <lb></lb>to the Scriptures for a Cloak to their inability to comprehend, <lb></lb>not to ſay reſolve the Reaſons alledged againſt them, ought (if I <lb></lb>be not miſtaken) to ſtand them in no ſtead: the Opinion which <lb></lb>they oppoſe having never as yet been condemned by Holy <lb></lb>Church. </s>

<s>So that if they would proceed with Candor, they <lb></lb>ſhould either by ſilence confeſs themſelves unable to handle ſuch <lb></lb>like points, or firſt conſider that it is not in the power of them or <lb></lb>others, but onely in that of the Pope, and of Sacred Councils to <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg856"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>cenſure a Poſition to be Erroneous: But that it is left to their <lb></lb>freedome to diſpute concerning its falſity. </s>

<s>And thereupon, <lb></lb>knowing that it is impoſſible that a Propoſition ſhould at the <lb></lb>ſame time be True and Heretical; they ought, I ſay, to imploy <lb></lb>themſelves in that work which is moſt poper to them, namely, <lb></lb>in demonſtrating the falſity thereof: whereby they may ſee <lb></lb>how needleſſe the prohibiting of it is, its falſhood being once <lb></lb>diſcovered, for that none would follow it: or the Prohibition <lb></lb>would be ſafe, and without all danger of Scandal. </s>

<s>Therefore <lb></lb>firſt let theſe men apply themſelves to examine the Arguments <lb></lb>of <emph type="italics"></emph>Copernicus<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and others; and leave the condemning of them <lb></lb>for Erroneous and Heretical to whom it belongeth: But yet let <lb></lb>them not hope ever to finde ſuch raſh and precipitous Determina­<lb></lb>tions in the Wary and Holy Fathers, or in the abſolute Wiſ­<lb></lb>dome of him that cannot erre, as thoſe into which they ſuffer <lb></lb>themſelves to be hurried by ſome particular Affection or Inte­<lb></lb>reſt of their own. </s>

<s>In theſe and ſuch other Poſitions, which are <lb></lb>not directly <emph type="italics"></emph>de Fide,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> certainly no man doubts but His Holineſs <lb></lb>hath alwayes an abſolute power of Admitting or Condemn­<lb></lb>ing them, but it is not in the power of any Creature to make <lb></lb>them to be true or falſe, otherwiſe than of their own nature, <lb></lb>and <emph type="italics"></emph>de facto<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> they are.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg856"></margin.target>If this paſſage <lb></lb>ſeem harſh, the <lb></lb>Reader muſt re­<lb></lb>member that I do <lb></lb>but Tranſlate.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>Therefore it is in my judgment more diſcretion to aſſure us <lb></lb>firſt of the neceſſary and immutable Truth of the Fact, (over <lb></lb>which none hath power) than without that certainty by condem­<lb></lb>ning one part to deprive ones ſelf of that authority of freedome 


<pb xlink:href="066/01/031.jpg" pagenum="456"></pb>to elect, making thoſe Determinations to become neceſſary, <lb></lb>which at preſent are indifferent and arbitrary, and reſt in the <lb></lb>will of Supreme Authority. </s>

<s>And in a word, if it be not poſ­<lb></lb>ſible that a Concluſion ſhould be declared Heretical, whilſt we <lb></lb>are not certain, but that it may be true, their pains are in vain <lb></lb>who pretend to condemn the Mobility of the Earth and Stabili­<lb></lb>ty of the Sun, unleſſe they have firſt demonſtrated it to be im­<lb></lb>poſſible and falſe.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>It remaineth now, that we conſider whether it be true, that <lb></lb>the Place in <emph type="italics"></emph>Joſhuab<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> may be taken without altering the pure ſig­<lb></lb>nification of the words: and how it can be that the Sun, obey­<lb></lb>ing the command of <emph type="italics"></emph>Joſhuah,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> which was, <emph type="italics"></emph>That it ſhould ſtand <lb></lb>ſtill,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> the day might thereupon be much lengthened. </s>

<s>Which bu­<lb></lb>ſineſſe, if the Celeſtial Motions be taken according to the <emph type="italics"></emph>Ptolo­<lb></lb>maick<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Syſteme, can never any wayes happen, for that the Sun <lb></lb>moving thorow the Ecliptick, according to the order of the <lb></lb>Signes, which is from Eaſt to Weſt (which is that which maketh <lb></lb>Day and Night) it is a thing manifeſt, that the Sun ceaſing its <lb></lb>true and proper Motion, the day would become ſhorter and not <lb></lb>longer; and that on the contrary, the way to lengthen it would <lb></lb>be to haſten and velocitate the Suns motion; inſomuch that to <lb></lb>cauſe the Sun to ſtay above the Horizon for ſome time, in one <lb></lb>and the ſame place, without declining towards the Weſt, it would <lb></lb>be neceſſary to accelerate its motion in ſuch a manner as that it <lb></lb>might ſeem equal to that of the <emph type="italics"></emph>Primum Mobile,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> which would be <lb></lb>an accelerating it about three hundred and ſixty times more than <lb></lb>ordinary. </s>

<s>If therefore <emph type="italics"></emph>Joſhuah<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> had had an intention that his <lb></lb>words ſhould be taken in their pure and proper ſignification, he <lb></lb>would have bid the Sun to have accelerated its Motion ſo, that <lb></lb>the Rapture of the <emph type="italics"></emph>Primum Mobile<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> might not carry it to the <lb></lb>Weſt: but becauſe his words were heard by people which hap­<lb></lb>ly knew no other Celeſtial Motion, ſave this grand and common <lb></lb>one, from Eaſt to Weſt, ſtooping to their Capacity, and having <lb></lb>no intention to teach them the Conſtitution of the Spheres, but <lb></lb>only that they ſhould perceive the greatneſs of the Miracle <lb></lb>wrought, in the lengthening of the Day, he ſpoke according to <lb></lb>their apprehenſion. </s>

<s>Poſſibly this Conſideration moved <emph type="italics"></emph>Diony­<lb></lb>ſius Areopagita<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> to ſay that in this Miracle the <emph type="italics"></emph>Primum Mobile<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>ſtood ſtill, and this ſtopping, all the Celeſtial Spheres did of <lb></lb>conſequence ſtay: of which opinion is S. <emph type="italics"></emph>Auguſtine<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> himſelf, and <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Abulenſis<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> at large confirmeth it. </s>

<s>Yea, that <emph type="italics"></emph>Joſhua&#039;s<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> intention <lb></lb>was, that the whole Syſteme of the Celeſtial Spheres ſhould <lb></lb>ſtand ſtill, is collected from the command he gave at the ſame <lb></lb>time to the Moon, although that it had nothing to do in the <lb></lb>lengthening of the day; and under the injunction laid upon the 


<pb xlink:href="066/01/032.jpg" pagenum="457"></pb>Moon, we are to underſtand the Orbes of all the other Planets, <lb></lb>paſſed over in ſilence here, as alſo in all other places of the Sacred <lb></lb>Scriptures; the intention of which, was not to reach us the Aſtro­<lb></lb>nomical Sciences. </s>

<s>I ſuppoſe therefore, (if I be not deceived) <lb></lb>that it is very plain, that if we allow the <emph type="italics"></emph>Ptolemaick<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Syſteme, we <lb></lb>muſt of neceſſity interpret the words to ſome ſenſe different from <lb></lb>their ſtrict ſignification. </s>

<s>Which Interpretation (being admo­<lb></lb>niſhed by the moſt uſefull precepts of S. <emph type="italics"></emph>Auguſtine)<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> I will not <lb></lb>affirm to be of neceſſity this above-mentioned, ſince that ſome <lb></lb>other man may haply think of ſome other more proper, and more <lb></lb>agreeable Senſe.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>But now, if this ſame paſſage may be underſtood in the <emph type="italics"></emph>Coper­<lb></lb>nican<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Syſteme, to agree better with what we read in <emph type="italics"></emph>Joſhuah,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>with the help of another Obſervation by me newly ſhewen in <lb></lb>the Body of the Sun; I will propound it to conſideration, ſpeak­<lb></lb>ing alwaies with thoſe ſafe Reſerves; That I am not ſo affectio­<lb></lb>nate to my own inventions, as to prefer them before thoſe of <lb></lb>other men, and to believe that better and more agreeable to the <lb></lb>intention of the Sacred Volumes cannot be produced.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>Suppoſing therefore in the firſt place, that in the Miracle of <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Joſhuah,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> the whole Syſteme of the Celeſtial Revolutions ſtood <lb></lb>ſtill, according to the judgment of the afore-named Authors: <lb></lb>And this is the rather to be admitted, to the end, that by the <lb></lb>ſtaying of one alone, all the Conſtitutions might not be con­<lb></lb>founded, and a great diſorder needleſly introduced in the whole <lb></lb>courſe of Nature: I come in the ſecond place to conſider how the <lb></lb>Solar Body, although ſtable in one conſtant place, doth neverthe­<lb></lb>leſs revolve in it ſelf, making an entire Converſion in the ſpace <lb></lb>of a Month, or thereabouts; as I conceive I have ſolidly demon­<lb></lb>ſtrated in my Letters <emph type="italics"></emph>Delle Machie Solari<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>: Which motion we <lb></lb>ſenſibly ſee to be in the upper part of its Globe, inclined to­<lb></lb>wards the South; and thence towards the lower part, to encline <lb></lb>towards the North, juſt in the ſame manner as all the other Orbs <lb></lb>of the Planets do. </s>

<s>Thirdly, If we reſpect the Nobility of the <lb></lb>Sun, and his being the Fountain of Light, by which, (as I neceſ­<lb></lb>ſarily demonſtrate) not onely the Moon and Earth, but all the <lb></lb>other Planets (all in the ſame manner dark of themſelves) become <lb></lb>illuminated; I conceive that it will be no unlogicall Illation to ſay, <lb></lb>That it, as the Grand Miniſter of Nature, and in a certain ſenſe <lb></lb>the Soul and Heart of the World, infuſeth into the other Bodies <lb></lb>which environ it; not onely Light, but Motion alſo; by revol­<lb></lb>ving ^{*} in it ſelf: So that in the ſame manner that the motion of <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg857"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>the Heart of an Animal ceaſing, all the other motions of its <lb></lb>Members would ceaſe; ſo, the Converſion of the Sun ceaſing, <lb></lb>the Converſions of all the Planets would ſtand ſtill. </s>

<s>And though 


<pb xlink:href="066/01/033.jpg" pagenum="458"></pb>I could produce the teſtimonies of many grave Writers to prove <lb></lb>the admirable power and influence of the Sun, I will content my <lb></lb>ſelf with one ſole place of Holy <emph type="italics"></emph>Dioniſius Areopagita<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> in his Book <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg858"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>de Divinis Nominibus<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; who thus writes of the Sun: ^{(*)} <emph type="italics"></emph>His Light <lb></lb>gathereth and converts all things to himſelf, which are ſeen, <lb></lb>moved, illuſtrated, wax hot, and (in a word) thoſe things which <lb></lb>are preſerved by his ſplendor: Wherefore the Sun is called<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> <foreign lang="grc">Hλιος,</foreign><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>for that he collecteth and gathereth together all things diſperſed.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>And a little after of the Sun again he adds; ^{(*)} <emph type="italics"></emph>If this Sun which <lb></lb>wo ſee, as touching the Eſſences and Qualities of thoſe things <lb></lb>which fall within our Senſe, being very many and different; yet <lb></lb>if he who is one, and equally beſtowes his Light, doth renew, <lb></lb>nouriſh, defend, perfect, divide, conjoyn, cheriſh, make fruitfull,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg859"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>encreaſe, change, fix, produce, move, and faſhion all living crea­<lb></lb>tures: And every thing in this Vniverſe at his Pleaſure, is par­<lb></lb>taker of one and the ſame Sun; and the cauſes of many things <lb></lb>which participate of him, are equally auticipated in him: Certain­<lb></lb>ly by greater reaſon<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; &amp;c. </s>

<s>The Sun therefore being the Foun­<lb></lb>tain of Light and, Principle of Motion, God intending, that at <lb></lb>the Command of <emph type="italics"></emph>Joſhua,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> all the Worlds Syſteme, ſhould con­<lb></lb>tinue many hours in the ſame ſtate, it ſufficeth to make the Sun <lb></lb>ſtand ſtill, upon whoſe ſtay (all the other Converſions ceaſing) <lb></lb>the Earth, the Moon, the Sun did abide in the ſame Conſtitution <lb></lb>as before, as likewiſe all the other Planets: Nor in all that time <lb></lb>did the Day decline towards Night, but it was miraculouſly pro­<lb></lb>longed: And in this manner, upon the ſtanding ſtill of the Sun, <lb></lb>without altering, or in the leaſt diſturbing the other Aſpects and <lb></lb>mutual Poſitions of the Stars, the Day might be lengthned on <lb></lb>Earth; which exactly agreeth with the Litteral ſenſe of the Sacred <lb></lb>Text.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg857"></margin.target>* <emph type="italics"></emph>i. </s>

<s>i.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> On its own <lb></lb>Axis.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg858"></margin.target>(*) <emph type="italics"></emph>Lux ejus colli­<lb></lb>git, convertitque ad <lb></lb>ſe omnia, quæ vi­<lb></lb>dentur, quæ mo­<lb></lb>ventur, quæ illu­<lb></lb>ſtrantur, quæ ca­<lb></lb>leſcunt, &amp; uno no­<lb></lb>mine ea, quæ ab e­<lb></lb>jus ſplendore cen­<lb></lb>tinentur. </s>

<s>Itaque <lb></lb>Sol <foreign lang="grc">Hλι&lt;34&gt;</foreign> dicitur, <lb></lb>quod omnia con­<lb></lb>greger, colligatque <lb></lb>diſperſa.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg859"></margin.target>(*) <emph type="italics"></emph>Si enim <lb></lb>Sol hic quem vi­<lb></lb>domus, eorum quæ <lb></lb>ſub ſenſum ca­<lb></lb>dunt, eſſentias &amp; <lb></lb>qualitates, quæ que <lb></lb>muliæ ſint ac diſ­<lb></lb>ſimiles, tamen ipſe <lb></lb>qui unus eſt, æqua­<lb></lb>literque lumen <lb></lb>fundit, renovat, a­<lb></lb>lit, tuetur, perficit, <lb></lb>dividit, conjungit, <lb></lb>fovet, fæcunda red­<lb></lb>dit, auget, mutat, <lb></lb>firmat, edit, movet, <lb></lb><expan abbr="vitaliaq;">vitaliaque</expan> facit om­<lb></lb>nia: &amp; <expan abbr="unaquæq;">unaquæque</expan> <lb></lb>res hujus univer­<lb></lb>ſitatis, pro cæptu <lb></lb>ſuo, unius atque e­<lb></lb>juſdem Solis eſt <lb></lb>particeps, cauſæſ­<lb></lb>que multorum, <lb></lb>quæ participant, in <lb></lb>ſe æquabiliter an­<lb></lb>ticipatas habet, <lb></lb>certe majori ratio­<lb></lb>ne,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> &amp;c.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>But that of which, if I be not miſtaken, we are to make no <lb></lb>ſmall account, is, That by help of this <emph type="italics"></emph>Copernican<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Hypotheſis, <lb></lb>we have the Litteral, apert, and Natural Senſe of another parti­<lb></lb>cular that we read of in the ſame Miracle; which is, That the <lb></lb>Sun ſtood ſtill <emph type="italics"></emph>in Medio Cæli<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>: Upon which paſſage grave Divines <lb></lb>raiſe many queſtions, in regard it ſeemeth very probable, That <lb></lb>when <emph type="italics"></emph>Joſhuah<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> deſired the lengthning of the Day, the Sun was <lb></lb>near ſetting, and not in the Meridian; for if it had been in the <lb></lb>Meridian, it being then about the Summer <emph type="italics"></emph>Solſtice,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and con­<lb></lb>ſequently the dayes being at the longeſt, it doth not ſeem likely <lb></lb>that it was neceſſary to pray for the lengthning of the day, to <lb></lb>proſecute Victory in a Battail, the ſpace of ſeven hours and more, <lb></lb>which remained to Night, being ſufficient for that purpoſe. <lb></lb></s>

<s>Upon which Grave Divines have been induced to think that the <lb></lb>Sun was near ſetting: And ſo the words themſelves ſeem to 


<pb xlink:href="066/01/034.jpg" pagenum="459"></pb>ſound, ſaying, <emph type="italics"></emph>Ne movearis Sol, ne movearis.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> For if it had <lb></lb>been in the Meridian, either it had been needleſs to have asked <lb></lb>a Miracle, or it would have been ſufficient to have onely praid <lb></lb>for ſome retardment. </s>

<s>Of this opinion is <emph type="italics"></emph>Cajetan,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> to which ſub­<lb></lb>ſcribeth <emph type="italics"></emph>Magaglianes,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> confirming it by ſaying, that <emph type="italics"></emph>Joſhua<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> had <lb></lb>that very day done ſo many other things before his commanding <lb></lb>the Sun, as were not poſſibly to be diſpatch&#039;t in half a day. <lb></lb></s>

<s>Whereupon they are forced to read the Words <emph type="italics"></emph>in Medio Cœli<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>(to confeſs the truth) with a little harſhneſs, ſaying that they <lb></lb>import no more than this: <emph type="italics"></emph>That the Sun ſtood ſtill, being in our <lb></lb>Hemiſphere, that is, above the Horizon.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> But (if I do not erre) <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg860"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>we ſhall avoid that and all other harſh expoſitions, if according <lb></lb>to the <emph type="italics"></emph>Copernican<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Syſteme we place the Sun in the midſt, that <lb></lb>is, in the Centre of the Cœleſtial Orbes, and of the Planetary <lb></lb>Converſions, as it is moſt requiſite to do. </s>

<s>For ſuppoſing any <lb></lb>hour of the day (either Noon, or any other, as you ſhall pleaſe <lb></lb>neerer to the Evening) the Day was lengthened, and all the <lb></lb>Cœleſtial Revolutions ſtayed by the Suns ſtanding ſtill, <emph type="italics"></emph>In the <lb></lb>midſt,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> that is, <emph type="italics"></emph>in the Centre of Heaven,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> where it reſides: A <lb></lb>Senſe ſo much the more accomodate to the Letter (beſides what <lb></lb>hath been ſaid already) in that, if the Text had deſired to have <lb></lb>affirmed the Suns Reſt to have been cauſed at Noon-day, the <lb></lb>proper expreſſion of it had been to ſay, <emph type="italics"></emph>It ſtood ſtill at Noon-day,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>or <emph type="italics"></emph>in the Meridian Circle,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and not <emph type="italics"></emph>in the midſt of Heaven<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>: In <lb></lb>regard that the true and only <emph type="italics"></emph>Middle<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> of a Spherical Body (as is <lb></lb>Heaven) is the Centre.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg860"></margin.target><emph type="italics"></emph>Solem ſtetiſſe, <lb></lb>dum adhuc in He­<lb></lb>miſpharto noſtro, <lb></lb>ſupra ſcilicet Ho­<lb></lb>rizontem exiſteret.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>Cajetan <emph type="italics"></emph>in loce.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>Again, as to other places of Scripture, which ſeem contrary to <lb></lb>this poſition, I do not doubt but that if it were acknowledged <lb></lb>for True and Demonſtrated thoſe very Divines who ſo long as <lb></lb>they repute it falſe, hold thoſe places incapable of Expoſitions <lb></lb>that agree with it would finde ſuch Interpretations for them, as <lb></lb>ſhould very well ſuit therewith; and eſpecially if to the know­<lb></lb>ledge of Divine Learning they would but adde ſome knowledge <lb></lb>of the Aſtronomical Sciences: And as at preſent, whilſt they <lb></lb>deem it falſe they think they meet in Scripture only with ſuch <lb></lb>places as make againſt it, if they ſhall but once have entertained <lb></lb>another conceipt thereof, they would meet peradventure as many <lb></lb>others that accord with it, and haply would judge, that the Holy <lb></lb>Church doth very appoſitly teach, That God placed the Sun in <lb></lb>the Centre of Heaven, and that thereupon by revolving it in it <lb></lb>ſelf, after the manner of a Wheel, He contributed the ordinary <lb></lb>Courſes to the Moon and other Erratick Stars, whilſt that ſhe <lb></lb>Sings,</s></p><p type="main">

<s><emph type="italics"></emph>Cœli Deus ſanctiſſime,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s><emph type="italics"></emph>Qui lucidum Centrum Poli,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p>


<pb xlink:href="066/01/035.jpg" pagenum="460"></pb><p type="main">

<s><emph type="italics"></emph>Candore ping is igneo,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s><emph type="italics"></emph>Augens decoro lumine,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s><emph type="italics"></emph>Quarto die, qui flammeam<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s><emph type="italics"></emph>Solis rotam conſtituens<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s><emph type="italics"></emph>Lunœ miniſtras ordinem,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s><emph type="italics"></emph>Vagoſque curſus Syderum.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>They might ſay, that the Name of <emph type="italics"></emph>Firmament<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> very well a­<lb></lb>greeth, <emph type="italics"></emph>ad literam,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> to the Starry Sphere, and to all that which <lb></lb>is above the Planetary Converſions; which according to this Hy­<lb></lb>potheſis is altogether <emph type="italics"></emph>firme<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and immoveable. <emph type="italics"></emph>Ad litteram<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> (the <lb></lb>Earth moving circularly) they might underſtand its <emph type="italics"></emph>Poles,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>where it&#039;s ſaid, <emph type="italics"></emph>Nec dum Terram fecerat, &amp; flumina, &amp;<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Cardi­<lb></lb>nes <emph type="italics"></emph>Orbis Terrœ,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Which <emph type="italics"></emph>Cardines<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> or ^{*} <emph type="italics"></emph>liinges<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> ſeem to be aſcribed <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg861"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>to the Earth in vain, if it be not to turn upon them.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg861"></margin.target>* Or Poles.</s></p><p type="head">

<s><emph type="italics"></emph>FINIS.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p>


<pb xlink:href="066/01/036.jpg" pagenum="461"></pb><p type="head">

<s>AN <lb></lb>ABSTRACT <lb></lb>OF THE <lb></lb>Learned Treatiſe <lb></lb>OF <lb></lb>JOHANNIS KEPL<emph type="italics"></emph>E<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>RUS, <lb></lb>The Emperours <emph type="italics"></emph>Mathematician<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>: <lb></lb>ENTITULED <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>His Introduction upon<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> MARS:</s></p><p type="main">

<s>It muſt be confeſſed, that there are very <lb></lb>many who are devoted to Holineſſe, <lb></lb>that diſſent from the Judgment of <emph type="italics"></emph>Co­<lb></lb>pernicus,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> fearing to give the Lye to the <lb></lb>Holy Ghoſt ſpeaking in the Scriptures, <lb></lb>if they ſhould ſay, that the Earth mo­<lb></lb>veth, and the Sun ſtands ſtill. </s>

<s>But let <lb></lb>ſuch conſider, that ſince we judge of ve­<lb></lb>ry many, and thoſe the moſt principal <lb></lb>things by the Senſe of Seeing, it is impoſſible that we ſhould ali­<lb></lb>enate our Speech from this Senſe of our Eyes. </s>

<s>Therefore many <lb></lb>things daily occur, of which we ſpeak according to the Senſe of <lb></lb>Sight, when as we certainly know that the things themſelves are <lb></lb>otherwiſe. </s>

<s>An Example whereof we have in that Verſe of <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Virgil<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>;</s></p><p type="head">

<s><emph type="italics"></emph>Provehimur portu, Terrœque urbeſque recedunt.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>So when we come forth of the narrow ſtraight of ſome Val­<lb></lb>ley, we ſay that a large Field diſcovereth it ſelf. </s>

<s>So Chriſt to <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Peter, Duc in altum<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; [Lanch forth into the Deep, or on high,] <lb></lb>as if the Sea were higher than its Shores; For ſo it ſeemeth to <lb></lb>the Eye, but the Opticks ſhew the cauſe of this fallacy. </s>

<s>Yet <lb></lb>Chriſt uſeth the moſt received Speech, although it proceed from <lb></lb>this deluſion of the Eyes. </s>

<s>Thus we conceive of the Riſing and 


<pb xlink:href="066/01/037.jpg" pagenum="462"></pb>Setting of the Stars, that is to ſay, of their Aſcenſion and Deſ­<lb></lb>cenſion; when at the ſame time that we affirm the Sun riſeth, o­<lb></lb>thers ſay, that it goeth down. </s>

<s>See my <emph type="italics"></emph>Optices Aſtronomiœ, cap.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>10. <emph type="italics"></emph>fol.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 327 So in like manner, the <emph type="italics"></emph>Ptolomaicks<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> affirm, that the <lb></lb>Planets <emph type="italics"></emph>ſtand ſtill,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> when for ſome dayes together they ſeem to be <lb></lb>fixed, although they believe them at that very time to be moved <lb></lb>in a direct line, either downwards to, or upwards from the <lb></lb>Earth. </s>

<s>Thus the Writers of all Nations uſe the word <emph type="italics"></emph>Solſtiti­<lb></lb>um,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and yet they deny that the Sun doth really ſtand ſtill. </s>

<s>Like­<lb></lb>wiſe there will never any man be ſo devoted to <emph type="italics"></emph>Copernicus,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> but <lb></lb>he will ſay, the Sun entereth into <emph type="italics"></emph>Cancer<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>Leo,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> although he <lb></lb>granteth that the Earth enters <emph type="italics"></emph>Capricorn<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> or <emph type="italics"></emph>Aquarius<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>: And ſo <lb></lb>in other caſes of the like nature. </s>

<s>But now the Sacred Scriptures, <lb></lb>ſpeaking to men of vulgar matters (in which they were not in­<lb></lb>tended to inſtruct men) after the manner of men, that ſo they <lb></lb>might be underſtood by men, do uſe ſuch Expreſſions as are <lb></lb>granted by all, thereby to inſinuate other things more Myſterious <lb></lb>and Divine. </s>

<s>What wonder is it then, if the Scripture ſpeaks <lb></lb>according to mans apprehenſion, at ſuch time when the Truth <lb></lb>of things doth diſſent from the Conception that all men, whe­<lb></lb>ther Learned or Unlearned have of them? </s>

<s>Who knows not <lb></lb>that it is a Poetical alluſion, <emph type="italics"></emph>Pſal.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 19. where, whilſt under the ſi­<lb></lb>militude of the Sun, the Courſe of the Goſpel, as alſo the Pere­<lb></lb>grination of our Lord Chriſt in this World, undertaken for our <lb></lb>ſakes, is deſcribed, <emph type="italics"></emph>The Sun<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> is ſaid <emph type="italics"></emph>to come forth of his Taberna­<lb></lb>cle<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> of the Horizon, <emph type="italics"></emph>as a Bridegroom out of his Chamber, re­<lb></lb>joycing as a Giant to run a Race<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>? </s>

<s>Which <emph type="italics"></emph>Virgil<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> thus imitates;</s></p><p type="head">

<s><emph type="italics"></emph>Tithono croceum linquens Auror a cubile<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>:</s></p><p type="main">

<s>For the firſt Poets were amongſt the Jews. </s>

<s>The Pſalmiſt knew that <lb></lb>the Sun went not forth of the Horizon, as out of its Tabernacle, <lb></lb>&amp; yet it ſeemeth to the Eye ſo to do: Nor did he believe, that the <lb></lb>Sun moved, for that it appeared to his ſight ſo to do. </s>

<s>And yet he <lb></lb>ſaith both, for that both were ſo to his ſeeming. </s>

<s>Neither is it <lb></lb>to be adjudged falſe in either Senſe: for the perception of the <lb></lb>Eyes hath its verity, fit for the more ſecret purpoſe of the Pſal­<lb></lb>miſt in ſhadowing forth the current paſſage oſ the Goſpel, as <lb></lb>alſo the Peregrination of the Son of God. <emph type="italics"></emph>Joſhua<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> likewiſe <lb></lb>mentioneth the Vallies on or in, which the Sun and Moon mo­<lb></lb>ved, for that they appeared to him at <emph type="italics"></emph>Jordan<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> ſo to do: And yet <lb></lb>both theſe Pen-men may obtain their ends. <emph type="italics"></emph>David,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> (and with <lb></lb>him <emph type="italics"></emph>Syracides<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>) the magnificence of God being made known, <lb></lb>which cauſed theſe things to be in this manner repreſented to <lb></lb>ſight, or otherwiſe, the myſtical meaning, by means of theſe <lb></lb>Viſibles being diſcerned: And <emph type="italics"></emph>Joſhua,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> in that the Sun, as to his 


<pb xlink:href="066/01/038.jpg" pagenum="463"></pb>Senſe of Seeing, ſtaid a whole day in the midſt of Heaven, where­<lb></lb>as at the ſame time to others it lay hid under the Earth. </s>

<s>But in­<lb></lb>cogitant perſons onely look upon the contrariety of the words, <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>The Sun ſtood ſtill,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> that is, <emph type="italics"></emph>The Earth ſtood ſtill<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; not conſidering <lb></lb>that this contradiction is confined within the limits of the Op­<lb></lb>ticks and Aſtronomy: For which cauſe it is not outwardly ex­<lb></lb>poſed to the notice and uſe of men: Nor will they underſtand <lb></lb>that the onely thing <emph type="italics"></emph>Joſhuah<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> prayed for, was that the Mountains <lb></lb>might not intercept the Sun from him; which requeſt he expreſ­<lb></lb>ſed in words, that ſuited with his Ocular Senſe: Beſides it had <lb></lb>been very unſeaſonable at that time to think of Aſtronomy, or <lb></lb>the Errours in Sight; for if any one ſhould have told him that <lb></lb>the Sun could not really move upon the Valley of <emph type="italics"></emph>Ajalon,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>, but <lb></lb>onely in relation to Senſe, would not <emph type="italics"></emph>Joſhuah<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> have replyed, that <lb></lb>his deſire was that the day might be prolonged, ſo it were by <lb></lb>any means whatſoever? </s>

<s>In like manner would he have anſwered <lb></lb>if any one had ſtarted a queſtion about the Suns Mobility, and <lb></lb>the Earths Motion. </s>

<s>But God eaſily underſtood by <emph type="italics"></emph>Joſhuahs<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>words what he asked for, and by arreſting the Earths Motion, <lb></lb>made the Sun in his apprehenſion ſeem to ſtand ſtill. </s>

<s>For the <lb></lb>ſumm of <emph type="italics"></emph>Joſhuahs<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Prayer amounts to no more but this, that it <lb></lb>might thus appear to him, let it in the mean time <emph type="italics"></emph>be what it <lb></lb>would<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> of it ſelf. </s>

<s>For that its ſo ſeeming, was not in vain and <lb></lb>ridiculous, but accompanied with the deſired effect. </s>

<s>But read <lb></lb>the tenth <emph type="italics"></emph>Chap.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> of my <emph type="italics"></emph>Book,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> that treats of <emph type="italics"></emph>the Optick part of A­<lb></lb>ſtronomy,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> where thou ſhalt finde the Reaſons why the Sun doth <lb></lb>in this manner ſeem to all mens thinking to be moved, and not <lb></lb>the Earth; as namely, becauſe the Sun appeareth ſmall; and the <lb></lb>Earth bigg. </s>

<s>Again, the Motion of the Sun is not diſcerned by <lb></lb>the eye, by reaſon of his ſeeming tardity, but by ratiocina­<lb></lb>tion onely; in that after ſome time it varieth not its proximity to <lb></lb>ſuch and ſuch Mountains. </s>

<s>Therefore it is impoſſible that Rea­<lb></lb>ſon, unleſs it be firſt inſtructed, ſhould frame to it ſelf any other <lb></lb>apprehenſion, than that the Earth with Heavens Arch placed <lb></lb>over it, is as it were a great Houſe, in which, being immoveable, <lb></lb>the Sun like a Bird flying in the Air, paſſeth in ſo ſmall a Species <lb></lb>out of one Climate into another. </s>

<s>Which imagination of all <lb></lb>Man-kinde being thus, gave the firſt line in the Sacred Leaves: <lb></lb>^{*} <emph type="italics"></emph>In the beginning<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> (ſaith <emph type="italics"></emph>Moſes) God created the Heaven and the <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg862"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>Earth<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; for that theſe two are moſt obvious to the eye. </s>

<s>As if <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Moſes<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> ſhould have ſaid thus to Man; This whole Mundane Fa­<lb></lb>brick which thou ſeeſt, lucid above, and dark, and of a vaſt ex­<lb></lb>tent beneath, wherein thou haſt thy being, and with which thou <lb></lb>art covered, was created by God.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg862"></margin.target>* Gen. <emph type="italics"></emph>Chv. </s>

<s>1. <lb></lb>v.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 1.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>In another place Man is queſtioned; <emph type="italics"></emph>Whether he can finde out<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>


<pb xlink:href="066/01/039.jpg" pagenum="464"></pb><emph type="italics"></emph>the height of Heaven above, or depth of the Earth beneath<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>: for <lb></lb>that each of them appeareth to men of ordinary capacity, to have <lb></lb>equally an infinite extent. </s>

<s>And yet no man that is in his right <lb></lb>mind will by theſe words circumſcribe and bound the diligence <lb></lb>of Aſtronomers, whether in demonſtrating the moſt contemptible <lb></lb>Minuity of the Earth, in compariſon of Heaven, or in ſearching <lb></lb>out Aſtronomical <emph type="italics"></emph>Diſtances<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>: Since thoſe words ſpeak not of the <lb></lb>Rational, but real Dimention; which to a Humane Body, <lb></lb>whilſt confin&#039;d to the Earth, and breathing in the open Air, is al­<lb></lb>together impoſſible. </s>

<s>Read the whole 38. Chapter of <emph type="italics"></emph>Job,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <lb></lb>compare it with thoſe Points which are diſputed in Aſtronomy, <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg863"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>and Phyſiologie. </s>

<s>If any one do alledge from <emph type="italics"></emph>Pſal.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 24. That ^{*} <emph type="italics"></emph>The <lb></lb>Earth is founded upon the Seas,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> to the end that he may thence <lb></lb>infer ſome new Principle in Philoſophy, abſurd to hear; as, That <lb></lb>the Earth doth float upon the Waters; may it not truly be told <lb></lb>him, That he ought not to meddle with the Holy Spirit, nor to <lb></lb>bring him with contempt into the School of Phyſiologie. <lb></lb></s>

<s>For the Pſalmiſt in that place means nothing elſe but <lb></lb>that which men fore-know, and daily ſee by experience; namely, <lb></lb>That the Earth (being lifted up after the ſeparation of the Wa­<lb></lb>ters) doth ſwim between the Grand Oceans, and float about the <lb></lb>Sea. </s>

<s>Nor is it ſtrange that the expreſſion ſhould be the ſame <lb></lb>where the <emph type="italics"></emph>Iſraelites<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> ſing, ^{*} <emph type="italics"></emph>That they ſate on the River of Baby­<lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg864"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>lon<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; that is, <emph type="italics"></emph>by<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> the River ſide. </s>

<s>or on the Banks of <emph type="italics"></emph>Euphrates<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Tygris.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg863"></margin.target>* Pſal. </s>

<s>24. 2.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg864"></margin.target>Pſal. </s>

<s>137. 1.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>If any one receive this Reading without ſcruple, why not the <lb></lb>other; that ſo in thoſe ſame Texts which are wont to be alledged <lb></lb>againſt the Motion of the Earth, we may in like manner turn our <lb></lb>eyes from Natural Philoſophy, to the ſcope and intent of Scri­<lb></lb>pture. <emph type="italics"></emph>One Generation paſſeth away,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> (ſaith <emph type="italics"></emph>Eccleſiaſtes) and a­<lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg865"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>nother Generation cometh: But the Earth abideth for ever.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> ^{*} As <lb></lb>if <emph type="italics"></emph>Solomon<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> did here diſpute with Aſtronomers, and not rather put <lb></lb>men in minde of their Mutability; when as the Earth, Mankindes <lb></lb>habitation, doth alwaies remain the ſame: The Suns Motion <lb></lb>doth continually return into what it was at firſt: The Wind is <lb></lb>acted in a Circle, and returns in the ſame manner: The Rivers <lb></lb>flow from their Fountains into the Sea, and return again from <lb></lb>thence unto their Fountains: To conclude, The Men of this <lb></lb>Age dying, others are born in their room; the Fable of Life is <lb></lb>ever the ſame; there is nothing new under the Sun. </s>

<s>Here is no <lb></lb>reference to any Phyſical Opinion. <foreign lang="grc"><gap></gap>ον<gap></gap>εσὶα</foreign> is Moral of a thing in it <lb></lb>ſelf manifeſt, and ſeen by the eyes of all, but little regarded: Tis <lb></lb>that therefore which <emph type="italics"></emph>Solomon<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> doth inculcate. </s>

<s>For who knows not <lb></lb>that the Earth is alwaies the ſame? </s>

<s>Who ſees not that the Sun <lb></lb>dothariſe from the Eaſt; That the Rivers continually run into 


<pb xlink:href="066/01/040.jpg" pagenum="465"></pb>the Sea; That the viciſſitudes of the Windes return into their <lb></lb>primitive State; That ſome men ſucceed others? </s>

<s>But who con­<lb></lb>ſidereth that the ſelf-ſame <emph type="italics"></emph>Scene<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> of Life is ever acting, by diffe­<lb></lb>rent perſons; and that nothing is <emph type="italics"></emph>new<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> in humane affairs? </s>

<s>There­<lb></lb>fore <emph type="italics"></emph>Solomon<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> inſtancing in thoſe things which all men ſee, doth <lb></lb>put men in minde of that which many thorowly know, but too <lb></lb>ſlightly conſider.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg865"></margin.target>* Chap. </s>

<s>1. v. </s>

<s>4, to <lb></lb>9.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>But the 104. <emph type="italics"></emph>Pſalm<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> is thought by ſome to contain a Diſcourſe <lb></lb>altogether Phyſical, in regard it onely concerns Natural Philoſo­<lb></lb>phy. </s>

<s>Now God is there ſaid, <emph type="italics"></emph>To have laid the Foundations of <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg866"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>the Earth, that it ſhould not be removed for ever.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> But here al­<lb></lb>ſo the Pſalmiſt is far from the Speculation of Phyſical Cauſes: <lb></lb>For he doth wholly acquieſce in the Greatneſſe of God, <lb></lb>who did all theſe things, and ſings an Hymne to God the <lb></lb>Maker of them, in which he runneth over the World in order, <lb></lb>as it appeared to his eyes. </s>

<s>And if you well conſider this <lb></lb>Pſalme, it is a Paraphraſe upon the ſix dayes work of the Crea­<lb></lb>tion: For as in it the three firſt dayes were ſpent in the Separa­<lb></lb>tion of Regions; the firſt of Light from the exteriour Dark­<lb></lb>neſs; the ſecond, of the Waters from the Waters, by the inter­<lb></lb>poſition of the Firm ament; the third, of the Sea from Land; <lb></lb>when alſo the Earth was cloathed with Herbage and Plants: <lb></lb>And the three laſt dayes were ſpent in the filling the Re­<lb></lb>gions thus diſtinguiſhed; the fourth, of Heaven; the <lb></lb>fifth, of the Seas and Aire; the fixth, of the Earth: So <lb></lb>here in this Pſalme there are ſo many diſtinct parts pro­<lb></lb>portionable to the Analogy of the ſix dayes Works. </s>

<s>For <lb></lb>in <emph type="italics"></emph>Verſe<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 2. he cloaths and covereth the Creator with Light <lb></lb>(the firſt of Creatures, and work of the firſt day) as with a <lb></lb>Garment. </s>

<s>The ſecond part beginneth at <emph type="italics"></emph>Verſe<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 3. and treats of <lb></lb>the Waters above the Heavens, the extent of Heaven and of Me­<lb></lb>teors (which the Pſalmiſt ſeemeth to intend by the Waters a­<lb></lb>bove) as namely of Clouds, Winds, Whirl-winds, Lightnings. <lb></lb></s>

<s>The third part begins at <emph type="italics"></emph>Verſe<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 6. and doth celebrate the Earth <lb></lb>as the foundation of all thoſe things which he here conſidereth. <lb></lb></s>

<s>For he referreth all things to the Earth, and to thoſe Animals <lb></lb>which inhabit it, for that in the judgment of Sight the two prin­<lb></lb>cipal parts of the World are Heaven and Earth. </s>

<s>He therefore <lb></lb>here obſerveth that the Earth after ſo many Ages hath not falte­<lb></lb>red, tired, or decayed; when as notwithſtanding no man hath <lb></lb>yet diſcovered upon what it is founded. </s>

<s>He goeth not about to <lb></lb>teach men what they do not know, but putteth them in minde <lb></lb>of what they neglect, to wit, the Greatneſſe and Power of God <lb></lb>in creating ſo huge a Maſs ſo firm and ſtedfaſt. </s>

<s>If an Aſtrono­<lb></lb>mer ſhould teach that the Earth is placed among the Planets, he 


<pb xlink:href="066/01/041.jpg" pagenum="466"></pb>overthroweth not what the Pſalmiſt here ſaith, nor doth he con­<lb></lb>tradict Common Experience; for it is true notwithſtanding, <lb></lb>that the Earth, the Structure of God its Architect, doth not de­<lb></lb>cay (as our Buildings are wont to do) by age, or conſume by <lb></lb>wormes, nor ſway and leane to this or that ſide; that the Seats <lb></lb>and Neſts of Living Creatures are not moleſted; that the <lb></lb>Mountains and Shores ſtand immoveable againſt the violence of <lb></lb>the Winds and Waves, as they were at the beginning. </s>

<s>But the <lb></lb>Pſalmiſt addeth a moſt Elegant Hypotheſis of the Separation of <lb></lb>the Waters from the Continent or Main-land, and adorns it <lb></lb>with the production of Fountains, and the benefits that Springs <lb></lb>and Rocks exhibit to Birds and Beaſts. </s>

<s>Nor doth he omit the <lb></lb>apparelling the Earths Surface, mentioned by <emph type="italics"></emph>Moſes<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> amongſt the <lb></lb>works of the third Day, but more ſublimely deſcribeth it in his <lb></lb>Caſe in expreſſions infuſed from Divine Inſpiration; and flouri­<lb></lb>ſheth out the commemoration of the many commodities which <lb></lb>redound from that Exornation for the Nouriſhment and Com­<lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg867"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>fort of Man, and ^{*} Covert of Beaſts. </s>

<s>The fourth part begins <lb></lb>at <emph type="italics"></emph>Verſe<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 20. celebrating the fourth dayes work, <emph type="italics"></emph>viz.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> The Sun <lb></lb>and Moon, but chiefly the commodiouſneſſe of thoſe things, <lb></lb>which in their Seaſons befall to all Living Creatures and to Man; <lb></lb>this being the ſubject matter of his Diſcourſe: So that it plain­<lb></lb>ly appeareth he acted not the part of an Aſtronomer. </s>

<s>For if he <lb></lb>had, he would not then have omitted to mention the five Planets, <lb></lb>than whoſe moiton nothing is more admirable, nothing more ex­<lb></lb>cellent, nothing that can more evidently ſet forth the Wiſdome <lb></lb>of the Creator amongſt the Learned. </s>

<s>The fifth part begins, <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Verſe<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 25. with the fifth Dayes work. </s>

<s>And it ſtores the Seas with <lb></lb>Fiſhes, and covers them with Ships. </s>

<s>The ſixth part is more ob­<lb></lb>ſcurely hinted at, <emph type="italics"></emph>Verſe<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 28. and alludeth to the Land-Creatures <lb></lb>that were created the ſixth day. </s>

<s>And laſtly, he declareth the <lb></lb>goodneſſe of God in general, who daily createth and preſerveth <lb></lb>all things? </s>

<s>So that whatever he ſaid of the World is in relation <lb></lb>to Living Creatures; He ſpeaks of nothing but what is granted <lb></lb>on all hands; for that it was his intent to extol things known, <lb></lb>and not to dive into hidden matters, but to invite men to con­<lb></lb>template the Benefits that redouud unto them from the works of <lb></lb>each of theſe dayes.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg866"></margin.target>Pſal. </s>

<s>104. v. </s>

<s>5.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg867"></margin.target>* Shelter.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>And I do alſo beſeech my Reader, not forgetting the Divine <lb></lb>Goodneſſe conferred on Mankind; the conſideration of which <lb></lb>the Pſalmiſt doth chiefly urge, that when he returneth from the <lb></lb>Temple, and enters into the School of <emph type="italics"></emph>Aſtronomy,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> he would <lb></lb>with me praiſe and admire the Wiſdome and Greatneſſe of the <lb></lb>Creator, which I diſcover to him by a more narrow explication <lb></lb>of the Worlds Form, the Diſquiſition of Cauſes, and Detection 


<pb xlink:href="066/01/042.jpg" pagenum="467"></pb>of the Errours of Sight: And ſo he will not onely extoll the <lb></lb>Bounty of God in the preſervation of Living Creatures of all <lb></lb>kindes, and eſtabliſhment of the Earth; but even in its Motion <lb></lb>alſo, which is ſo ſtrange, ſo admirable, he will acknowledge the <lb></lb>Wiſdome of the Creator. </s>

<s>But he who is ſo ſtupid as not to <lb></lb>comprehend the Science of <emph type="italics"></emph>Aſtronomy,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> or ſo weak and ſcrupu­<lb></lb>lous as to think it an offence of Piety to adhere to <emph type="italics"></emph>Copernicus,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>him I adviſe, that leaving the Study of <emph type="italics"></emph>Aſtronomy,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and cenſuring <lb></lb>the opinions of Philoſophers at pleaſure, he betake himſelf to <lb></lb>his own concerns, and that deſiſting from further purſuit of theſe <lb></lb>intricate Studies, he keep at home and manure his own Ground; <lb></lb>and with thoſe Eyes wherewith alone he ſeeth, being eleva­<lb></lb>ted towards this to be admired Heaven, let him pour forth his <lb></lb>whole heart in thanks and praiſes to God the Creator; and aſ­<lb></lb>ſure himſelf that he ſhall therein perform as much Worſhip to <lb></lb>God, as the <emph type="italics"></emph>Aſtronomer,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> on whom God hath beſtowed this Gift, <lb></lb>that though he ſeeth more clearly with the Eye of his Under­<lb></lb>ſtanding; yet whatever he hath attained to, he is both able and <lb></lb>willing to extoll his God above it.</s></p><p type="main">

<s>And thus much concerning the Authority of Sacred Scripture. <lb></lb></s>

<s>Now as touching the opinions of the Saints about theſe Natural <lb></lb>Points. </s>

<s>I anſwer in one word, That in Theology the weight of <lb></lb>Authority, but in Philoſophy the weight of Reaſon is to be con­<lb></lb>ſidered. </s>

<s>Therefore Sacred was <emph type="italics"></emph>Lactantius,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> who denyed the <lb></lb>Earths rotundity; Sacred was <emph type="italics"></emph>Auguſtine,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> who granted the Earth <lb></lb>to be round, but denyed the <emph type="italics"></emph>Antipodes<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>; Sacred is the ^{*}Liturgy of <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg868"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>our Moderns, who admit the ſmallneſſe of the Earth, but deny <lb></lb>its Motion: But to me more ſacred than all theſe is Truth, who <lb></lb>with reſpect to the Doctors of the Church, do demonſtrate <lb></lb>from Philoſophy that the Earth is both round, circumhabited by <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Antipodes,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> of a moſt contemptible ſmalneſſe, and in a word, <lb></lb>that it is ranked amongſt the Planets.</s></p>


<pb xlink:href="066/01/043.jpg" pagenum="468"></pb><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg868"></margin.target>* Officium</s></p><p type="head">

<s>AN <lb></lb>ABSTRACT <lb></lb>OF <lb></lb>Some paſſages in the Commentaries of <lb></lb>Didacus à Stunica, <lb></lb>OF <lb></lb>SALAMANCA <lb></lb>Upon <emph type="italics"></emph>JOB:<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="head">

<s>The Toledo Edition, Printed by <emph type="italics"></emph>JOHN RODERICK, <lb></lb>Anno<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 1584, in <emph type="italics"></emph>Quarto,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Pag. </s>

<s>205. &amp; <emph type="italics"></emph><expan abbr="ſeqq.">ſeqque</expan><emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> on <lb></lb>theſe Words, Chap. </s>

<s>9. Verſe 6.</s></p><p type="head">

<s><emph type="italics"></emph>Who ſhaketh the Earth out of her place, and the Pil­<lb></lb>lars thereof Tremble.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="main">

<s>The Sacred Pen-man here ſets down another ef­<lb></lb>fect whereby God ſheweth his Ahnighty Po­<lb></lb>wer, joyned with infinite Wiſdom. </s>

<s>Which <lb></lb>place, though it muſt be confeſſed very diffi­<lb></lb>cult to underſtand, might be greatly cleared <lb></lb>by the Opinion of the <emph type="italics"></emph>Pythagorians,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> who <lb></lb>hold the Earth to be moved of its own Na­<lb></lb>ture, and that the Motion of the Stars can no other way be aſcer­<lb></lb>tained, they being ſo extreamly different in tardity and velocity. <lb></lb></s>

<s>Of which judgement was <emph type="italics"></emph>Philolaus,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and <emph type="italics"></emph>Heraclides Ponticus,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> as <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Plutarch<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> relateth in his Book <emph type="italics"></emph>De Placitis Philoſophorum<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end>: Who <lb></lb>were followed by <emph type="italics"></emph>Numa Pompilius,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and, which I more regard, <lb></lb>The Divine <emph type="italics"></emph>Plato<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> in his old age; inſomuch that he affirmed that <lb></lb>it was moſt abſurd to think otherwiſe, as the ſame <emph type="italics"></emph>Plutarch<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> tells <lb></lb>us in his ^{*} <emph type="italics"></emph>Numa.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> And <emph type="italics"></emph>Hypocrates<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> in his Book <emph type="italics"></emph>De Flatibus,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg869"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>calleth the Air <foreign lang="grc">τησγησὀχἠμα,</foreign> <emph type="italics"></emph>i. </s>

<s>e.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> The Earths Chariot. </s>

<s>But in this 


<pb xlink:href="066/01/044.jpg" pagenum="469"></pb>our Age, <emph type="italics"></emph>Copernicus<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> doth demonſtrate the courſes of the Pla­<lb></lb>nets to be according to this Opinion. </s>

<s>Nor is it to be doubted <lb></lb>but that the Planets Places may be more exactly and certainly <lb></lb>aſſigned by his Doctrine, than by <emph type="italics"></emph>Ptolomies<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> Great Almogeſt of <lb></lb>Syſteme, or the Opinions of any others. </s>

<s>For its manifeſt, that <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Ptolomy<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> could never deſcribe either the Motion of the Equi­<lb></lb>noxes, or aſſign the certain and poſitive beginning of the Year:<lb></lb>the which he ingeniouſly confeſſeth in <emph type="italics"></emph>Lih.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 3. <emph type="italics"></emph>De Almageſt. </s>

<s>Mag­<lb></lb>num. </s>

<s>Ch.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> 2. and which he leaveth to be diſcovered in after times <lb></lb>by thoſe Aſtronomers, who coming into the World much later <lb></lb>than he, might be able to invent ſome way to make more accurate <lb></lb>obſervations. </s>

<s>And although the ^{*} <emph type="italics"></emph>Alphonſines &amp; Thebith Ben Core<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg870"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>have attempted to explain them; yet it appeareth that they have <lb></lb>done as much as nothing. </s>

<s>For the Poſitions of the <emph type="italics"></emph>Alphonſines<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>diſagree amongſt themſelves, as <emph type="italics"></emph>Ricius<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> proveth. </s>

<s>And although <lb></lb>the Reaſon of <emph type="italics"></emph>Thebith<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> be more acute, and that thereby he de­<lb></lb>termined the certain beginning of the year, (being that which <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Ptolomy<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> ſought for) yet it is now clear, that the Progreſſions of <lb></lb>the Equinoxes are much longer than he conceived they could be. <lb></lb></s>

<s>Moreover, the Sun is found to be much nearer to us than it was <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg871"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>held to be in times paſt, by above fourty thouſand ^{*} <emph type="italics"></emph>Stadia,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> or <lb></lb>furlongs. </s>

<s>The Cauſe and Reaſon of whoſe Motion, neither <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Ptolomy<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> nor any other Aſtrologers could ever comprehend: And <lb></lb>yet the Reaſons of theſe things are moſt plainly explained and <lb></lb>demonſtrated by <emph type="italics"></emph>Copernicus<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> from the Motion of the Earth, with <lb></lb>which he ſheweth that all the other <emph type="italics"></emph>Phœnomena<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> of the Univerſe <lb></lb>do more aptly accord. </s>

<s>Which opinion of his is not in the leaſt <lb></lb>contradicted by what <emph type="italics"></emph>Solomon<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> ſaith in ^{*} <emph type="italics"></emph>Eccleſiaſtes: But the <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg872"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>Earth abideth for ever.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> For that Text ſignifieth no more but <lb></lb>this, That although the ſucceſſion of Ages, and generations of <lb></lb>Men on Earth, be various; yet the Earth it ſelf is ſtill one and <lb></lb>the ſame, and continueth without any ſenſible alteration; For <lb></lb>the words run thus: <emph type="italics"></emph>One Generation paſſeth away, and another <lb></lb>Generation cometh; but the Earth abideth for ever.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> So that it <lb></lb>hath no coherence with its Context, (as Philoſophers ſhew) if it <lb></lb><arrow.to.target n="marg873"></arrow.to.target><lb></lb>be expounded to ſpeak of the Earths immobility. </s>

<s>And al­<lb></lb>though in this Chapter <emph type="italics"></emph>Eccleſiaſtes,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> and in many others, Holy <lb></lb>Writ aſcribes Motion to the Sun, which <emph type="italics"></emph>Copernicus<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> will have to <lb></lb>ſtand fixed in the Centre of the Univerſe; yet it makes nothing <lb></lb>againſt his Poſition. </s>

<s>For the Motion that belongs to the Earth, <lb></lb>is by way of ſpeech aſſigned to the Sun, even by <emph type="italics"></emph>Copernicus<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> him­<lb></lb>ſelf, and thoſe who are his followers, ſo that the Revolution of <lb></lb>the Earth is often by them phraſed, The Revolution of the Sun. <lb></lb></s>

<s>To conclude, No place can be produced out of Holy Scripture, <lb></lb>which ſo clearly ſpeaks the Earths Immobility, as this doth its 


<pb xlink:href="066/01/045.jpg" pagenum="470"></pb>Mobility. </s>

<s>Therefore this Text, of which we have ſpoken, is ea­<lb></lb>ſily reconciled to this Opinion. </s>

<s>And to ſet forth the Wonder­<lb></lb>ful power and Wiſdome of God, who can indue and actuate the <lb></lb>Frame of the Whole Earth (it being of a monſtrous weight by <lb></lb>Nature) with Motion, this our Divine pen-man addeth; <emph type="italics"></emph>And <lb></lb>the pillars thereof tremble:<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> As if he would teach us, from the <lb></lb>Doctrine laid down, that it is moved from its Foundations.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg869"></margin.target>* <emph type="italics"></emph>In vita ejus.<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end></s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg870"></margin.target>* Followers of <lb></lb>that Learned <lb></lb>Kings Hypothe­<lb></lb>ſis.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg871"></margin.target>* That is 5000 <lb></lb>miles; eight of <lb></lb>theſe making an <lb></lb><emph type="italics"></emph>Italian,<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end> or <emph type="italics"></emph>Engliſh<emph.end type="italics"></emph.end><lb></lb>mile of a 1000. <lb></lb>paces, every pace <lb></lb>containing 5. <lb></lb>Feet.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg872"></margin.target>* Chap. </s>

<s>1. v. </s>

<s>4.</s></p><p type="margin">

<s><margin.target id="marg873"></margin.target>The Motion of <lb></lb>the Earth, not a­<lb></lb>gainſt Scripture.</s></p> 		</chap>		</body>		<back></back>	</text></archimedes>